<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.4.1" ident="GROBID" when="2016-02-29T12:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text xml:lang="en"><p>Comet C/2013 A1 (siding Spring) will experience a high velocity encounter with Mars on October 19, 2014 at a distance of 135,<measure type="value"><num>000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ± <measure type="value"><num>5000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> from the planet center. We present a comprehensive analysis of the trajectory of both the comet nucleus and the dust tail. The nucleus of C/2013 A1 cannot impact on Mars even in the case of unexpectedly large nongravitational perturbations. Furthermore, we compute the required ejection velocities for the dust grains of the tail to reach Mars as a function of particle radius and density and heliocentric distance of the ejection. A comparison between our results and the most current modeling of the ejection velocities suggests that impacts are possible only for millimeter to centimeter size particles released more than <measure type="value"><num>13</num></measure> au from the Sun. However, this level of cometary activity that far from the Sun is considered extremely unlikely. The arrival time of these particles spans a 20-minute time interval centered at October 19, 2014 at 20:09 TDB, i.e., around the time that Mars crosses the orbital plane of C/2013 A1. Ejection velocities larger than currently estimated by a factor &gt; 2 would allow impacts for smaller particles ejected as close as 3 au from the Sun. These particles would reach Mars from <measure type="interval"><num atMost="43">43</num> to <num atMost="130">130</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> after the nominal close approach epoch of the purely gravitational trajectory of the nucleus.</p><p>Comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) was discovered on January 2013 at the Siding Spring observatory (McNaught et al. 2013). Shortly after discovery it was clear that C/2013 A1 was headed – 2 – for a close encounter with Mars on October 19, 2014. C/2013 A1 is on a near parabolic retrograde orbit and will have a high relative velocity with respect to Mars of about <measure type="value"><num>56</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km/s">km/s</measure></measure> during the close approach. If the comet has no significant nongravitational perturbations, the trajectory of the nucleus consistent with the present set of astrometric observations rules out an impact on Mars. However, comet orbits are generally difficult to predict. As the comet gets closer to the Sun cometary activity can result in significant nongravitational perturbations (Marsden et al. 1973) that in turn can lead to significant deviations from the purely gravitational ( " ballistic " ) trajectory. In the case of C/2013 A1, cometary activity was already visible in the discovery observations, when the comet was at more than 7 au from the Sun.</p><p>Beside the effect of nongravitational perturbations, dust grains in the tail of the comet could reach Mars and possibly damage spacecrafts orbiting Mars, i.e., NASA's Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter , NASA's Mars Odyssey, ESA's Mars Express, NASA's MAVEN, and ISRO's MOM. Vaubaillon et al. (2014) and Moorhead et al. (2014) show that dust grains can reach Mars if they are ejected from the nucleus with a sufficiently high velocity. The modeling of the ejection velocity is in continuous evolution. As the comet gets closer to the inner solar system we have additional observation that provide constraints to the ejection velocities of dust grains. In particular, by making use of observations from HST/WFC3, Swift/UVOT, and WISE, Farnham et al. (2014) and Tricarico et al. (2014) find ejection velocities lower than those derived by Vaubaillon et al. (2014) and Moorhead et al. (2014), thus significantly reducing the hazard due to dust grains in the comet tail.</p><p>In this paper we study the trajectory of C/2013 A1's nucleus, including the contribution of nongravitational perturbations. We also present an analysis of the required ejection velocities for the dust grains to reach Mars. This analysis can be used as a reference as the understanding and the modeling of the dust grain ejection velocities evolve.</p><p>We examined all available ground-based optical astrometry (Right Ascension and Declination angular pairs) as of March 15, 2014. To remove biased contributions from individual observatories we conservatively excluded from the orbital fit batches of more than <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> observations in the same night with mean residual larger than <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="?" unit="′′">′′</measure></measure> , and batches of <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> or <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> observations showing mean residual larger than 1 ′′ . We also adopted the outlier rejection scheme of Carpino et al. (2003) with χ rej = 2. To the remaining 597 optical observations we applied the standard one arcsecond data-weights used for comet astrometry.Figure 1 shows the residuals of C/2013 A1's observations against our new orbit solution (JPL solution 46). [Figure 1 about here.] – 3 – Our force model included solar and planetary perturbations based on JPL's planetary ephemerides DE431 1 , the gravitational attraction due to the 16 most massive bodies in the main asteroid belt, and the Sun relativistic term. No significant nongravitational forces were evident in the astrometric data and so the corresponding JPL orbit solution is ballistic, identified as number 46.Table 1 contains the orbital elements of the computed solution.</p><p>[Table 1Table 2 provides information on the close encounter between C/2013 A1 and Mars. C/2013 A1 passes through the orbital plane of Mars <measure type="value"><num>69</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="minutes">minutes</measure></measure> before the close approach epoch, while Mars passes through the orbital plane of C/2013 A1 <measure type="value"><num>99</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="minutes">minutes</measure></measure> after the close approach. The Minimum Orbit Intersection Distance (MOID) is the minimum distance between the orbit of the comet and the orbit of Mars (MOID, Gronchi et al. 2007). The MOID points on the two orbits are not on the line of nodes. Mars arrives at the minimum distance point <measure type="value"><num>101</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> after the close approach epoch, while C/2013 A1 arrives at the minimum distance point <measure type="value"><num>70</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> before the close approach, which means that the comet is <measure type="value"><num>171</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> early for the minimum distance encounter. [Table 2 about here.] A standard tool to analyze planetary encounters is the b-plane (Kizner 1961; Valsecchi et al. 2003 ), defined as the plane passing through the center of mass of the planet and normal to the inbound hyperbolic approach asymptote. The coordinates on the b-plane described in Valsecchi et al. (2003) are oriented such that the projected heliocentric velocity of the planet is along −ζ. Therefore , ζ varies with the time of arrival, i.e., a positive ζ means that the comet arrives late at the encounter while a negative ζ means that the comet arrives early. On the other hand ξ is related to the MOID. The b-plane is used on a daily basis for asteroid close approaches to the Earth and computing the corresponding impact probabilities (Milani et al. 2005).Figure 2 shows the projection of the 3σ uncertainty ellipsoid of JPL solution 46 on the b-plane. The projection of the velocity of Mars on this plane is oriented as −ζ, while the Mars-to-Sun vector projection is on the left side, at a counterclockwise angle of 186 @BULLET with respect to the ξ axis. The negative ζ coordinate of the center of the ellipse corresponds to the <measure type="value"><num>171</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> time shift between Mars and C/2013 A1. [Figure 2 about here.] 3.</p><p>Comet trajectories can be significantly affected by nongravitational perturbations due to cometary outgassing. We use the Marsden et al. (1973) comet nongravitational model:</p><p>where g(r) is a known function of the heliocentric distance r, and A i are free parameters that give the nongravitational acceleration at 1 au in the radial-transverse-normal reference frame defined byˆrbyˆbyˆr, ˆ t, ˆ n.</p><p>The observational dataset available for C/2013 A1 does not allow us to estimate the nongravitational parameters A i . Still, nongravitational accelerations could cause statistically significant deviations at the close approach epoch. To deal with this problem, we analyzed the properties of known nongravitational parameters in the comet catalog.Figure 3 shows the known A 1 and A 2 in the catalog. A 3 values have an order of magnitude similar to that of A 2 .Figure 4 contains scatter plots of nongravitational parameters showing the correlation between these parameters. For comets with an orbit similar to that of C/2013 A1, i.e., with large orbital period (&gt; 60 yr) and high eccentricity (&gt; <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num></measure>), values of A 1 are on average ∼ 10 −8 au/d 2 , but they can be as large as ∼ 10 −6 . A 2 and A 3 are generally one order of magnitude smaller, i.e., on average they are ∼ 10 −9 au/d 2 but can be as large as ∼ 10 −7 au/d 2 . We can see that A 1 is generally one order of magnitude larger than A 2 and A 3 , which makes sense since the radial component is usually the largest for nongravitational accelerations. [ According to the properties of the comet population we considered three different scenarios as described inTable 3: the ballistic scenario corresponds to JPL solution 46; the " reference " scenario uses typical values of the nongravitational parameters; the " wide " scenario assumes extreme values of the nongravitational parameters. We selected the A 1 uncertainty so that its range would span from 0 au/d 2 to twice the nominal value at 3σ. For A 2 and A 3 the nominal value is 0 au/d 2 since these components can be either positive or negative, while A 1 can only be positive.</p><p>[Table 3Figure 5 shows the position difference among the three scenarios compared to the position uncertainty of the ballistic solution. The available observations put a strong constraint the trajectory of C/2013 A1 for heliocentric distances between 3 au and 8 au from the Sun. Outside of this distance range we have no observations and therefore the uncertainty increases. Because of – 5 – the fast decay of the g(r) function in Eq. (1) the contribution of nongravitational accelerations for large heliocentric distances is well within the uncertainty and so the trajectory of C/2013 A1 in the past is not significantly affected. It is worth pointing out that the function g(r) represents water sublimation while distant activity is not driven by water and therefore may be inaccurate a large distances. However, for such large distances the position uncertainty is large enough to make this possible discrepancy irrelevant. Finally, for smaller heliocentric distances nongravitational perturbations become relevant and can affect the predictions for the Mars encounter, especially in the wide scenario.</p><p>[Figure 5 about here.] For the three different scenarios,Table 4 gives the close approach information whileFig. <measure type="value"><num>6</num></measure> shows the projection of the orbital uncertainties on the b-plane. The ballistic and reference solutions provide very similar predictions, from which we conclude that nongravitational perturbations will not significantly affect the orbit unless they are larger than expected. The wide solution, which has to be regarded as an extreme case, produces a significantly different nominal prediction and quite a large uncertainty. In all three scenarios, the nominal close approach distance is more than 130,<measure type="value"><num>000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> from Mars and therefore there is no chance of an impact between the nucleus of C/2013 A1 and Mars.</p><p>[Table 4</p><p>The predictions and the uncertainty provided so far are based on the optical astrometry available as of March 15, 2014. At the time of submission of this paper (April 2014), comet C/2013 A1 was difficult to observe because of the low solar elongation. On June 18, 2014 the solar elongation becomes larger than <measure type="value"><num>60</num></measure> @BULLET and we therefore expect observations to resume, which will help in further constraining the trajectory of C/2013 A1. To quantify the effect of future optical astrometry, we simulated geocentric optical observations, with two observations every five nights. – 6 –Figure 8 shows the 3σ uncertainty evolution for the close approach epoch. The ballistic and reference scenarios have a current uncertainty of <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> and this uncertainty decreases to less than <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num> <measure type="?" unit="min right">min right</measure></measure> before the close approach. For the wide scenario the uncertainty goes from <measure type="value"><num>45</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> down to <measure type="value"><num>1–2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>. [Figure 8 about here.] As already discussed in Sec. 3, the wide solution produces predictions significantly different from the ballistic and reference solutions. Thus, at some point observations will reveal whether or not the nongravitational perturbations are behaving as in the wide scenario.Figure 9 shows the uncertainty in A 1 when estimated from the orbital fit as a function of time. When this uncertainty becomes smaller than a given value of A 1 , the observation dataset reveals such A 1 value if it is real. By comparing the uncertainty evolution to the nominal values of A 1 assumed for the different scenarios, we can see that large nongravitational accelerations to the level assumed in the wide scenario are detectable about <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="days">days</measure></measure> before the close encounter. On the other hand, the reference solution becomes distinct from the ballistic solution only a couple of weeks before the encounter. [Figure 9 about here.] Some skilled observers are capable of gathering comet observations even for solar elongations smaller than 60 @BULLET . Therefore, we also simulated observations using 40 @BULLET as a lower threshold for the solar elongation, which makes it possible to collect new observations for C/2013 A1 starting on May 7, 2014. However, the improvement in the uncertainties discussed above is a factor of 1.3 or less and is therefore not relevant.</p><p>Though an impact the nucleus of C/2013 A1 on Mars is ruled out, there is a chance that dust particles in the tail could reach Mars and some of the orbiting spacecrafts. Due to their small size, the motion of dust particles is strongly affected by solar radiation pressure. It is therefore to use the β parameter (Burns et al. 1979), i.e., the non-dimensional number corresponding to the ratio between solar radiation pressure and solar gravity. In terms of physical properties, β is proportional to the area-to-mass ratio and inversely proportional to both the density and to the radius of the particle:</p><p>where a is the particle radius in µm, ρ is the density in g/cc, and Q is the solar radiation pressure efficiency coefficient.</p><p>– 7 – For each ejected particle, the location on the b-plane for the Mars encounter is determined by the β parameter, the heliocentric distance r at which the particle is ejected (or the ejection epoch), and the ejection velocity ∆v.Figure 10 shows the typical behavior using as an example β = <measure type="value"><num>0.01</num></measure> and ∆v = |∆v| = <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m/s</measure></measure>. For each given β we have a curve on the b-plane corresponding to zero ejection velocity. This curve can be parameterized by the heliocentric distance at which the ejection takes place. Finally, the ejection velocity ∆v yields dispersion around the curve: the larger the ∆v the wider the dispersion.</p><p>The ejection velocity depends on the particle size and density, as well as the heliocentric distance at which the particle is ejected (Whipple 1951). Since cometary activity is very hard to predict, modeling the ejection velocities is a complicated task and is subject to continuous updates as additional observations are available. Therefore, we decided to adopt a different approach: for given ejection distance r and β parameter we computed the minimum ∆v required to reach Mars. In mathematical terms we look for the tridimensional ∆v that is a minimum point of ∆v 2 = |∆v| 2 under the constraint that the particle reaches Mars, i.e., (ξ, ζ)(r, β, ∆v) = (0, 0). This problem is a typical example of finding the minima of a function subject to equality constraints. Thus, we can solve this problem by means of the Lagrange multipliers, i.e., the ∆v we are looking for must satisfy the following system of equations:</p><p>where λ 1 and λ 2 are free parameters. To solve this system, we first tested the linearity of (ξ, ζ) in ∆v and then linearized system (3) around ∆v = 0, thus obtaining the following linear system:</p><p>To compute the required ∆v, we followed these steps:</p><p>@BULLET We sampled β in log-scale from <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="?" unit="−6">−6</measure></measure> to 1 and r from 1.</p><p>@BULLET For each couple (r, β) we computed the b-plane coordinates (ξ, ζ) obtained without ejection velocity as well as a finite difference approximation of the (ξ, ζ) partials with respect to ∆v; @BULLET We solved system (4). We scaled the resulting ∆v to account for the size of Mars and the 3σ uncertainty of the particle projection on the b-plane. For this analysis we used the ballistic solution as reference trajectory.</p><p>– 8 –Figure 11 shows the required ∆v needed to reach Mars as a function of the heliocentric distance at which the ejection takes place for different values of β. On the right side of the plot the required velocities are almost the same. This behavior makes sense as the closer we get to Mars the less time is available for solar radiation pressure to affect the trajectory. Therefore, the required ejection velocity is almost independent of the particle size and density. For β = <measure type="value"><num>1.43 × 10</num></measure> −4 we can see that the required velocity goes to zero for heliocentric distances around 22.5 au. The reason for this is that the curve on the b-plane defined by this particular value of β passes through the center of Mars. Thus, if ejected at the right distance, i.e., 22.5 au, the particle reaches Mars under the action of solar radiation pressure, with no ejection velocity at all. It is also worth noticing that the β = <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num> <measure type="?" unit="curve">curve</measure></measure> does not go all the way back to 30 au because, for such a high β, solar radiation pressure is extremely strong and the particle does not even experience the close encounter with Mars if ejected too far in advance. [Figure 11 about here.] The results obtained so far can be used to assess the possibility that particles of a given size could reach Mars for a given ejection velocity model. For instance, the best fit for the ejection velocity according to Farnham As shown inFig. 12, we can scale the required velocity to β = 1 and make a comparison to the velocity given by (5). We can see that, according to this ejection velocity model, impacts are possible only for particles with β ∼ <measure type="value"><num>2 × 10</num></measure> −4 or smaller ejected at more than ∼ 16 au from the Sun. – 9 – We conclude that impacts are possible only in one of these two unlikely cases: @BULLET millimeter to centimeter dust grains are ejected from the nucleus more than <measure type="value"><num>13</num></measure> au from the Sun; @BULLET the ejection velocities are larger than current estimates by a factor &gt; 2. To analyze the risk posed by dust grains in the tail, we computed the required ejection velocities as a function of the heliocentric distance at which the particle is ejected and the particle's β parameter, i.e., the ratio between solar radiation pressure and solar gravity. By comparing our results to the most updated modeling of dust grain ejection velocities, impacts are possible only for β of the order of 10 −4 , which, for a density of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="?" unit="g/cc">g/cc</measure></measure>, corresponds to millimeter to centimeter particles. However, the particles have to be ejected at more than 13 au, which is generally considered unlikely. See Kelley et al. (2014) As the comet gets closer to the inner solar system, new observations will be available and will allow better constraints on the dust grain ejection velocity profile. Our analysis can be used as a reference to quickly figure out what particles can reach Mars and the heliocentric distance at – 10 – which they would have to have been ejected. In the unlikely case that future astrometry reveals unexpectedly large nongravitational perturbations, the required velocity to reach Mars for particles ejected within 2 au from the Sun can change and the presented analysis will need to be refined.Figures 1 Scatter plot of the astrometric residuals in Right Ascension and Declination with respect to JPL solution 46. Crosses correspond to rejected observations, while dots correspond to the observations included in the fit.</p><p>2 Projection of the 3σ uncertainty of JPL solution 46 on the October 2014 b-plane. The nominal prediction for the b-plane coordinates is (ξ, ζ) = (−27, <measure type="list"><num>445</num></measure>, −132, 407) km. The dashed line represents the projection of the orbit of C/2013 A1 on the bplane . The minimum distance between the orbits of Mars and C/2013 A1 is ∼27,<measure type="value"><num>400</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>.</p><p>3 Estimated nongravitational parameters A 1 and A 2 for the comets in the catalog. A 2 is reported in absolute value. Circles correspond to comets with a period larger than 60 yr or an eccentricity larger than <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num></measure>. Crosses are for all other comets. The dashed line corresponds to the total magnitude of C/2013 A1.</p><p>4 Scatter plots for nongravitational parameters A 1 , A 2 , and A 3 . A 2 and A 3 are reported in absolute value. Circles correspond to comets with a period larger than 60 yr or an eccentricity larger than 0.9. Crosses are for all other comets.</p><p><measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="?" unit="Magnitude">Magnitude</measure></measure> of the position difference between the reference and ballistic solutions, and between the wide and ballistic solutions, as a function of heliocentric distance. The dashed line is the semimajor axis of the 1σ uncertainty ellipsoid of the ballistic solution.</p><p>6 Projection on the b-plane of C/2013 A1 3σ uncertainty according to different scenarios for nongravitational perturbations. The ballistic and reference solutions are almost indistinguishable.</p><p>9 Expected evolution of the A 1 uncertainty (1σ).</p><p>10 Projection on the b-plane of particles ejected with ∆v = <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m/s</measure></measure> and for β = <measure type="value"><num>0.01</num></measure>. The solid line represents the position of the particles with no ∆v.</p><p>11 For different values of β, required ∆v to reach Mars as a function of the heliocentric distance at which the ejection takes place.</p><p>– 13 – 12 Required ∆v to reach Mars multiplied by (1/β) 0.6 . The dashed line corresponds to ∆v = <measure type="value"><num>418</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m/s</measure></measure> β 0.6 (1 au /r) 1.5 . Impacts are possible only for particles ejected more than 16 au from the Sun and with β ∼ 2 × 10 −4 or smaller.</p><p>13 Required ∆v to reach Mars multiplied by (<measure type="value"><num>5.7</num><measure type="?" unit="×10">×10</measure></measure> −4 /β) 0.5 . The lower dashed line corresponds to ∆v = <measure type="value"><num>1.3</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m/s</measure></measure> (β/<measure type="value"><num>5.7 × 10</num></measure> −4 ) <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num></measure> (5 au /r) 1 . In this case impacts are possible for particles ejected more than <measure type="value"><num>13</num></measure> au from the Sun and β ∼ <measure type="value"><num>2 × 10</num></measure> −4 or smaller. The upper dashed line corresponds to ∆v = <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m/s</measure></measure> (β/<measure type="value"><num>5.7 × 10</num></measure> −4 ) <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num></measure> (5 au /r) 1 . In this case impacts are possible also for β = <measure type="value"><num>0.001</num></measure> and particles ejected as close as ∼ 3 au from the Sun.</p><p>– – 27 – List of Tables 1 J2000 heliocentric ecliptic orbital parameters of JPL orbit solution 46. Numbers in parentheses indicate the 1σ formal uncertainties of the corresponding (last two) digits in the parameter value.</p><p>2 Close approach data for JPL orbit solution 46.</p><p>3 A priori values and 3σ uncertainties of nongravitational parameters for the three scenarios.</p><p>shows the b-plane coordinates, the semimajor axis of the 3σ uncertainty projected on the b-plane, and the time of closest approach.</p><p>– 28 – – 29 – – 30 –</p><p><measure /><measure /><measure /><measure />Ballistic 0 ± 0 0 ± 0 0 ± 0 Reference (1 ± 1) × 10 −8 (0 ± 2) × 10 −9 (0 ± 2) <measure type="value"><num>× 10</num></measure><measure /><measure /><measure /> −9 Wide (1 ± 1) × 10 −6 (0 ± 2) × 10 −7 (0 ± 2) × 10 −7</p><p>Part of this research was conducted at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology , under a contract with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p><p>Copyright 2014, California Institute of Technology.</p></text></tei>