<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.1" ident="GROBID" when="2016-02-29T12:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
        <p>We present WMAP <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> observations of bright sources which are often used as calibrators at microwave frequencies. <measure type="value"><num>Ten</num></measure> objects are studied in <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> frequency bands (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="23">23</num>-<num atMost="94">94</num><measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>): the outer planets (Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune) and <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> fixed celestial sources (Cas A, Tau A, Cyg A, 3C274 and 3C58). The <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> analysis of Jupiter provides temperatures which are within 1&#x3C3; of the previously published WMAP <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> values, with slightly tighter constraints on variability with orbital phase (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">0.4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), and limits (but no detections) on linear polarization. Observed temperatures for both Mars and Saturn vary significantly with viewing geometry. Scaling factors are provided which, when multiplied by the Wright Mars thermal model predictions at <measure type="value"><num>350</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>, reproduce WMAP seasonally averaged observations of Mars within &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. An empirical model is described which fits brightness variations of Saturn due to geometrical effects and can be used to predict the WMAP observations to within <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. <measure type="value"><num>Seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean temperatures for Uranus and Neptune are also tabulated. Uncertainties in Uranus temperatures are <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>-<num atMost="4">4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in the <measure type="list"><num>41</num>, <num>61</num> and <num>94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> bands; the smallest uncertainty for Neptune is <measure type="value"><num>8</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the <measure type="value"><num>94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> band. Intriguingly, the spectrum of Uranus appears to show a dip at &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> of unidentified origin, although the feature is not of high statistical significance. Flux densities for the <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> selected fixed celestial sources are derived from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP sky maps, and are tabulated for Stokes I, Q and U, along with polarization fraction and position angle. Fractional uncertainties for the Stokes I fluxes are typically <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> to <num atMost="3">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. Source variability over the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> baseline is also estimated. Significant secular decrease is seen for Cas A and Tau A: our results are consistent with a frequency independent decrease of about <measure type="value"><num>0.53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year for Cas A and <measure type="value"><num>0.22</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year for Tau A. We present WMAP polarization data with uncertainties of a few percent for Tau A. Where appropriate, WMAP results are compared against previous findings in the literature. With an absolute calibration uncertainty of <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, WMAP data are a valuable asset for calibration work.</p>
		<p>The primary goal of the Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP) mission (Bennett et al. 2003b) is to study the cosmic microwave background (CMB) anisotropy, an undertaking that requires detailed knowledge of the instrumental angular response and noise, low systematic errors, and absolute calibration at sub-percent levels. These attributes make WMAP data of natural interest for ancillary studies of sky-based calibration objects. This paper focuses on WMAP observations of selected planets and fixed celestial objects which have been commonly used as calibrators in the microwave, either by ground-or space-based instruments. We provide fundamental measurements for these objects which will be of use not only for calibration purposes, but also other studies, such as planetary radiative transfer. A brief discussion of WMAP planetary radiometric data was made by Hill et al. (2009), with an earlier discussion of Jupiter temperatures by Page et al. (2003b). We extend these presentations to include WMAP observations of Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune over a <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> interval (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2001">2001</num> - <num atMost="2008">2008</num></measure>), in <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> microwave passbands ranging from &#x223C;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="23">23</num> to <num atMost="94">94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. We also select <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> bright celestial sources for more detailed study: Cas A, Cyg A, Tau A, 3C58 and 3C274. The WMAP project routinely compiles and distributes a point source catalog, which tabulates mean flux values in those same <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> passbands for bright sources off the Galactic plane (Wright et al. 2009; Hinshaw et al. 2007; Bennett et al. 2003a). However, <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> of the <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> objects discussed here (Cas A, Tau A, Cyg A, 3C 58) have low Galactic latitudes and are not included in the catalog. An earlier analysis of <measure type="value"><num>three</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP Tau A observations by Page et al. (2007) included both intensity and linear polarization measurements. This paper is one of a suite that details the analysis of WMAP <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data. An overview and description of data processing methods is provided by Jarosik et al. (2010). Gold et al. (2010 discuss Galactic foregrounds and techniques for removing them; an updated point source catalog is included. Analysis of CMB power spectra, best fit models and cosmological interpretations are presented by Larson et al. (2010) and Komatsu et al. (2010). Bennett et al. (2010 assess potential CMB " anomalies " relative to the best-fit <measure type="value"><num>six</num></measure> parameter &#x39B;CDM model.</p>
		<p>We organize this paper as follows: a short discussion of the WMAP instrument, plus data strengths and limitations for calibration source work, is provided in Section 2. The paper then divides into <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> major sections: analysis and results for planets (Section 3), and then Section 4 discusses analysis methods and results for the <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> bright celestial sources. A closing summary and conclusions follow in Section 5.</p>
		<p>Since its arrival at the Earth-Sun L2 point in <measure type="value"><date when="2001-08">2001 August</date></measure>, WMAP has produced a well-calibrated, multi-wavelength microwave survey of the entire sky with high sampling redundancy. Detailed descriptions of the mission profile and hardware can be found in Bennett et al. (2003b), Jarosik et al. (2003a) and Page et al. (2003b . To assist with clarifying the terminology and analysis methods presented in this paper, we describe the key features of the mission. WMAP observes the sky differentially: signal from the sky is simultaneously sampled in <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> different directions &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>140</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> apart and guided by <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> feed horn pairs into <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> receivers, referred to as differencing assemblies (DAs). The receivers cover <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> frequency bands (K, Ka, Q, V and W) with approximate center frequencies of &#x223C;<measure type="list"><num>23</num>, <num>33</num>, <num>41</num>, <num>61</num> and <num>94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, respectively. There is  <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> DA each for K and Ka bands (K1, Ka1),  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> DAs each for Q and V bands (Q1, Q2, V1, V2) and  <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> DAs (W1, W2, W3, W4) for W band. The frequency passbands are broad (&#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> fractional bandwidth), so that the exact frequency associated with an observation depends on the source spectrum. An orthomode transducer at the throat of each feed separates the sky signal into  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> orthogonal polarizations, allowing for reconstruction of both intensity and linear polarization signals. Angular resolution is moderate, ranging from roughly <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.2">0.2</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure> FWHM in W band to &#x223C; <num atMost="0.9">0.9</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> FWHM in K band.</p>
		<p>As a survey mission, WMAP is not commanded to point at specific targets, but executes a pole-to-pole sky-scanning strategy whose position on the ecliptic advances &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> eachday. To facilitate high redundancy in sky coverage, the spacecraft rotates about a spin axis, which also precesses. These combined motions produce a &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>45</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> wide scan swath which looks like a " belt " projected onto the sky, passing through the ecliptic poles. The scan swath returns to its original starting position on the ecliptic every year, after completing a full-sky survey with multiple observations per sky pixel. A primary strength of WMAP data is the calibration accuracy, with an absolute calibration error of <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (Jarosik et al. 2010). The absolute calibration is tied to knowledge of the CMB monopole and the spacecraft orbital velocity, and thus is independent of any reliance on previously established measurements of the sources under study. When coupled with WMAP's temporal and spectral coverage, the accurate flux measurements can provide a useful measure of intrinsic or geometrically induced source variability.</p>
        <p>There are some limiting factors, however. Temporal coverage of an object is constrained by the sky-scanning method. For a fixed source on the ecliptic, the WMAP scan strategy provides for <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> <measure type="value"><num>&#x223C; 45</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> windows a year in which to observe that source. These " observing seasons " are spaced roughly <measure type="value"><num>six </num><measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> apart. <!-- IGNORED While this geometry is modified somewhat for moving objects, only Mars is near enough that the orbital motion can extend a single viewing window from <measure type="value"><num>45</num><measure type="TIME" unit="days">days</measure></measure> to as much as <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="60">60</num> to <num atMost="90">90</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="days">days</measure></measure>.--> Since WMAP does not dwell on an object, but simply scans as it passes through the viewing swath, the number of observations for an individual object is also limited, which affects the signal-to-noise. Finally, WMAP's moderate spatial resolution, which allows us to characterize the planets as calibrators, also places detailed knowledge of structures such as Saturn's rings beyond instrument capabilities.</p>
		<p>There are <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> planets with sufficient signal-to-noise for analysis. Listed in order of decreasing signal-to-noise, these are Jupiter, Saturn, Mars, Uranus and Neptune. Since WMAP points away from the Sun, Earth and Moon in its L2 orbit, it cannot observe Mercury or Venus.</p>
        <p>Planets are excluded from the standard map-based products used for WMAP studies of the CMB and Galactic foregrounds. Observations of the planets must be extracted from the calibrated time-ordered data (TOD), and then undergo quality assessment and background removal before they can be analyzed. The extraction process gathers all observations from the TOD taken within <measure type="value"><num>several</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">degrees</measure></measure> of each planet and associates ancillary information such as position in the focal plane, attitude, planet viewing aspect and data quality flags with each observation. Observations whose sky positions lie within a <measure type="value"><num atMost="7">7</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> radius of other planets or which are of suspect quality are immediately rejected. In addition, observations are excluded from use if either beam of a DA feed-horn pair samples sky coordinates that fall within the boundaries of a spatial processing mask (Jarosik et al. 2007). The purpose of this " Galactic masking " is to mitigate background removal error by excluding observations located near strong-signal, high-gradient regions of the Galaxy. For those observations which survive these quality control steps, Galactic and CMB background signals are subtracted. The background signal subtracted from each observation is computed from the DA-appropriate <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean map (from which planetary data were excluded), using the value from the &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>6</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> wide pixel which is closest in spatial coordinates to those of the time-ordered observation.Table 1 lists the beginning and ending dates of the observing seasons for the <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> planets, i.e., when they are directly in the WMAP viewing swath. The " sky proximity " column in the Table indicate probable reasons for an unusually high rejection of observations within a season.</p>
		<p>As noted in Page et al. (2003b), planets are " point sources " for WMAP and thus the brightness temperature of a planet T p can be computed via the relation</p>
		<p>where T m is the peak response observed by WMAP, &#x2126; B is the main-beam solid angle, and &#x2126; p is the solid angle subtended by the planet. Changing distance between the planet and WMAP, plus changes in viewing aspect of an oblate planet, will cause &#x2126; p (and also T m ) to vary with time. We account for both geometrical effects and compute the brightness temperature relative to a fiducial solid angle &#x2126; ref p via the use of time-dependent geometrical scaling factors f d and f A . The factors f d and f A may be thought of as " distance correction " and " disk oblateness correction " factors:</p>
		<p>where A ref and d ref are a fixed fiducial disk area and distance, respectively. A proj disk is the projected area of the planetary disk, and d p the distance of the planet from WMAP, at the time of each observation. The projected area of the oblate disk is computed from A proj disk = &#x3C0;R proj pole R eq ,</p>
		<p>where R eq is the planet's equatorial radius and R proj pole is the projected polar radius given by</p>
		<p>where D W is the planetary latitude of WMAP ( " sub-WMAP latitude " ). The fiducial disk area A ref is simply A proj disk evaluated at D W of <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> . Planetary radii and north pole directions used to compute D W are adopted from Seidelmann et al. (2007); the polar and equatorial radii are listed inTable 2. Because WMAP is at L2, D W is not very dissimilar to that of the sub-Earth latitude, D e . As the brightest " point source " visible to WMAP, Jupiter is used to characterize the main beam response of the instrument. This process and analysis are described in detail in Hill et al. (2009), Jarosik et al. (2010), and Page et al. (2003b. The end result is a set of <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure>, azimuthally-symmetrized, one-dimensional radial beam profiles per DA. These radial beam profiles are then used to derive window functions used for CMB power spectrum deconvolution. Unlike the rest of the planetary temperatures in this section, the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean Jupiter temperatures are derived from the l = <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> value of the unnormalized window functions (which measures T m &#x2126; B ), coupled with the fiducial solid angle for Jupiter (Hill et al. 2009). For all other planetary analysis, brightness temperatures are derived using a template-fitting technique, which takes advantage of the high-quality beam information obtained from <measure type="value"><num>seven</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of Jupiter observations. After the processing steps described above, radial response profiles are produced for each planet, per DA, per season, by assigning observations to <measure type="value"><num>0.25</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">arcmin</measure></measure> bins increasing in angular distance from the planet's center. Each bin is assigned a mean value and an error based on instrument noise appropriate to the number of observations within the bin. The known radial beam response, based on <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> Jupiter data, is used as a fitting template to the seasonal radial profile for each DA. The fit returns T m for the planet. The brightness temperature is then derived from T m , the main-beam solid angle (Jarosik et al. 2010) and the reference solid angle for the planet as per the above equations. Errors include the formal error in the template coefficient and the propagated error in the beam solid angle.Figure 1 illustrates sample W1 radial profiles for a single observing season for each of the planets. The beam template is overplotted in red. As well as illustrating the technique, the figure is also a useful comparator of signal quality for each planet at W-band. Beam dilution increases with decreasing WMAP frequency: &#x2126; B is roughly <measure type="list"><num>24.6</num>, <num>14.4</num>, <num>8.98</num>, <num>4.20</num> and <num>2.10&#xD7;10 &#x2212;5</num> <measure type="SOLID_ANGLE" unit="sr">sr</measure></measure> for the K -W bands respectively (Jarosik et al. 2010). Tabulated brightness temperatures are appropriate for the Rayleigh-Jeans (RJ) approximation . Brightness temperatures provided in the Tables do not include the CMB contribution blocked by the planet but included in the background. As noted in the Tables, absolute brightness temperature is obtained by adding <measure type="list"><num>2.2</num>, <num>2.0</num>, <num>1.9</num>, <num>1.5</num> and <num>1.1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> in bands K, Ka, Q, V and W respectively (Page et al. 2003a ), since in the RJ approximation the CMB temperatures are frequency dependent. WMAP data points shown in comparison to measurements in the literature are converted to absolute brightness.</p>
		<p>Jupiter is a bright, accessible source whose whole-disk observations have long been used for calibration in the infrared through radio. Hill et al. (2009) recommend the use of WMAP radiometry of Jupiter as the preferred method of transferring the WMAP dipole calibration to another microwave instrument. For some instruments, Jupiter is unfortunately too bright, hence the interest in the use of fainter sources, and a set of observations which tie several common sources together on the same calibration scale. We continue to recommend Jupiter as the primary comparison calibrator, however.</p>
		<p><measure type="value"><num>Seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean brightness temperatures for Jupiter, computed as described in Section 3.1, are presented inTable 3. The <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure  type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> values differ from those of the <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure  type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> analysis of Hill et al. (2009) by 1&#x3C3; or less. The largest changes, which hover near 1&#x3C3;, are for K band and some of the W band DAs. A detailed explanation of these changes is given in Jarosik et al. (2010). Briefly, the change in K band results from improved background subtraction, and the W band changes are driven by small revisions to the beam solid angles , based on modeling. The <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> temperatures for W band show a decreased scatter between the individual DAs compared to <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure  type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure>, implying an improved calibration. The Jupiter temperature uncertainties listed in Table 3 are derived from the quadrature sum of the solid angle error and absolute calibration error of <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (Jarosik et al. 2010), as they were in the <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> analysis.</p>
		<p>Thermal emission from Jupiter's atmosphere is the primary signal source at wavelengths spanned by WMAP. As such, the observations are helpful for providing constraints on atmospheric models for Jupiter, which in turn could be used for calibration purposes. However, as noted by e.g., Gibson et al. (2005) , there is a fine point to consider: small contributions to the total observed intensity from a synchrotron component up to about <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> are expected. This non-thermal " decimetric emission " arises from charged particles trapped close to Jupiter by its strong magnetic field, and dominates the spectrum at frequencies less than about <measure type="interval"><num atMost="3">3</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. Estimates in the literature place the synchrotron contribution at <measure type="value"><num>23</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> near <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total intensity (de Pater &amp; Dunn 2003; Gibson et al. 2005), with a roughly T &#x223C; &#x3BD; &#x2212;2.4 frequency dependence (). However, the synchrotron emission is known to be variable on a wide range of time scales (Santos-Costa et al. 2009; de Pater &amp; Dunn 2003; de Pater et al. 2003; Miyoshi et al. 2000), and accurate removal is difficult. The WMAP <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean Jupiter brightness temperatures are graphically compared against those in the literature in Figure 2. Ground-based observational values are taken from compilations of Joiner &amp; Steffes (1991) and , along with individual observations from de Pater et al. (1982 Pater et al. ( , 2001), Greve et al. (1994) and Goldin et al. (1997). Estimates of the synchrotron emission have been removed from the observations in the figure by many, but not all, of the authors, and not necessarily to the same level. The WMAP observations are plotted " as observed " . As an estimate of the stability of Jupiter's emission with orbital phase over the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> interval, we extend the <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> analysis of Hill et al. (2009), in which temperatures for individual Jupiter observing seasons are computed and compared to the multi-year mean values. Individual seasonal temperatures are derived using the same beam-profile fitting technique which is used for the other planets (Section 3.1). We compute &#x2206;T /T as the mean deviation of all DAs from their <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure  type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean values, and include a 1&#x3C3; standard deviation as a measure of coherency. These results are listed inTable 4. Using the WMAP <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data, Hill et al. (2009) quote an upper limit of <measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> based on the largest deviation and scatter seen in the first <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> observing seasons, which occurred in season four. A careful examination of the entries in Table 4 with the largest deviations and/or scatter (observing seasons 4, 11, 12) shows that these particular instances have more to do with template fitting and background subtraction quality than with intrinsic source variability. The <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> seasons with high scatter (4, 12) are those in which the number of available observations for fitting has been significantly reduced because of foreground masking ( " % masked " in theTable), which increases the statistical error in the temperature determination. Season 11, with the highest &#x2206;T /T , is one in which Jupiter is nearly aligned with the Galactic center, but outside the processing mask. This is a region in which background subtraction is subject to greater error because of higher temperature gradients across the pixels in the map used for background removal. If one ignores these <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> entries, then an upper limit of <measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">0.4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> is more appropriate. We also searched for indications that K band might be more intrinsically variable than W band, because of the small synchrotron contribution. There is no indication of such a frequency dependence in the data, but the upper envelope here is about <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. The WMAP Jupiter observations were analyzed to determine if any linear polarization signal could be detected. A special version of the beam mapping software was run for Jupiter, in which the angle between the polarization axis of each radiometer and the planet's magnetic dipole was computed for each observation. For each differencing assembly, all observations within a tight radius of beam center were accumulated, corrected to peak beam response, background subtracted, loss imbalance corrected, separated by radiometer, and then used to solve for Stokes parameters I, Q, U and their errors. For a more complete description of the relevant equations, see Hinshaw et al. (2003) and Jarosik et al. (2007). Normalized Stokes parameters Q/I and U/I are reported inTable 5, along with their propagated errors and estimated linear polarization fraction, p lin = (Q/I) 2 + (U/I) 2 . No attempt has been made to correct for noise bias in either p lin or its reported error, which is simply the propagated error. The estimated signal-to-noise is low, with no significant detections in any differencing assembly. Linear polarization of the synchrotron emission at <measure type="list"><num>15</num> and <num>22</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> has been detected by de Pater &amp; Dunn (2003) using the Very Large Array (VLA). They were unable to obtain a synchrotron polarization fraction at <measure type="value"><num>22</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, but estimated <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> polarization based on the <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> observations, which implies roughly a <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> polarization fraction at K band using a combined thermal and non-thermal intensity. The WMAP results are consistent with this estimate, but do not provide any further constraint.</p>
		<p>Mars' value as a calibrator depends upon the accuracy to which its whole-disk brightness variations (both apparent and intrinsic) can be modeled. Much of the perceived variability from earth-orbit is attributable to geometrical factors: the apparent phase as seen by the observer and changes in solar irradiance as Mars' distance from the Sun varies in its elliptical orbit (Wright 1976). There are a number of additional complexities, however. The day/night cycle imparts a significant rotational modulation to the observed temperature as the surface heats and cools. In the infrared, variable atmospheric effects including molecular line absorption and dust storms can be of importance. Additionally, the Martian surface is itself far from homogenous, with polar ice-caps of changing extent and variations in albedo and thermal inertia on relatively small scales (Putzig &amp; Mellon 2007; Christensen et al. 2001). Planetary science studies notwithstanding, the astronomical community has most consistently referenced <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> basic models when calibrating to Mars: the " Wright model " (Wright 1976, Wright &amp; Odenwald 1980, Wright 2007) and the " Rudy model " (Rudy et al. 1987, Muhleman &amp; Berge 1991), both developed before the current level of detail available from orbiters such as Mars Global Surveyor (MGS). In the thermal emission regime (&#x3BB; <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>), the planet's brightness temperature can be computed to first order as re-emission of absorbed solar energy by a surface layer with a characteristic albedo, emissivity and thermal inertia (de Pater 1990). The Wright model uses this approach to predict thermal emission in the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>-<num atMost="350">350</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> range, with no positional variations of parameters such as albedo and thermal inertia. The Rudy model originates from VLA observations at <measure type="list"><num>2</num> and <num>6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure>, which sample further into the Martian subsurface. Concurrent measurements of the polarized flux are used to estimate radio reflectivities and absorption lengths as a function of planetary latitude , and brightness temperatures calculated via radiative transfer as a function of position on a longitude/latitude grid. Typical errors on T b quoted for the Wright model are <measure type="interval">&#xB1;<num type="range">5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, or about <measure type="interval">&#xB1;<num type="range">10K</num></measure>, and those for the Rudy model at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>-<num atMost="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. We have chosen in this paper to compare the WMAP observations against predictions from the Wright model, primarily because of its long history of use and readily available model code (Wright 2007), but also because the seasonal brightness temperatures quoted for WMAP are the resultant average over <measure type="value"><num>several</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure> of data, which means we are only sampling mean properties at best. We have modified the 2007 Wright model code in <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> ways: (1) JPL ephemeris positions are substituted for the lower precision formulae originally used; (2) an option is added to use WMAP spacecraft positions rather than those of the Earth; and (3) computations are extended out to WMAP frequencies. The first <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> changes are not critical to the analysis, as the combined modifications introduce at most at <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> difference from the original results. Typically the model predicts brightness temperatures at <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> which are a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">Kelvins</measure></measure> lower than those at <measure type="value"><num>350</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>, and the temperature spread between the extrema of the <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> WMAP frequencies is quite low, of order <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. Hill et al. (2009) presented the first <measure type="value"><num>five</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of WMAP Mars observations at <measure type="value"><num>94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. Here we extend the W-band observations to <measure type="value"><num>seven</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, and include the observations at the other <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> WMAP frequencies. Mean brightness temperatures for Mars at <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> frequencies and <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> WMAP observing seasons derived from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure  type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data are presented inTable 6 . After correcting to absolute brightness temperature and converting from Rayleigh- Jeans to Planck brightness temperature 1 , the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> seasonal W-band averages are shown in comparison to the Wright model predictions at <measure type="value"><num>3.2</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> inFigure 3. This plot is similar toFigure 15 of Hill et al. (2009), whose preliminary analysis found that the Wright model was a good predictor of the mean temporal variation, but the model T b seemed high by roughly <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. Our results generally agree, but we find that multiplying the Wright model by a factor of <measure type="value"><num>0.953</num></measure> fits the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure  type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data best. If one uses the Wright model tabulated at <measure type="value"><num>350</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>, the plot looks nearly identical, but the scaling factor is <measure type="value"><num>0.941</num></measure>, or about a <measure type="value"><num>6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> reduction. A previous comparison by Griffin et al. (1986) indicated that the <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> wholedisk observations of Ulich (1981) were within <measure type="value"><num>7.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of Wright model predictions at <measure type="value"><num>350</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>. The first WMAP Mars observing season occurred during the time of the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2001-07">2001 July</date>-<date to-iso="2001-10">October</date></measure> massive global dust storm which elevated atmospheric temperatures in the mid-IR by nearly <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> (Smith et al. 2002). The effect of dust storms on microwave data is expected to be less of a concern, but we did fit for the model scaling factor both with and without inclusion of the first observing season, with no significantly different results.</p>
		<p>The uncertainties on the derived WMAP seasonal brightness temperatures increase with decreasing frequency, which follows as a result of decreasing signal-to-noise in the data. However, it is possible to extract a trend in temperature with frequency by finding within each season the ratio of the brightness temperature at each frequency to that at W band, and then computing the mean over all <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> observing seasons as a function of frequency. These means are plotted inFigure 4 in black. Errors are standard deviations of the mean. The weak frequency dependence can be characterized roughly as &#x3BD; <measure type="value"><num>0.03</num></measure> , indicated by the blue line. The Wright model, processed in the same fashion, predicts almost no variation with frequency (red line). Such a frequency dependence could be attributed to an emissivity change of &#x223C; <measure type="interval"><num type="base">5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> over the wavelength interval. In a similar vein, a weak <measure type="interval"><num type="base">5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> decline in surface emissivity with increasing wavelength was noted by Burgdorf et al. (2000) in the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num> to <num atMost="180">180</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> range, based on analysis of Infrared Space Observatory (ISO) observations of water vapor absorption lines.</p>
		<p>Some consideration was given to placing the WMAP observations in a wider context, with the goal of gaining further insight into the model parameters. A search was made for a dataset that would provide absolutely calibrated, whole-disk observations of Mars which spanned both sides of the thermal energy distribution peak and were taken over a reasonably contiguous interval of time. Mars data taken by the COBE/DIRBE instrument (Boggess et al. 1992; Hauser et al. 1998) for a <measure type="value"><num>146</num><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> interval (<measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1990-04-28">1990 April 28</date> -<date to-iso="1990-09-20">September 20</date></measure>) most closely matched these requirements, although no analysis of the publicly available data appears to have been previously published. There are <measure type="value"><num>six</num></measure> DIRBE wavebands which sample the thermal emission portion of the Mars spectrum, with effective wavelengths of <measure type="list"><num>12</num>, <num>25</num>, , <num>60</num><num>100</num>, <num>140</num> and <num>240</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>. Of these, the <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> observations cannot be used as an independent check of the Wright model, since the model itself was the ultimate source of the DIRBE absolute calibration in this band (S. Moseley &amp; W. Glaccum 2009, private commu- nication, Hauser et al. 1998). In addition, while the <measure type="list"><num>12</num>, <num>25</num>, <num>140</num> and <num>240</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> detectors are well-behaved linear devices, the <measure type="list"><num>60</num> and <num>100</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> detectors are known to suffer non-linear response , and Mars is on the bright end of that response. DIRBE is a broad-band photometer, and reports monochromatic flux values at the effective wavelength of each band assuming a constant source spectrum in &#x3BD;I &#x3BD; across the band. One must apply a " color correction factor " to the reported fluxes if the source spectrum is different from that assumed. The DIRBE Explanatory Supplement provides such factors for gray-body and power-law spectra. However , in the case of Mars, some of the DIRBE bands intercept known atmospheric absorption lines. A significant CO 2 absorption centered at <measure type="value"><num>15</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> lies well within the <measure type="value"><num>12</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> passband, and grazes the blue edge of the <measure type="value"><num>25</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> band. Numerous minor water vapor absorptions are known to occur at wavelengths sampled by the <measure type="list"><num>60</num> and <num>100</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> bands (Sidher et al. 2000). We have used spectral data available from the MGS Thermal Emission Spectrograph (TES) public archives and the ISO spectrum published by Sidher et al. (2000) to form approximate correction factors for the DIRBE data at these bands: only the <measure type="value"><num>12</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> band required significant correction. For the <measure type="list"><num>140</num> and <num>240</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> bands, color corrections were calculated using the spectrum predicted by the Wright model.</p>
		<p>A mean flux at each DIRBE effective wavelength was evaluated over the <measure type="value"><num>146</num><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> interval, including application of color corrections and scaling to a fiducial solid angle at a distance of <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="au">AU</measure></measure> (Table 7). Although the epochs of WMAP and DIRBE observations are separated by more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, the viewing geometry at the time of the DIRBE observations is most closely duplicated during WMAP observing season four. The WMAP mean brightness temperatures for this season were also converted to fluxes using the same fiducial solid angle,</p>
		<p>and both sets of data plotted as a spectrum in Figure 5. The spectra predicted by the Wright model for the mean time of the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> epochs are also shown on the plot. For clarity, the quoted model errors of about <measure type="interval">&#xB1;<num type="range">5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> are not shown on the plot. On the logarithmic scale needed to show both sets of data together, the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> model spectra overlay each other. Within the quoted data and model errors, the DIRBE measurements at <measure type="list"><num>60</num> and <num>100</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> do not match well with the model. The DIRBE <measure type="value"><num>12</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> data deviate by a little more than 1&#x3C3;, accounting for both data errors and model accuracy. In the case of the <measure type="list"><num>60</num> and <num>100</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> bands, we suspect a non-linear response to a bright object is the root cause. The <measure type="value"><num>12</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> band has a low absolute calibration error, but there is a significant and uncertain color correction due to the CO 2 atmospheric absorption. Ratios of the DIRBE fluxes to Wright model predictions are presented inTable 7; the major source of DIRBE error is that of the absolute calibration, which is also listed. DIRBE observations at <measure type="list"><num>140</num> and <num>240</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> agree within the <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> calibration errors, but cannot be used to deduce any trend with frequency, such as seen by WMAP. We decided to forgo adjustments to the model at this point.</p>
		<p>As currently implemented, the Wright model may be used to predict microwave observations at WMAP frequencies by applying a " post-processing " multiplicative scaling factor to the published values: T new = T pub &#xD7; f scl . For both model and data evaluated at <measure type="value"><num>3.2</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, we have already noted a scaling factor of <measure type="value"><num>0.953</num></measure>. We use the mean ratios of the remaining  <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> frequencies to W band (Figure 4) as scaling factors for these frequencies, which are in Column 2 ofTable 8 . The W-band observations can be reproduced to <measure type="value">&#x223C; <num>0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, with confidence decreasing with frequency to &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at K band. Since the <measure type="value"><num>3.2</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> model values we have computed are not published, we also provide scaling factors to the <measure type="value"><num>350</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> temperatures, which are derived from the the scaling factor of <measure type="value"><num>0.941</num></measure> noted earlier and multiplied through by the <measure type="value"><num>3.2</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> scaling ratios.</p>
		<p>Differences between measurements and the Wright model at WMAP wavelengths are not unexpected. The Wright model was designed to predict infrared emission arising from the top layer of the Martian surface, whereas the microwave signal originates from subsurface layers of order <measure type="value"><num>several</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">centimeters</measure></measure> deep (de Pater 1990; Orton &amp; Burgdorf 2003 ), with potentially different composition and compaction. This was recognized by Griffin et al. (1986 slightly revised version of the model maintained at NRAO 4 . In general, Rudy model predictions using the " standard dielectric constant " were slightly high compared to the WMAP observations, by &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at <measure type="list"><num>3.2</num> and <num>4.9</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> and roughly <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at <measure type="list"><num>7.3</num>, <num>9.1</num> and <num>13.1</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>. It should be noted that the WMAP observations provide model constraints only in the disk-averaged sense. The post-processing scaling of the Wright model suggested here simulates a frequency-dependent emissivity, which implies slow changes in mean subsurface properties with depth. In the Rudy model, which already incorporates subsurface sampling, use of model parameters derived from the radio data produces agreement with WMAP within a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure>. It is possible that this agreement could be improved either through the use of a revised dielectric function or updated thermal inertia and albedo maps. The thermophysical parameters used by the Rudy model are based on &#x223C;<measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> old maps of thermal inertia and albedo from the Infrared Thermal Mapper (IRTM) aboard Viking (Muhleman &amp; Berge 1991). More recent MGS maps of these quantities obtained using the TES instrument are available with roughly <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> to <num atMost="40">40</num></measure> times better spatial resolution, full planet coverage and approximately twice the signal-to-noise (Christensen 1998; Christensen et al. 2001). The surface albedo has been observed to have some time dependence: a visual comparison between the Viking IRTM and TES albedo maps shows alterations in the spatial pattern have occurred since the Viking mapping (Christensen et al. 2001).</p>
		<p>As with Mars, Saturn's microwave brightness temperature varies considerably over time for near-Earth observers, primarily as a result of geometrical effects. Here the dominant factors are the observer's changing viewing angle of the rings and projected disk of the oblate planetary spheroid.</p>
		<p>The ring system presents the main difficulty in Saturn's use as a calibrator in the microwave, although substantial progress has been made in understanding and modeling it. As evidenced by images from Hubble Space Telescope (HST) and data from orbiter and flyby missions such as Cassini and Voyager, Saturn's ring system is complex and rich in detail. The brightest rings (A, B, C) are composed of objects typically less than <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> in size (Marouf et al. 1983) and are composed primarily of water ices mixed with a small amount of impurities (Poulet et al. 2003, and references therein). Those portions of the rings between the observer's line-of-sight and the planet serve to attenuate emission from Saturn's disk. The rings also contribute to the microwave signal via a mix of scattering and</p>
		<p>thermal re-emission of planetary radiation. The crossover point between the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> emission mechanisms occurs near <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> (Dunn et al. 2002; Schloerb et al. 1980; Epstein et al. 1980), with thermal emission dominating shortwards and scattering longwards. Optical depths have been measured at a variety of wavelengths: Dowling et al. (1987) found that the optical depth of the combined ABC rings is roughly gray over a wide frequency range. Voyager I radio occultation observations (Tyler et al. 1983) at <measure type="list"><num>3.6</num> and <num>13</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> produced radial profiles of optical depth for the A and C rings and Cassini division, but only approximate results for portions of the B ring with &#x3C4; &gt; 1. The most complex and recent modeling of microwave data is that of Dunn et al. (2002 Dunn et al. ( , 2005 Dunn et al. ( , 2007) who use a Monte Carlo radiative transfer code to simulate the scattered and thermal emission of the rings based on VLA and other high-resolution observations. WMAP does not spatially resolve the individual components of the Saturn system, nor is the spectral coverage sufficient to definitively isolate ring scattering and thermal spectral regimes. However, the changes in viewing geometry with orbital phase can be used to break degeneracy between ring and disk components, especially as the viewing aspect of the rings becomes more " edge-on " . Over the currently available <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> observing baseline, Saturn's rings are seen at inclinations between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-28"> &#x2212;28</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure> and <num atMost="-6"> &#x2212;6</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> : the sign convention indicates that the planet's south pole is tilting slowly away from the observer as the <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> edge-on equatorial configuration is approached.Figure 6 illustrates the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> extrema andTable 9 lists mean times and ring opening angles for each observing season. Hill et al. (2009) briefly discussed WMAP <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> W-band observations of Saturn, which sampled ring opening angles B &#x2264; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="-17">&#x2212;17</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> . They found that the brightness temperature could be fit remarkably well with a simple sin B dependence. This convenient relationship does not effectively characterize the behavior at lower inclinations, however, and so a more complex formulation is needed for the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data. We adopt a simple empirical model of Saturn's microwave emission, variants of which have appeared in the literature for over <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (e.g., Epstein et al. 1980). The goal is to provide a predictive formula for the unresolved observed brightness of Saturn with as low an error as possible: however, given the WMAP data constraints, such a model will lack physical detail. At a given frequency &#x3BD;, we assume a single temperature for the planetary disk, T disk (&#x3BD;), and that all rings are characterized by the same temperature T ring (&#x3BD;). The model variant we adopt allows for <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> radially concentric ring divisions as defined by Dunn et al. (2002), which are based on optical depth variations observed by Voyager (Tyler et al. 1983). Each of the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> ring sectors has its own ring-normal optical depth &#x3C4; 0,i , with <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num> &#x2264; i &#x2264; <num atMost="7">7</num></measure>, but each &#x3C4; 0,i is assumed to be both constant within its ring and frequency independent.</p>
		<p>Those portions of the planetary disk which are obscured by ring cusps will have their emission attenuated by a factor e &#x2212;&#x3C4; 0,i | csc B| , where B is the ring opening angle seen by the observer. Thus at a given frequency and ring opening angle B:</p>
		<p>where A ud , A od,i and A r,i are the projected areas of the unobscured disk, the portion of the disk obscured by ring i, and i th ring, respectively. These areas are normalized to the total (obscured+unobscured) disk area. T ring (&#x3BD;) is an observed brightness temperature and hides such physical details as ring emissivity and the apportionment of the scattering versus thermal emission. The assumption of a single mean ring temperature is a convenience rather than reality (Spilker et al. 2006; Grossman et al. 1989; Dunn et al. 2002). However, the apportionment between individual rings is not critical to the model fit, as it only depends on the summed total ring emission. Potential contributions to modeling error from nonuniform planetary disk emission are discussed later in this section.</p>
		<p>The WMAP brightness temperatures inTable 9 are sorted by frequency band and B and then a single simultaneous fit for the model parameters is made.  <measure type="value"><num>Two</num></measure> separate fits were tried, differentiated from one another in the handling of the ring optical depth. In one fit, the &#x3C4; 0,i were held fixed at the values chosen by Dunn et al. (2002) (Table 10), and the <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> disk and ring temperatures (for each of <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> DAs) were solved for. In an alternate fit, the relative ratios between the &#x3C4; 0,i were fixed as per the table, but a single &#x3C4; 0,max was solved for in addition to the <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> free temperatures. Both fits returned similar results, with reduced &#x3C7; 2 of &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>1.2</num></measure> for &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>100</num></measure> degrees of freedom. We show only the results for the fixed-&#x3C4; fit.</p>
		<p>The disk and ring brightness temperatures derived from this model fit are presented inTable 11. Formal errors for the ring and disk temperatures at lower frequencies are higher because the ring contribution is smaller and there is a larger covariance between the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> components. The model fit and residuals are shown inFigure 7. The model reproduces the observations to within &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, but observations closer to B = <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> would better constrain the disk temperatures and so reduce the covariance between the disk and rings. The parameterization chosen for the ring optical depths, together with the incomplete sampling of the ring system orientation, allows for alternate models which would fit the data equally well but return somewhat different mean disk and ring temperatures. This systematic is not reflected in the formal fitting errors inTable 11. In order to assess the magnitude of this error, we explored a small number of model variants. The model which fit the data equally well but returned temperatures with the largest differences compared toTable 11 consisted of a combined ABC ring represented by a single &#x3C4; 0 , which was a free parameter in the fit. Disk temperatures derived for this model were &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>2.5</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> higher, and ring temperatures &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>1</num> 	<measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>  lower. As a conservative approach, we additively combine this estimated systematic error with the formal fitting errors to produce the " adopted error " columns inTable 11. The derived disk and ring temperatures match well with those already in the literature.Figure 8 shows the WMAP derived disk temperatures in context with the compendium of plus more recent interferometric observations. The ring temperatures also compare well with those measured directly from high-resolution images of the ring ansae (Dunn et al. 2005; Schloerb et al. 1980;): seeFigure 9.Figure 10 illustrates the percentage contribution of the ring to our total model, which sums the ring emission and attenuation of disk radiation, as a function of frequency and ring inclination B.</p>
		<p>The empirical model described here assumes Saturn's mean whole-disk temperature is time invariant at each frequency. The presence of band-like structures (which can persist for <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) and latitudinal brightness gradients at the &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> level have been noted by several observers at wavelengths of <measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> and longward (Grossman et al. 1989; de Pater &amp; Dickel 1991; van der Tak et al. 1999 ). There is less discussion in the literature of disk temperature structure and/or variability at the frequencies observed by WMAP: there have been no reports of bands or localized structures, but some indication of north/south latitudinal brightness differences. Within the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> epoch under consideration, Dunn et al. (2005) observed a latitudinal disk brightness gradient at <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, such that the north pole was brighter than the south by &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. They interpreted differences between their <measure type="value"><num>1.3</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> data, taken roughly <measure type="value"><num>4</num><measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> apart, as possible evidence for atmospheric changes on week to month timescales. In order to estimate potential model bias caused by the assumption of a uniform disk temperature, Saturn seasonal brightness temperatures were simulated using geometrical models similar to those described in this section, with the addition of a disk latitudinal gradient as described by Dunn et al. (2005) . If one makes the assumption that such a temperature gradient is persistent over <measure type="value"><num>seven</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> and exists at all WMAP frequencies, then such structure would produce a temperature behavior with inclination which is asymmetric about B = <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> . This is because the rings would obscure hotter regions in the northern portion of the disk but colder regions in the south, producing a maximum deviation from symmetry of &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at the largest ring opening angles. Since the WMAP <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> observations sample slightly less than <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> of the full B range, this asymmetry would not be evident, and a model fit which assumes a constant disk temperature would use the ring model component to compensate for the disk temperature gradient. For a simulated dataset matching the WMAP <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> observing seasons, the model fit returns a mean ring temperature biased by less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>, with an unbiased recovery of the mean whole-disk temperature. This estimate is of uncertain quality, however, because it is based on a snapshot of Saturn at  <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> wavelength and a narrow time window. For this reason, the adopted errors inTable 11  An extended, low optical depth dust ring associated with Saturn's moon Phoebe was recently discovered using Spitzer imaging at <measure type="list"><num>24</num> and <num>70</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> (Verbiscer et al. 2009). With a quoted radial extent between at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="128">128</num> and <num atMost="207">207</num></measure> Saturn radii, or roughly <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> in apparent diameter, it would be possible for WMAP to resolve the Phoebe ring, with W band as the best chance for doing so. However, no signal from the ring was detected by WMAP. Properties of the grains are not well specified, but naive estimates assuming typical dust emission and optical depth frequency dependencies would predict temperatures at <measure type="value"><num>94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> of less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="µK">&#xB5;K</measure></measure>, well below achievable noise levels of about <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="µK">&#xB5;K</measure></measure> (1&#x3C3;).</p>
		<p>With their lower brightness, lack of a dominant ring system, and small solid angle, Uranus and Neptune are used as primary calibrators in infrared through radio wavebands for both ground-and space-based instruments. Spectral coverage in the microwave is somewhat undersampled, however, leaving room for interpretation in atmospheric modeling efforts . The microwave spectra of Uranus and Neptune lack the broad NH 3 absorption centered near <measure type="value"><num>24</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> which is characteristic of Jupiter and Saturn. At <measure type="value"><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">millimeter</measure></measure> wavelengths, collision-induced absorption by H 2 is considered the dominant continuum opacity source. CO rotational absorptions have been observed for Neptune in the <measure type="value"><num>sub</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">millimeter</measure></measure> (Marten et al. 2005 ). At <measure type="value"><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">centimeter</measure></measure> wavelengths, ammonia (which is depleted relative to solar nitrogen levels ) and hydrogen sulfide are the main opacity contributors (Deboer &amp; Steffes 1996; Spilker 1995;). Of special note is Uranus' unique <measure type="value"><num>98</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> obliquity, which allows for a slowly changing pole-to-pole panorama of the planet as it moves in its <measure type="value"><num>84</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> orbit, and may also play a role in determining atmospheric conditions. For selected frequencies, observational databases spanning <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> have permitted characterization of the variability of these <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> planets. Uranus in particular has exhibited long-term whole-disk temperature changes since 1966 which correlate with the viewing aspect of the south pole. After accounting for geometrical solid angle changes, Kramer et al. (2008) reported a gradual temperature drop of order <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> over <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="TIME" unit="years">years</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1985">1985</date>-<date to-iso="2005">2005</date></measure>) at <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. This is interpreted as a true integrated-disk temperature change, as the <measure type="value"><date when="1985">1985</date></measure> face-on contribution from the bright south pole progressively morphs into a <measure type="value"><date when="2007">2007</date></measure> view dominated by colder equatorial regions. Similar findings, with similar phasing albeit different amplitudes, have been reported in the radio (Klein &amp; Hofstadter 2006) and visible (Hammel &amp; Lockwood 2007). There is weaker evidence that some portion of variability in the light curves is attributable to changes deep in the atmosphere (Klein &amp; Hofstadter 2006); Hofstadter &amp; Butler (2003) used VLA 2 and <measure type="value"><num>6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> " snapshots " of the disk over <measure type="value"><num>several</num>  <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> to argue for opacity changes in zonal bands. Neptune's microwave variability is less well documented, although there is ample evidence for variability in the visible and near- IR, as summarized by Hammel &amp; Lockwood (2007). Kramer et al. (<measure type="value"><date when="2008">2008</date></measure> find the <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> integrated disk temperature to be constant to within &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>8</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> over <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Peak WMAP antenna temperatures for these distant " ice giants " range from roughly <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="mK">mK</measure> at W band to &#x223C;<num atLeast="0.2">0.2</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="mK">mK</measure></measure> at K band. The signal-to-noise for individual observations of these objects is low (&#x223C;<measure type="list"><num>0.3</num> at W band, &#x223C;<num>0.14</num> at K band</measure>), resulting in large statistical errors in single-season disk temperature determinations. Tables 12 and 13 present the single-season brightness temperatures computed for Uranus and Neptune. Brightness temperatures are listed per frequency rather than per DA as a means of boosting signal-to-noise for those frequencies with multiple DAs. Temperatures for Uranus observing seasons four and five exhibit somewhat larger error bars than other seasons. For these <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> seasons, there was a reduction in the number of observations available for analysis because data quality checks excluded observations in close proximity to Mars sky coordinates. Sub-WMAP latitudes for Uranus range between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-30">&#x2212;30</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure> and <num atMost="4">4</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> over our <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> baseline . Linear correlations of T b against both sub-WMAP latitude and time produced no statistically significant trend other than a flat line. This is not surprising given that the tightest seasonal temperature errors are of order <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, which encompasses the entire <measure type="value"><num>twenty</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> range of variation seen in the <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> light curves of Kramer et al. (2008). We performed similar correlations for Neptune, with again the same null variability result. Note, however, that the sub-WMAP latitude for this planet is relatively unchanged over the epochs of observation . With no discernable variability over the observing baseline, we computed <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> means of the disk brightness for each planet; these are listed as the last line in Tables 12 and 13 . These <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> means in turn may be compared to observations in the literature and placed in context with the microwave spectra in general.  only returned those few acquired in the late 1960s, listed inTable 1 of Gulkis et al. (1978). For a variety of reasons, more recent observations would be preferable, but the older epoch does have the advantage of sharing a similar viewing geometry to that of the WMAP data. These older observations are plotted in gray in the Figure, and agree well with the WMAP measurements, but also do not define a " dip " at high statistical significance. Although suggestive of an interesting atmospheric opacity constraint for future study, the possibility of such a feature has gone unremarked in the literature.</p>
		<p>Non-variable, spatially isolated fixed celestial calibrators for <measure type="value"><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">millimeter</measure></measure> wavelengths are not common. At high Galactic latitude, bright sources are predominantly identified as some form of AGN/QSO, which are prone to outbursts and variability on a wide range of timescales and frequencies. Brighter sources in the Galactic plane tend to be HII regions (which may not be " point-like " ) or supernova remnants (SNRs) with potential variability. At moderate spatial resolution, confusion with neighboring diffuse and compact sources in the Galactic plane can be an issue for background subtraction. <measure type="value"><num>Five</num></measure> sources were chosen for study out of an original list which included some of the brightest sources from Baars et al. (1977) and Ott et al. (1994), in addition to the brightest, least variable objects from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP source catalog (Gold et al. 2010). The <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> selected sources are listed inTable 14. Some of the sources which were initially considered  but ultimately rejected, primarily because of low background contrast, included 3C286, NGC 7027, 3C84, 3C218, 3C123, and 3C147. There are unfortunately few suitable calibration sources in the Southern hemisphere with a long-term history of observation.</p>
		<p>Flux densities of the selected sources are measured from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> sky maps at HEALPix 5 resolution 9 (Nside=512). For each frequency band, the azimuthally symmetrized beam profile (see Section 3.1) is convolved with a sky map pixel to produce a map-based beam template. The sum of the pixel-convolved beam template plus a sloping planar base level is fit to the Stokes I, Q, and U sky map data at each source position, using pixels within <measure type="value"><num>3.5</num></measure> times the beam width &#x3C3; (<measure type="value"><num>1.5</num></measure> times the FWHM) in each band. The peak source temperature from each fit is converted from thermodynamic temperature to Rayleigh-Jeans brightness temperature and then translated to a source flux density using a conversion factor &#x393; that is a weak function of the source spectral index (Jarosik et al. 2010). For point sources, this method of flux measurement is more accurate than the aperture photometry method as used for example by Page et al. (2003b) for Tau A. The WMAP beam profiles have extended wings (Hill et al. 2009), so an aperture radius <measure type="value"><num>3</num></measure> times the beam FWHM should be used and the results are more susceptible to error due to background confusion. The uncertainty in flux density is calculated as the quadrature sum of (1) map measurement uncertainty, (2) the uncertainty in &#x393; (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.5">0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> to <num atMost="0.7">0.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> depending on the band), and (3) the <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> absolute calibration uncertainty. For Stokes I, map measurement uncertainty is estimated from the rms fit residual in the fit region. The Stokes I residuals generally appear to be dominated by beam asymmetry effects, but also include background confusion and noise. (The source profiles in the maps are asymmetric due to asymmetry in the instantaneous beam profiles and the nonuniform distribution of scan angles over <measure type="value"><num>a</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> for sources away from the ecliptic poles.) For Stokes Q and U, map measurement uncertainty is calculated either from the 1&#x3C3; source peak uncertainty and base level uncertainty from the beam fitting or as the Q or U flux times the fractional map measurement uncertainty for I, whichever is largest. The latter method is the estimated uncertainty in Q or U due to beam asymmetry effects, assuming the fractional uncertainty is the same in Q or U as it is in I. The flux determination was tested on simulated sky maps containing a population of point  sources with no other signals and no noise, generated using WMAP beam window functions as described in Wright et al. (2009). Recovered flux densities were accurate to about <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> or better, except in W band where the recovered fluxes tended to be larger than the input fluxes by up to <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. This is allowed for by including an additional <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> uncertainty term in the quadrature sum for W band. Fractional year-to-year variability for the selected sources has been obtained using sky maps for individual <measure type="interval"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure> <num atLeast="1">1</num>-<num atMost="7">7</num></measure>. To remove confusion noise from the CMB and Galactic foregrounds, we subtract the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> average map from each individual year map for each band. A pixel-convolved beam plus flat base level is fit to each difference map at each source position, giving a flux difference &#x2206;F i for the ith year for each source in each band. Uncertainty in &#x2206;F i is calculated from the quadrature sum of the source peak uncertainty and the base level uncertainty. The flux difference is divided by the mean flux from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> map to get the fractional flux variation &#x2206;F i /F . For K, Ka, and Q bands, there is a small ( <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) but significant year-to-year variation in the WMAP calibration, which we have measured by correlating each yearly map against the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> map (seeFigure 1 of Jarosik et al. 2010). The measured fractional flux variations in K-Q bands are corrected for these calibration variations c i using (&#x2206;F i /F ) corrected = (&#x2206;F i /F ) measured + (1 &#x2212; c i ).</p>
		<p>Source flux densities from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> maps are presented inTable 15. Fractional uncertainties for the Stokes I fluxes are typically <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num> to <num atMost="3">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. For some of the sources, the maximum source extent given inTable 14 is not entirely negligible relative to the WMAP beam width in V or W band (FWHM <measure type="value"><num>19.6</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> in V, FWHM <measure type="value"><num>12.2</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> in W, Hinshaw et al. 2009). We have estimated the possible error due to source extent for Tau A. The <measure type="value"><num>1.4</num><measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> map of the Tau A region from the NVSS survey (beam size <measure type="value"><num>45</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> FWHM, Condon et al. 1998) was smoothed with the symmetrized WMAP V or W-band beam and converted to a resolution <measure type="value"><num>9</num></measure> (Nside = <measure type="value"><num>512</num></measure>) HEALPix map. The flux determined by our method was found to underestimate the true flux by <measure type="list"><num>1.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> in V band and <num>3.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in W band. Spatial variations of the spectral index over Tau A are very small (Morsi &amp; Reich 1987; Bietenholz et al. 1997; Green et al. 2004) so the source extent at W band is probably similar to that at <measure type="value"><num>1.4</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. Our V and W-band fluxes for Cas A and 3C58 may also be underestimated by similar amounts. To allow for this, the uncertainty values listed for these  <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> sources inTable 15 nificant secular decrease is seen for Cas A and Tau A. The results are consistent with a frequency independent decrease of about <measure type="value"><num>0.53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year for Cas A and <measure type="value"><num>0.22</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year for Tau A. Our results for Cas A fall between the &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year decrease found by O'Sullivan &amp; Green (1999) Significant yearly flux variation is not seen for Cyg A and 3C58; the rms year-to-year variation is consistent with the uncertainties in each band. The lowest rms variation is in K band, and is <measure type="value"><num>0.27</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for Cyg A and <measure type="value"><num>0.33</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for 3C58. Carilli &amp; Barthel (1996) give an upper limit of <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> on Cyg A core variability from observations at <measure type="list"><num>5</num>, <num>15</num>, and <num>90</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> over timescales from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num><measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure> to <num atMost="15">15</num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. The core contributes &#x2264; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total flux at WMAP frequencies (e.g., Robson et al. 1998). For 3C274 there is evidence for year-to-year variability of about <measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in K, Ka, and Q bands. The rms variation is <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="=1.8">1.8</num> to <num atMost="2.6">2.6</num></measure> times the mean uncertainty in these bands, and the variations are correlated from band to band. Previous observations of 3C274 have shown greater variability. At <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, Steppe et al. (1988)Wagner et al. 2009), which corresponds to <measure type="value"><num>4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total flux. Smaller core flux variations, less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total flux, have been observed at lower frequencies (Morabito et al. 1988; Junor &amp; Biretta 1995; Harris et al. 2009). Spectra of the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP fluxes together with previous measurements from the literature are shown in Figures 14 -18. For Cas A, we have scaled the WMAP fluxes, the Archeops fluxes of Desert et al. (2008), the SCUBA fluxes of Dunne et al. (2003), and the BLAST fluxes of Sibthorpe et al. (2010) to epoch 2000 using a secular variation of <measure type="value"><num>&#x2212;0.53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year. These are plotted with previous measurements that were scaled to <measure type="value"><date when="2000-01-01T11:58:55.816Z">epoch  2000</date></measure> by Hafez et al. (2008) using frequency-dependent scaling. For Tau A, we have scaled previous measurements from Perez et al. (2010) to the epoch of the WMAP data using a secular variation of <measure type="value"><num>&#x2212;0.167</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year at all frequencies. Results are not significantly different if <measure type="value"><num>&#x2212;0.22</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per year is used.Table 17 presents parameters from fits to the spectra for WMAP data alone and for the combined data. The <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> fits are generally consistent within their uncertainties over the WMAP frequency range. Some notes on the individual sources follow.</p>
		<p>A slightly curved spectrum gives a better fit to the combined data than a power law (chi-squared per degree of freedom &#x3C7; 2 &#x3BD; = <measure type="value"><num>1.20</num></measure> compared to &#x3C7; 2 &#x3BD; = <measure type="value"><num>2.13</num></measure> for a power law). The flattening of the spectrum with increasing frequency was previously noted by Hafez et al. (2008). This may be consistent with observations of spatial variations of the spectrum in Cas A (e.g., Wright et al. 1999, Anderson &amp; Rudnick 1996). Wright et al. (1999) presented spectra of <measure type="value"><num>26</num></measure> brightness peaks from maps with <measure type="value"><num>7</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> resolution at <measure type="list"><num>1.5</num>, <num>5</num>, <num>28</num>, and <num>83</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. The data were mostly consistent with power-law spectra, with spectral indices ranging from <measure type="interval"><num atMost="-0.75">-0.75</num> to <num atLeast="-0.95">-0.95</num></measure>. (For comparison, the overall spectral index from a power-law fit to our integrated spectrum from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.4">1.4</num> to <num atMost="93">93</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> is <measure type="value"><num>-0.73</num></measure>). Such a variation will lead to curvature in the integrated spectrum. Wright et al. (1999) also found curvature for some of the brightness peaks with the spectra progressively flattening at the higher frequencies, and noted that such curvature is expected from models of particle acceleration in cosmic ray modified shocks (Reynolds &amp; Ellison 1992). Within the WMAP frequency range, all of the <measure type="value"><date when="2000-01-01T11:58:55.816Z">epoch 2000</date></measure> scaled fluxes are consistent within the uncertainties with the fit to the combined data. This includes the WMAP fluxes, the absolutely calibrated fluxes from Janssen et al. (1974) at <measure type="value"><num>22.29</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> and Mason et al. (1999) at <measure type="value"><num>32</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, the <measure type="value"><num>33</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> flux from Hafez et al. (2008), which is calibrated using the <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP Jupiter temperature, and the <measure type="value"><num>86</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> flux from Liszt &amp; Lucas (1999), which is calibrated using the Ulich (1981) Jupiter temperature. Above <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, there is excess emission above that expected for synchrotron emission, which has most recently been interpreted as emission from cool dust by Sibthorpe et al. (2010). The <measure type="list"><num>353</num> and <num>545</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> fluxes from Archeops (Desert et al. 2008) are much higher than the <measure type="value"><num>600</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> flux from BLAST (Sibthorpe et al. 2010) and the <measure type="list"><num>353</num> and <num>666</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> fluxes from SCUBA (Dunne et al. 2003). The Archeops measurements were made with a larger beam (&#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>12</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> compared to &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> or better for SCUBA and BLAST) and appear to be affected by dust emission that is not associated with Cas A. The WMAP <measure type="value"><num>23</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> (K band) polarization map for Cas A exhibits unexpected structure.</p>
		<p>Figure 19 shows <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean intensity and polarization images centered on each source at each of the <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> WMAP frequency bands. These images are <measure type="value"><num>4.15</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> on a side, have not been background subtracted, and are scaled such that brighter pixels are black. The polarization (P) image for Cas A shows an irregular &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>0.15</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="mK">mK</measure></measure> ring at a radial distance roughly <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure> &#x2212; <num atMost="50">50</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> from the source position. The angular extent of Cas A is &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> (Table 14), leaving the reality of the ring feature in question. We have attempted to simulate this feature under the hypothesis that it is an artifact introduced by a combination of beam and source spectrum characteristics. Cas A is a steep-spectrum source. As a result of effective frequency differences between the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> K-band radiometers (Jarosik et al. 2003b), the K11 radiometer (fed by the axial OMT port) has an FWHM roughly <measure type="value"><num>3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> wider than that of K12 (which is fed by the lateral OMT port), and the peak observed signal in K11 is a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> higher than that of K12. Simulated beam maps for the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> K-band radiometers were generated separately using Jupiter data as a template, and then individually scaled to peak values representative of Cas A. The difference between the  <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> beams as a function of azimuthal angle and radial distance from beam center can be used to compute a rough estimate of induced Cas A polarization signal, under the assumption of complete scan-angle coverage.Figure 20 shows the results of such a simulation, which produces a feature with an approximately correct peak position (near <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> ), but slightly wider and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="30">30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>-<num atMost="40">40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> brighter than that shown in the data image. A more complete simulation would include scan-angle coverage effects, which in this scenario are presumed responsible for the gaps in the ring. This is the only known instance of an apparent artifact in WMAP polarization data.</p>
		<p>The fluxes from Janssen et al. (1974) at <measure type="value"><num>22.29</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, Wright &amp; Birkinshaw (1984 at <measure type="value"><num>89</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, and Wright &amp; Sault (1993) at <measure type="value"><num>94</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> are consistent with the WMAP results. The flux from Hafez et al. (2008) at <measure type="value"><num>33</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> is lower than WMAP Ka-band flux by 2.7&#x3C3;, taking both flux uncertainties into account. We found that excluding the Hafez et al. (2008) flux from the power-law fit to the combined data improved &#x3C7; 2 &#x3BD; from <measure type="value"><num>2.89</num></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>0.79</num></measure>, so it was excluded for the fit plotted inFigure 15 and the fit parameters given inTable 17. Most of the measurements above <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> inFigure 15 are fluxes summed over the core and <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> hot spots in the radio lobes. These are probably valid measurements of the total flux, since the contribution of extended emission from the steep-spectrum lobes appears to be small or negligible at these frequencies. At <measure type="value"><num>230</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, Salter et al. (1989b) found that the integrated flux over the entire source was only about <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> greater than the summed flux of the hot spots and core, which did not amount to a significant detection of emission from the lobes.</p>
		<p>The WMAP flux agrees with that of Janssen et al. (1974) at <measure type="value"><num>22.29</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> and with that  of Hafez et al. (2008) at <measure type="value"><num>33</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. Flux measurements from <measure type="value"><num>three</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP sky maps by Macias-Perez et al. (2010) are consistent with our results in K-V bands, but their Wband measurement is 2.8&#x3C3; greater than ours. The difference is probably due to difference in background subtraction error. Tau A has been recommended as a polarization calibrator for CMB experiments by Aumont et al. (2010) This mean rotation measure appears to be consistent with the rotation measure map obtained by Bietenholz &amp; Kronberg (1991) from VLA observations at <measure type="value"><num>1.8</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> resolution. They found a large-scale rotation measure of &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>&#x2212;21</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="rad.m^-2">rad m &#x2212;2</measure></measure> that they attribute to the interstellar medium, and from the observed depolarization they inferred absolute rotation measure values of a <measure type="value"><num>few hundred</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="rad.m^-2">rad m &#x2212;2</measure></measure> in unresolved filaments. Lopez-Caniego et al. (2009) report polarized flux densities they measured from <measure type="value"><num>5</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP data that are smaller than the values inTable 15 by <measure type="list"><num>9</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>28</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, and <num>67</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at <measure type="list"><num>23</num>, <num>33</num>, <num>41</num>, and <num>61</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, respectively. For Cas A, Cyg A, and 3C274, their polarized fluxes agree with those inTable 15 within the uncertainties.</p>
		<p>The WMAP data show the spectral steepening first suggested by the <measure type="value"><num>84</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> measurement of Salter et al. (1989a) and confirmed by the upper limits of Green &amp; Scheuer (1992) in the infrared. Our adopted form for the spectrum transitions between a low-frequency power law and a high-frequency power law, and gives a good fit to the combined radio to infrared data. Our fit gives a change in spectral index of about <measure type="value"><num>0.9</num></measure>. Additional steepening is needed to explain the observed X-ray spectrum, and Slane et al. (2008) suggested there is a second spectral break somewhere in the infrared. They presented model calculations in which the break at &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> is due to a break in the electron spectrum injected into the nebula and the higher frequency break is due to synchrotron losses. 3C274 &#x2013; The WMAP K-band flux agrees with that of Janssen et al. (1974) at <measure type="value"><num>22.29</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>. The combined data are better fit by a quadratic (&#x3C7; 2 &#x3BD; = <measure type="value"><num>0.99</num></measure>) than by a linear power law (&#x3C7; 2 &#x3BD; = <measure type="value"><num>2.54</num></measure>). Curvature in the overall spectrum might be expected since 3C274 has a steep spectrum  halo. Above <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, the contribution of the halo to the total flux is &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (Baars et al. 1977). Over the WMAP frequency range, the quadratic fit and the WMAP only power-law fit are not significantly different. The data of Ott et al. (1994) give a flatter <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.4">1.4</num>-<num atMost="10.6">10.6</num><measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure> spectral index than that of Baars et al. (1977), and they suggested that this may be due to core activity that could cause variability at the <measure type="value"><num atLeast="5">5</num>-<num atMost="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> level. As noted above, variability of about <measure type="list"><num>4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>17</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> has been observed at <measure type="list"><num>43</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure> and <num>90</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, respectively.</p>
		<p>WMAP data provide well-calibrated radiometry of the outer planets and bright sources. The <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data provide the longest WMAP baseline to date from which to study temporal variability, plus an increase in signal-to-noise which allows us to include fainter objects such as Uranus and Neptune in the analysis. Jupiter temperatures derived from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> data are within 1&#x3C3; of the previously published <measure type="value"><num>five</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> values of Hill et al. (2009). The disk-integrated temperatures derived for Jupiter at WMAP frequencies have uncertainties of less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, with an apparent seasonal stability of &#x2206;T /T = <measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">0.4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. As a planet, Jupiter has additional advantages in that it has a small apparent angular diameter and moves with respect to the fixed sky, allowing for well-characterized background subtraction. Of the <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> objects studied, WMAP uncertainties for Jupiter are lowest, and we continue to recommend it as the best means for transferring the WMAP dipole calibration to another microwave instrument.</p>
		<p>With the aid of models to predict geometrical and/or intrinsic variations, the WMAPderived temperatures for Mars and Saturn are predictable to &#x2264; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="3">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. The recommendation for using the Mars values needs to be tempered by the knowledge that these have been derived using mean seasonal properties only. The Saturn model is purely empirical, and can be improved with the addition of the <measure type="list"><date when="2009">2009</date> and <date when="2010">2010</date></measure> WMAP observations when the rings are nearly edge-on. Uncertainties in the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean Uranus temperatures range from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="7">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> at W band to about <num atMost="7">7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in K and Ka band; only the Q, V and W measurements are suitable for calibration at the <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> level. Some form of simple model including polar brightness effects would be required to extend the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean data here beyond the observing epoch, since longterm studies in the literature show clear seasonal temperature variations. There is also the surprising hint of a dip in the microwave spectrum near <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="GHz">GHz</measure></measure>, where none is expected based on discussions in the literature. <measure type="value"><num>Seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> mean temperature uncertainties for Neptune exceed <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at all WMAP frequencies and so are not recommended for serious calibration usage. Flux densities in Stokes I for the <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> celestial calibrators have typical uncertainties of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>-<num atMost="3">3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, and are in good agreement with previous measurements in the WMAP frequency range. For <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> of the sources, the WMAP data and other available data are consistent with a simple well-defined spectrum over  <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">two</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> in frequency or more. The WMAP observations improve the accuracy of the spectral fit parameters and in some cases they extend the frequency range where the object may be used for calibration. The uncertainties in the spectral fits are typically <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> or less in amplitude and <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.02">0.02</num></measure> or less in spectral index. We provide new estimates for the secular variation of Cas A and Tau A, and provide limits and an estimate for year-to-year variability of the other sources. We present WMAP polarization data with uncertainties of a few percent for Tau A. The <measure type="value"><num>seven</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> WMAP data products are available to the research community through the Legacy Archive for Microwave Background Data Analysis (LAMBDA) at http://lambda.gsfc.nasa.gov. The WMAP mission is made possible by the support of the Science Mission Directorate Office at NASA Headquarters. This research has made use of NASA's Astrophysics Data System Bibliographic Services. We acknowledge the use of the HEALPix package (Gorski et al. 2005).</p>
	</text>
</tei>
