<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>The increased participation of master athletes (i.e., &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old) in endurance and ultra-endurance events (&gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> duration) over the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> has been accompanied by an improvement in their performances at a much faster rate than their younger counterparts. Aging does however result in a decrease in overall endurance performance. Such age-related declines in performance depend upon the modes of locomotion, event duration, and gender of the participant. For example, smaller age-related declines in cycling performance than in running and swimming have been documented. The relative stability of gender differences observed across the ages suggests that the age-related declines in physiological function did not differ between males and females. Among the main physiological determinants of endurance performance, the maximal oxygen consumption (VO 2max) appears to be the parameter that is most altered by age. Exercise economy and the exercise intensity at which a high fraction of VO 2max can be sustained (i.e., lactate threshold), seem to decline to a lesser extent with advancing age. The ability to maintain a high exercise-training stimulus with advancing age is emerging as the single most important means of limiting the rate of decline in endurance performance. By constantly extending the limits of (ultra)-endurance, master athletes therefore represent an important insight into the ability of humans to maintain physical performance and physiological function with advancing age.</p>
		<p>Over the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="interval"><num atMost="3">three</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>, there has been a continual increase in the number of master athletes (i.e., &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old) in endurance and ultra-endurance (&gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure>) events (Zaryski and Smith, 2005). Indeed, the percentage of male finishers older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> is frequently higher than those under <measure type="interval"><num atMost="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. At the New-York marathon, male master runners represent now more <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of total male finishers while female master athletes represented <measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of total female finishers, respectively (Lepers and Cattagni, 2012). This finding corroborates previous observations for <measure type="list"><num>100</num>-and <num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultra-marathon running where master runners represent the greatest part of the finishers; up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="73">73</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> (Hoffman et al., 2010;Knechtle et al., 2012). Similar trends have been observed for multiple discipline events such as triathlon (swimming, cycling, running). For example, master triathletes represent now more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="55">55</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total field for males and more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="45">45</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total field for females at the World championship Ironman triathlon in Hawaii ( Lepers et al., 2013a). The increase in participation of master athletes in endurance events inevitably has an influence on the mean age of the finishers. Generally finishers are older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> in endurance and ultra-endurance events<!-- case not supported: mixed lists --><!-- , e.g., <measure type="value"><num>47</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running ( Knechtle et al., 2012), <measure type="list"><num>43</num>-<num>44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running (Hoffman et al., 2010), or <measure type="value"><num>43</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for ultra-cycling such as Race Across America ( Shoak et al., 2013) -->.</p>
		<p>Different factors could explain the increase in participation of master athletes in endurance events. With the increase in life expectancy and training facilities, such as specific masters programs, the increased participation of oldest athletes (&gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="60">60</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old) described may be a reflection that these athletes, who may in some cases be retired, have more available time and resources at their disposal to train and therefore to compete (Reaburn and Dascombe, 2008). However, sporting background, social category and working profession of the master athletes all remain unknown. Some may have the experience of <measure type="value"><num>many</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of training and competition, while others only begin as they approach middle-age and beyond.</p>
		<p>The relative increase in participation of master athletes in endurance events could also result from a decrease in participation in the younger age groups. Younger people wanting to try endurance activities may be more and more attracted to more "fun" events, such as "Obstacle course races" or "Mud runs" (http://www.outsideonline.com/1892576/american-gladiators). Indeed, an estimated <measure type="value"><num>4.5 million</num></measure> participated in such races in the USA in <measure type="value"><date when="2015">2015</date></measure> alone (http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/ 2015/11/02/obstacle-races-going-mainstream-more-popularthan-marathons/73743474/).</p>
		<p>The current age of elite marathoners is around <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for both males and females (Hunter et al., 2011), but the age of peak performance in endurance events generally increases as race distance increases ( Knechtle et al., 2014;Romer et al., 2014). Interestingly, data from ultra-endurance events reported that the age of the elite athletes has increased over the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> as have their performances. For example, at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon<!-- case not supported: interval bounded by an interval --><!-- , since the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980">80's</date></measure> -->, the age of the annual top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> finishers increased over time from <measure type="value"><num>26</num></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>35</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for females and from <measure type="value"><num>27</num></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>34</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for males, respectively ( Gallmann et al., 2014). Anecdotally, this year (<measure type="value"><date when="2016">2016</date></measure>) the winner of the New-Zealand Ironman triathlon (i.e., Cameron Brown) was <measure type="value"><num>43</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> and became the oldest winner of any Ironman race. Similarly, the winner of the Austria Ironman triathlon (i.e., Marino Vanhoenacker) was <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old and the second placed athlete (Viktor Zyemtsev), <measure type="value"><num>43</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old. Similar trends have been observed for elite ultra-marathoners who also became older over time (Hoffman and Wegelin, 2009;Eichenberger et al., 2012). During the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="interval"><num atMost="4">four</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>, the age of the top <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> runners at the "Western States <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> Endurance Run" increased from the early to the upper <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1930" to-iso="1939">thirties</date></measure> (Hoffman and Wegelin, 2009). These data show that the upper age limit of elite ultra-endurance athletes has increased during the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="value"><num>decades</num></measure> bringing into question what the upper limit of the age of peak performance in elite ultra-endurance performance actually is.</p>
		<p>Age-related declines in endurance and ultra-endurance performance have been well described in the literature for swimming (Tanaka and Seals, 2003;Zamparo et al., 2012;Ferreira et al., 2016;Knechtle et al., 2016), cycling ( Balmer et al., 2008;Baker and Tang, 2010;Capelli et al., 2016), running ( Leyk et al., 2007;Hoffman, 2008;Hoffman et al., 2010;Knechtle et al., 2012;Lepers and Cattagni, 2012), and triathlon (Baker and Tang, 2010;Bernard et al., 2010;Lepers and Maffiuletti, 2011;Stevenson et al., 2013, Lepers et al., 2013b). The age-related decline in (ultra)-endurance performance with advancing age depends on the discipline and on gender.<!-- case not supported: atomic values inside interval --><!--  It ranges from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="8">8</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> per decade (e.g., in <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> male ultra-marathon runners; Knechtle et al., 2012) to <num atMost="15">15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per decade (e.g., in Ironman female triathletes, Lepers et al., 2013a). --> Interestingly, the increase in participation of master athletes in ultra-endurance and endurance events over the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> has been accompanied by an improvement in their performance at a faster rate than young athletes. This has been observed for marathon running ( Lepers and Cattagni, 2012) and also for triathlon ( Lepers et al., 2013a,b;Stiefel et al., 2014). The improvement in performance of master athletes is more pronounced for the oldest age group categories (&gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="60">60</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>). For example, it has been shown that the best marathon male runners under <measure type="interval"><num atMost="60">60</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> did not significantly improve their performances at the New-York marathon during the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980">1980</date>-<date to-iso="2009">2009</date></measure> period, while average running time within the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="70">70</num>-<num atMost="74">74</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> age group decreased by <measure type="value"><num>7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> over the same <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> ( Lepers and Cattagni, 2012). Master female runners followed the same trends but the improvements occurred in all age group categories &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> and were greater than for males. For a newest ultra-endurance sport such as Ironman triathlon that started in the early <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980" to-iso="1989">80's</date></measure> ( Lepers, 2008), the improvement in performance of master triathletes is much more pronounced compared to running. For example, at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon, the male <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="60">60</num>-<num atMost="64">64</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> age group triathletes improved their performance by <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> during <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date>-<date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> the period. The same rate of improvement was found for the best female <measure type="interval"><num atMost="50">50</num>-<num atLeast="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> age group triathletes (Lepers et al., 2013a; Figure 1).</p>
		<p>The better physical condition of older athletes is likely to have increased participation, competitive spirit and performance (Maharam et al., 1999;Ransdell et al., 2009). The higher participation rates of master athletes increases the possibility of them achieving better results due to the competitive nature of the sport (Hunter and Stevens, 2013). Other reasons may explain the improved endurance performance of master athletes such as improvement of training facilities, new training methods FIGURE 1 | Changes in performance ratio for total time at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon across the years for best male and female master triathletes. A performance ratio equal to <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> corresponds to the performance of the top<measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> elite triathletes (&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old). Solid lines represent conditions where the slopes of the linear regressions were significantly different (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>) from <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>. Dashed lines indicate the slopes of the linear regressions were not significantly different from <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>. Lines cross only the range of years for which data were considered.</p>
		<p>(e.g., concurrent strength and endurance training, polarized training), master athlete coaching, nutritional strategies, and equipment (Reaburn and Dascombe, 2008;Louis et al., 2012;Piacentini et al., 2013;Brisswalter and Louis, 2014;Pugliese et al., 2015).</p>
		<p>The age-related decline in endurance performance depends on the modes of locomotion. Studies on triathlon involving running, cycling, and swimming have offered the possibility of comparing age-related declines in <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> disciplines for the same athlete. Interestingly, it has been observed that there was a smaller age-related decline in cycling performance than in running and swimming performances for both short-and longdistance triathlons Lepers et al., 2010Lepers et al., , Lepers and Stapley, 2011). These findings show that age-related declines in endurance performance are specific to the mode of locomotion, although the cause for such mode-specificity is not really clear. Several hypotheses have been proposed to explain the smaller declines in cycling performance with advanced age such as difference in mechanical power between in cycling and running, a lesser reduction in lactate threshold or economy during cycling, a greater muscle fatigue during running with age or greater training volume in cycling compared to running to limit the traumatic injuries ( Easthope et al., 2010;Lepers et al., 2010Lepers et al., , 20162016<!--OCR Error-->, but these assumptions remain speculative and require further investigations. In addition, the age-related declines in ultra-endurance performance seem also depend on exercise duration at least for cycling and running. Indeed, it has been shown that the magnitude of the declines in cycling and running performances with advancing age during short distance triathlon (<measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure>) are less pronounced than during long distance triathlon (<measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure>), while the age-related decline in swimming performance are not influenced by triathlon duration ( Lepers et al., 2010).</p>
		<p>Gender differences in endurance performance for elite athletes is generally close to <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (Cheuvront et al., 2005) except for ultra-endurance swimming where females tend to reduce the gap with males ( Lepers and Maffiuletti, 2011;Eichenberger et al., 2012;Knechtle et al., 2014). Men have a greater VO 2max than women because they have larger hearts, greater hemoglobin concentration, less body fat, and greater muscle mass per unit of body weight (Cheuvront et al., 2005). The other <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> primary factors that limit endurance performance at least for running including running economy and the "lactate threshold" seem not to differ between men and women (Joyner and Coyle, 2008). Gender differences in endurance performance are of biological origin and the gap between elite males and females is unlikely to narrow naturally. Several studies have shown that the gender difference in endurance performance increases with advanced age. It has been observed for running (Hunter and Stevens, 2013;Senefeld et al., 2016) and triathlon ( Lepers and Maffiuletti, 2011;Lepers et al., 2013b) but is still controversial for swimming ( Knechtle et al., 2016;Senefeld et al., 2016). Differences in swimming with advanced age appear to be less than in marathon running and may be related to a greater more depth in women's swimming than marathon running ( Senefeld et al., 2016). The lower participation rate and less depth among women competitors in master age group categories is likely to amplify the difference between genders in endurance performance above that due to physiological differences alone (Hunter and Stevens, 2013). Environmental and social conditions and achievement motivation have played a role in limiting women's participation but it seems less and less true more recently (Deaner, 2013). For example, at the New-York marathon, differences between men and women in running times decreased for older age groups during the last <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="interval"><num atMost="3">three</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> but since <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2000">2000</date></measure> the differences have not significantly differed across age groups ( Lepers and Cattagni, 2012). This relative stability of gender differences observed across the ages suggest that the age-related declines in physiological function did not differ between males and females. We suppose that in the near future, gender differences in endurance performance will be the same for all age group categories at least for the best older athletes, but this assumption will need to be verified.</p>
		<p>Previous data indicate that decrease in maximal oxygen consumption (i.e., VO 2max ) is the predominant contributor to the decline in performance with advancing age (for details see Tanaka and Seals, 2008). Reductions in the ability to sustain a high fraction of VO 2max , evaluated by blood lactate threshold and submaximal exercise economy may also contribute. VO 2max declines by ∼<measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> per decade after <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="30">30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> in healthy sedentary adults. It has been suggested that the rate of decline in VO 2max with age was smaller in master endurance athletes than in sedentary adults ( Heath et al., 1981), however, this observation has been brought into question by more recent data. Indeed, some studies found that master endurance athletes demonstrate similar and even greater absolute rates of decline in VO 2max with age than healthy sedentary adults, as a result of greater baseline VO 2max as young adults and greater reductions in training with advancing age compared with sedentary adults ( Fitzgerald et al., 1997;Eskurza et al., 2002). Trappe et al. (2003) showed that the aerobic power of octogenarian lifelong endurance athletes was approximately double that of untrained octogenarians (<measure type="list"><num>38</num> vs. <num>21</num> <measure type="VO2_MAX" unit="ml/kg/min">ml.kg −1 .min −1</measure></measure> ). These remarkable aerobic capacities are the highest ever recorded in this age group. Some trained octogenarian athletes can still achieve high level of endurance performance. For example, the current marathon world record for a male octogenarian athlete was set in <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure> by a Canadian athlete (Ed Whitlock) <!-- case not supported: Atomic value expressed with different values and units--><!-- who ran <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>  -->(http://www.worldmasters-athletics.org/). This amazing performance corresponds to a running speed of <measure type="value"><num>3.59</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m.s −1</measure></measure> that is only <measure type="value"><num>37</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> lower than that of the actual absolute world record (<measure type="value"><num>5.72</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m.s −1</measure></measure> <!-- case not supported: Atomic value expressed with different values and units--><!-- , <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>02</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>57</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure> -->). Lepers et al. (2013c) have estimated that the VO 2max of Ed Whitlock was close to <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="VO2_MAX" unit="ml/kg/min">ml.kg −1 .min −1</measure></measure>. In regards to Ed Whitlock's performance, we could expect in the future significant improvements in the performances of elderly master athletes who had high aerobic capacities when younger.</p>
		<p>Reductions in the lactate threshold and exercise economy or locomotor efficiency in master endurance athletes may also contribute to the decrease in performance with advancing age but to a lesser extent compared to VO 2max. The decrease in locomotor efficiency in master athletes remains controversial and may depend on the locomotion mode. For example, with cycling efficiency, an increase or a possible reduction ( Sacchetti et al., 2010;Louis et al., 2012;Brisswalter et al., 2014) in efficiency with advanced age has been observed. The same inconsistent results have been reported concerning the energy cost of running in master athletes. For instance, Allen et al. (1985) did not observe a difference in running economy between young (<measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) and master athletes (<measure type="value"><num>56</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>). In contrast, Sultana et al. (2012) reported a higher energy cost of running in master triathletes (≥<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) when compared with their young counterparts. The higher energy cost of running in master athletes is associated with a lower muscle power. However, a long-lasting running exercise seems to preserve the spring-like mechanism (i.e., stiffness during running) of master athletes ( Pantoja et al., 2016). The inconsistency of the results may be explained by the different age and fitness level of the tested master athletes. Interestingly, a recent study testing young (<measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) and master (<measure type="value"><num>60</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) triathletes showed that cycling efficiency was lower (<measure type="value"><num>−11</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) and energy cost of running was greater (<measure type="value"><num>+11</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) in the master compared with young triathletes (Peiffer et al., 2016); but when scaled to lean body mass, changes were more pronounced during the run (<measure type="value"><num>+22</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). These findings suggest that at least within trained triathletes, aging can influence efficiency in both the run and cycle discipline. However, the effects of different types of training with advanced age, such as concurrent strength and endurance training (e.g., Louis et al., 2012;Piacentini et al., 2013) or polarized training (e.g., Pugliese et al., 2015) on exercise economy and more generally on endurance performance, remain to be explored.</p>
		<p>The precise contribution of central (i.e., cardiovascular) and peripheral (i.e., oxygen extraction) factors to the reduced VO 2max with advancing age in master endurance athletes remains unclear (Figure 2). Both parameters of the Fick equation i.e., maximal cardiac output and maximal arterio-venous oxygen difference have been found to decrease in master athletes (Tanaka and Seals, 2008). The reduction in maximal cardiac output in master endurance athletes results from a reduction in both maximal heart rate and maximal stroke ( Rivera et al., 1989;Ogawa et al., 1992). However, maximal heart rate seems to be the predominant mechanism mediating the reduction in maximal cardiac output with age. Interestingly, it seems that the rate of maximal heart rate decrease (∼<measure type="value"><num>0.7</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="beat.min^-1.year^-1">beat.min −1 .year −1</measure></measure> ) with advancing age is similar between healthy sedentary, recreationally active and master athletes ( Tanaka et al., 2001). At a peripheral level, maximal arterio-venous oxygen difference, which reflects in general the capacity of active skeletal muscles to extract and consume oxygen, has been found to decline modestly with age in master endurance athletes ( Rivera et al., 1989). Moreover, it seems that maximal oxygen delivery, rather than oxygen extraction, is the major contributor to age-related decline in maximal arterio-venous oxygen difference in master endurance athletes (Tanaka and Seals, 2008). A decrease in maximal  O 2 difference may also be secondary to an age-related decline in of muscle mass, however chronic intense endurance exercise preserves muscle mass. For example, Wroblewski et al. (2011) showed that despite an increase in total body fat percentage with age, midthigh muscle area, quadriceps area, and specific strength did not decline significantly with age in master athletes. Dubé et al. (2016) recently showed that lifelong exercise was associated with higher intramyocellular triglyceride and glycogen content in all muscle fibers and higher metabolic efficiency during exercise. From a neuromuscular viewpoint, Power et al. (2010) also showed master runners preserved the number of functioning motor units in the tibialis anterior well into the seventh <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> of life providing evidence that chronic activity has beneficial effects not only on the muscle fibers but also on the motoneuron. This same group of research also recently showed that world champion master athletes in their 9th <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> of life had a greater number of surviving motor units, better neuromuscular transmission stability and a greater amount of excitable muscle mass as compared to age-matched controls (Power et al., 2016).</p>
		<p>The inevitable age-related decline in endurance exercise performance of endurance master athletes is closely related with reductions in exercise training volume and intensity ( Tanaka et al., 1997;Eskurza et al., 2002). However, the changes in the physical (e.g., prevalence of injuries, distribution of relative times spent at the different training intensities) and behavioral (e.g., reductions in time and motivation to train) characteristics of training of the endurance master athletes with age remain poorly described in the literature.</p>
		<p>Endurance exercise performance of master athletes continues to improve each year. In a descriptive point of view, we now need a model to compare the performance master athlete of different ages (Vanderburgh, 2015). We also lack information regarding training characteristics, nutrition habits, and recovery capacities of master endurance athletes ( Louis et al., 2010;Brisswalter and Louis, 2014;Borges et al., 2016;Piacentini et al., 2016). Several other questions need to be addressed in the future, such as: Is endurance competition a greater psycho-physiological stressor for master athletes compared to young athletes ( Piacentini et al., 2015)? Does response to high intensity interval training differ between young and old athletes? Is fatigue by induced prolonged endurance exercise amplified with advancing age? Are the benefits from chronic exercise observed in master athletes achievable in lifelong sedentary adults who begin exercising after age <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num></measure>? We also need to identify the concomitant roles genetics and training in performance of master endurance athletes. Master athletes require the continued attention of sport scientists and exercise physiologists to extend their limits of (ultra)endurance.</p>
		<p>All of the listed authors contributed to writing the manuscript (RL and PS), suggesting improvements to, and reviewing the manuscript (RL and PS). All the listed authors approved the final version of the manuscript.</p>
		<p>The publication fee was supported by the Région de Bourgogne (Contract 9201AAO050S02953) and the Fonds Européen de Développement Régional (FEDER).</p>
		<p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p>
	</text>
</tei>