<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Background: We investigated whether circulating tumor cells (CTCs) and circulating endothelial cells (CECs) predict clinical outcome of first-line chemotherapy combined with bevacizumab in metastatic breast cancer patients. Patients and methods: In a French substudy of the MO19391 trial, CTC and CEC counts (CellSearch system) at baseline and changes after <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> cycles of treatment were correlated with time to progression (TtP). Results: CTC and CEC levels were not correlated in the <measure type="value"><num>67</num></measure> patients included. At baseline, CTC positivity was a significant prognostic marker for TtP at a threshold of <measure type="value"><num>3</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure>) but not at <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.09</num></measure>). Baseline CEC levels (median <measure type="value"><num>17</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>, range <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>-<num atMost="769">769</num></measure>) were associated with age ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="45">45</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.01</num></measure>), elevated lactate dehydrogenase (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>) and not with TtP at any threshold. Changes of CTC count during treatment were not a surrogate of TtP, with any of the model tested (threshold based or relative decrease in percent). However, increase in CEC count was associated with improved TtP, at the threshold of <measure type="value"><num>20</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>). Conclusion: Bevacizumab combined with first-line chemotherapy may modify the predictive value of CTC during treatment possibly due to impaired tumor cells intravasation through vessels endothelium. Variations in CEC levels appear to be a promising early surrogate marker of TtP under antiangiogenic treatment.</p>
		<p>Several methods for the detection of cancer cells disseminated in the bone marrow and/or circulating in the peripheral blood of patients have been developed recently for the most common epithelial tumors. Beyond biological characterization of the metastatic process, disseminated tumor cells (DTCs) and circulating tumor cells (CTCs) detection can be used in a few clinical settings as a prognostic factor and/or as an early surrogate marker of treatment response <!-- [1,2] -->. In patients with metastatic breast cancer, it has been reported that DTC detection was not clinically relevant, whereas CTC detection was of prognostic significance <!-- [3] -->. Currently, the most commonly used detection system in this setting is the automated and standardized CellSearchÒ assay <!-- [4] -->, which has a validated reproducibility <!-- [5] -->. In a pivotal study reported by Cristofanilli et al. in 2004 <!-- [6] -->, CTCs were screened by this system in patients who received hormonal treatments or chemotherapy as first-or second-line treatment of metastatic breast cancer. In patients under standard chemotherapy, CTC positivity at baseline was an independent prognostic factor for progression-free survival (PFS; <measure type="value"><num>2.7</num></measure> versus <measure type="value"><num>7.0</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>; P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>) and overall survival (OS; <measure type="value"><num>10.1</num></measure> versus &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>; P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>). CTC positivity was defined in a training set (n = <measure type="value"><num>102</num></measure> patients) and validated in another set of patients (n = <measure type="value"><num>75</num></measure> patients). <measure type="value"><num>Three</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure> after the start of the treatment, CTC status was also independently associated with PFS (<measure type="value"><num>2.1</num></measure> versus <measure type="value"><num>7.0</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>; P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>) and OS (<measure type="value"><num>8.2</num></measure> versus &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>; P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>). In the same series, other studies reported that CTC detection was poorly correlated to the CA 27-29 serum marker nor to the tumor burden <!-- [7,8] -->. The threshold of <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> for CTC positivity and its association with clinical outcome have been confirmed in <measure type="value"><num>80</num></measure> patients treated with standard chemotherapy at the European Institute of Oncology (Milan, Italy) <!-- [9] -->, and in another <measure type="value"><num>74</num></measure> American patients <!-- [10] -->. However, the clinical benefit of using CTC count as an early surrogate marker of response and/or time to progression (TtP) under treatment has not yet been demonstrated prospectively, explaining why American Society of Clinical Oncology has not recommended its use <!-- [11] -->.</p>
		<p>In this specific setting of first-line treatment of metastatic breast cancer patients, it has been demonstrated that the antiangiogenic agent bevacizumab, when given in combination with first-line chemotherapy, significantly improves PFS and response rates as compared with chemotherapy alone <!-- [12][13][14] -->. The impairment of vascular endothelial growth factor-A actions (endothelial cell proliferation and migration, endothelial cell apoptosis inhibition, extracellular matrix remodelling, vasodilatation, increase of vascular permeability) <!-- [15] --> explains bevacizumab antitumoral effects together with its main side-effects. There is currently no validated prognostic or predictive marker of response to the combination of bevacizumab and standard chemotherapy. In a French substudy of the phase IIIb international multicentric MO19391 trial evaluating the safety of bevacizumab with first-line taxane-based chemotherapy in patients with metastatic breast cancer, we investigated whether CTC and circulating endothelial cell (CECs) counts were associated with the outcome (TtP, as defined in the MO19391 trial).</p>
		<p>This article has been written in accordance with the REporting of tumor MARKer studies criteria <!-- [16] -->.</p>
		<p>The single-arm, prospective, multinational, observational MO19391 study enrolled &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2000">2000</num></measure> patients with metastatic breast cancer to better understand the safety profile of first-line bevacizumab in combination with taxanebased therapy. Briefly, MO19391 inclusion criteria were age ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, metastatic (mBC) or nonresectable locoregional recurrence (LR) of breast cancer adenocarcinoma, HER2-negative tumors (or HER2 positive if they have progressed after previous adjuvant trastuzumab), Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">zero</num> to <num atMost="2">two</num></measure> and adequate liver, kidney and hematopoietic functions. Exclusion criteria included prior chemotherapy for LR or mBC and evidence of central nervous system metastasis. Bevacizumab regimen was <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mg/kg">mg/kg</measure></measure> every <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure> or <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mg/kg">mg/kg</measure></measure> every <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure>, combined with the physician's choice of taxane regimen (or investigator's standard of care, excluding anthracyclines). Treatment with bevacizumab was continued until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or patient withdrawal. Our ethically approved companion study was prospectively conducted in <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> centers in France between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2007-06">June 2007</date> and <date to-iso="2008-06">June 2008</date></measure>. All samples were obtained with the patient's written informed consent, after approval by the regional ethics committee. Neither patients nor clinicians were informed of the results of CTC and CEC analysis. Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) and CA 15-3 levels were also investigated before the first treatment cycle (baseline) and before cycle 3 (C3). There was no prior publication on this cohort of patients.</p>
		<p>Briefly, <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> CellSaveÒ tubes of blood (one tube for CTC and the other for CEC analysis) were drawn at baseline and before C3, i.e. <measure type="value"><num>6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure> after the start of the treatment, at the time of physician consultations. Samples were maintained at <measure type="value"><measure type="TEMPERATURE">room temperature</measure></measure> and processed within <measure type="list"><num>96</num> (CTC samples) or <num>72</num> (CEC samples) <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> after collection. All evaluations were carried out with no knowledge of the patient's clinical status. The standardized CellSearchÒ technique has been reported previously for CTC <!-- [4] --> and CEC <!-- [17] --> detection. Briefly, CTCs expressing the epithelial cell adhesion molecule were immunomagnetically enriched and stained with 4,2diamidino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI) (+), cytokeratin 8,18,19 (+) and CD45 (2). CECs expressing CD146 were immunomagnetically enriched and stained with DAPI (+), CD105 (+) and CD45 (2). CTC and CEC morphology was confirmed in all cases. Quantitative results were expressed as per <measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> blood and per <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> blood for CTCs and CECs, respectively.</p>
		<p>criteria and statistical analyses CTC and CEC detection was carried out whenever possible, without any target statistical power. According to MO19391 study end points, TtP was measured from the time treatment began to the time documented progression occurred (i.e. not taking into account deaths occurring before tumor progression). Tumor response to treatment was evaluated as per standard of care and included complete and partial responses. Initially, the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure>-CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold was used to define CTC positivity (for Table 1). The chi-square test or Fisher's exact test was applied for dichotomous and categorical data, and the Student's t-test or analysis of variance was used to compare continuous variables between groups. For comparison of quantitative parameters, if the normality hypothesis was not fulfilled, nonparametric tests were used as Wilcoxon test or Kruskall-Wallis test. Signed rank test was used to compare quantitative parameter between baseline and before C3. Correlation between CTCs and CECs was studied using linear regression. Kaplan-Meier survival curves were used to analyze TtP for each group of interest defined by CEC or CTC thresholds, and Cox regression model was used to provide the hazard ratio and its <measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> confidence interval (CI). To correlate CTC and CEC changes under treatment with tumor response, <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> models were used: threshold-based and relative change-based models, the latter considering CTCs and CECs as continuous variables. Threshold-based models divided patients into <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> classes <!--encoding problem: minus sign becomes 2--><!-- (positive at baseline/positive before C3 (+/+), +/2, 2/+ and 2/2) -->. For TtP analysis, in the threshold-based models, Wald test (provided by Cox model regression) compared TtP of patients classified according to their positivity status before C3, this analysis being stratified on patient's baseline status. Relative change-based model divided patients into <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> classes: patients with relative change (between baseline and before C3) above a threshold and patients with relative change below this threshold. For TtP prediction by CTC/CEC counts, this article reports every test made. <measure type="value"><num>Two</num></measure>-tailed P values &lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure> were regarded as statistically significant. Statistical analyses were carried out using SASÒ 9.1.3 software. results patients <measure type="value"><num>Sixty-seven</num></measure> patients have been included, of whom <measure type="value"><num>63</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>94</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) had a metastatic disease and <measure type="value"><num>4</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) a nonoperable locoregional relapse. <measure type="value"><num>Fifty-five</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>82</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) received prior chemotherapy for localized breast cancer. The patient characteristics are shown in Table 1. Only <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> patients had a HER2-positive breast cancer, as targeted anti-HER2 treatment was not authorized in this study. Main metastatic sites were bone (n = <measure type="value"><num>37, 55</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), liver (n = <measure type="value"><num>24, 36</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) and lungs (n = <measure type="value"><num>21, 31</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). Chemotherapy regimens associated with bevacizumab, were mostly docetaxel and paclitaxel as single agents (n = <measure type="list"><num>27</num> and <num>16</num></measure> patients, respectively). The median number of bevacizumab cycles received was <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> (range <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>-<num atMost="27">27</num></measure>); however, <measure type="value"><num>11</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>19</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) discontinued bevacizumab before the fourth cycle. After a median duration of follow-up of <measure type="value"><num>8.8</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> (range <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.4">0.4</num>-<num atMost="14.7">14.7</num></measure>), the median TtP was <measure type="value"><num>11.9</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CI <measure type="value"><num>8.3</num></measure> to not reached). <measure type="value"><num>Twenty-eight of 50</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>56</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) patients achieved an objective response and <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>17</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) had died at the time of analysis.</p>
		<p>The median CTC count was <measure type="value"><num>7</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (range <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>-<num atMost="496">496</num></measure>) at baseline (n = <measure type="value"><num>65</num></measure> patients assessed), dropping to <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> (range <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>-<num atMost="71">71</num></measure>) before C3 (n = <measure type="value"><num>42</num></measure> patients assessed). CTC count change between baseline and before C3 was statistically significant (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>). A decrease in CTC count was observed in <measure type="value"><num>32</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>76</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), in <measure type="value"><num>9</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>22</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) values remained stable (at <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>) whereas an increase was seen in <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> patient (<measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). According to the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold previously defined by Cristofanilli et al. <!-- [6] -->, <measure type="value"><num>35</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>54</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) were CTC positive at baseline and only <measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>12</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) were CTC positive before C3. Detection of CTC at baseline was correlated with high tumor burden (more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num></measure> metastatic sites; P = <measure type="value"><num>0.03</num></measure>), elevated LDH (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.04</num></measure>) and elevated serum marker CA 15-3 (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>) (Table 1). Also, CTC levels ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> were highly associated with bone (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>) and liver (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.003</num></measure>) metastatic sites.</p>
		<p>The median CEC count was <measure type="value"><num>17</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (range <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>-<num atMost="769">769</num></measure>) at baseline (n = <measure type="value"><num>59</num></measure> patients assessed) and <measure type="value"><num>26</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (range</p>
		<p><measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num>-<num atMost="335">335</num></measure>) before C3 (n = <measure type="value"><num>42</num></measure> patients assessed). CEC count change between baseline and before C3 was statistically significant (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.013</num></measure>). CEC levels at baseline were associated with age ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="45">45</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.01</num></measure>) and elevated LDH (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>) (Table 1). No association was seen between CEC count and metastatic sites (type and number). We found no association between CEC levels and CTC levels or positivity (according to the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold).</p>
		<p>The patient characteristics at baseline were not associated with tumor response or TtP (Table 1). At baseline, CTC prognostic value was assessed using different thresholds to define CTC positivity (Table 2). In this serial, using the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold to define CTC positivity, CTC status was not predictive of tumor response (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.11</num></measure>) nor of TtP (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.09</num></measure>). However, among the different thresholds tested (Table 2), a threshold of ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> was a significant predictor of both tumor response and TtP (Figure 1; P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure>). At baseline, CEC count was not associated with tumor response or TtP, at any threshold (Table 2). We further studied whether CTC and CEC count changes under treatment may be correlated with tumor response and used as an early surrogate of TtP. Results are shown in Table 3. Strikingly, focusing on CTC count, all threshold-based and relative change-based models failed to accurately predict tumor response or TtP. On the contrary, TtP was significantly associated with CEC changes, using the threshold-based model, at the threshold of ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>; Table 3; see also Figure 2A). More simply, TtP was also associated with the CEC status before C3, using the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num></measure>-CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold ( Figure 2B; P = <measure type="value"><num>0.003</num></measure>). Among relative change-based models, a relative increase of <measure type="value"><num>50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of CEC count during treatment was trended toward significance (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.06</num></measure>). In comparison, neither LDH and CA 15-3 serum levels before C3 nor their changes between baseline and C3 were associated with TtP or to tumor response (data not shown). We checked that these results, based on patients assessed twice, were not biased by a significant difference in TtP between patients assessed only at inclusion or twice (P = <measure type="value"><num>0.59</num></measure> and P = <measure type="value"><num>0.85</num></measure> for CTCs and CECs, respectively).</p>
		<p>This exploratory prospective substudy is the first to report both CTC and CEC counts in metastatic breast cancer patients who were homogeneously treated by first-line chemotherapy (mostly taxanes) combined with the antiangiogenic agent bevacizumab.</p>
		<p>Our analysis does not confirm the clinical relevance of CTC counts reported previously by Cristofanilli et al. <!-- [18] --> and Nole et al. <!-- [9] -->, using the same ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold as a threshold for poor outcome. In line with these results, we observed that (i) at baseline CTC was of prognostic significance for TtP and (ii) was also predictive of tumor response, using a lower threshold of ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>. However, the most striking result was that <measure type="value"><num>6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure> after the start of the treatment, irrespective of the model tested, CTC count was not associated with TtP or tumor response.</p>
		<p>Concerning these finding for CTC counts, a lack of power should be discussed at first, as our analysis included <measure type="value"><num>67</num></measure> patients. By comparison, the successful validation set of the study of Cristofanilli et al. <!-- [6] --> included <measure type="value"><num>75</num></measure> patients, of whom about <measure type="value"><num>a third</num></measure> were treated only by hormone therapy, a clinical setting Time to progressive disease (months)</p>
		<!--table--><!-- <p>Baseline &lt; 3 Baseline &gt;= 3 Censure baseline &lt; 3 Censure baseline &gt;= 3</p> -->
		<p>Wald test : p &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0,05</num></measure> original article</p>
		<p>in which CTC count seemed to have less significance <!-- [6] -->. The study of Nole et al. <!-- [9] -->, which was also successful, included <measure type="value"><num>80</num></measure> patients: <measure type="value"><num>70</num></measure> patients received chemotherapy (in combination with trastuzumab for <measure type="value"><num>27</num></measure> patients), but only <measure type="value"><num>33</num></measure> patients had not received previous chemotherapy for their metastatic disease <!-- [9] -->.</p>
		<p>The sample size in our study is therefore of similar size to that of Cristofanilli's group <!-- [19] --> (validation set) and Nole et al.</p>
		<p><!-- [9] --> and also showed a similar CTC detection rate at baseline ( ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>). Moreover, the fact that we do describe in our series the significant correlations of CTC positivity ( ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/ <measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>) with high CA 15-3 serum marker and with bone metastatic site, which have been also reported by Nole et al. <!-- [9] --> and De Giorgi et al. <!-- [19] -->, does not support a lack of power of our study. The lack of clinical relevance of CTC changes during treatment might also be due to the difference in the CTC count schedule, as it was before C2 (i.e. theoretically at <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>21</num></measure>) in the study by Cristofanilli et al. <!-- [6] -->, at <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>30</num></measure> in the study of Nole et al. <!-- [9] --> and before C3 (i.e. theoretically at <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>42</num></measure>) in our study. However, a recent retrospective study of the series by Cristofanilli's group showed that later CTC count (i.e. between <measure type="interval"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num atLeast="56">56</num> and <measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num atMost="91">91</num></measure>) retained a strong <!-- numbers from a table --><!-- 1.00 a 0.55 b --> prognostic relevance in patients treated by standard chemotherapy alone <!-- [20] -->. We therefore favor the hypothesis that the lack of CTC significance during treatment is directly related to the systematic use of bevacizumab in our homogeneously treated series of patients. In our study, CTC counts were in line with previous studies at baseline but unusually low after <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> cycles of treatment compared with previous studies (without bevacizumab): <measure type="value"><num>12</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of patients had ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> here (<measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>42</num></measure>) versus <measure type="list"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> (<measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>30</num></measure>) <!-- [9] --> or <num>22</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num atLeast="42">42</num>-<num atMost="56">56</num></measure>) <!-- [21] -->. Besides a hypothetical direct anti-CTC effect of bevacizumab, <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> possible explanations should be discussed. First, bevacizumab gained its worldwide regulatory approval after the demonstration of a significant prolongation in PFS, leading to its use as a standard for first-line treatment <!-- [2] -->. Importantly, it is highly probable that the intrinsic properties of CTC positivity, defined by a precise threshold (here, ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> was initially tested) and used as an early surrogate test of PFS, will strongly depend on the length of the PFS obtained by treatments, which are continuously improved. In other words, the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold which successfully separated early (median: <measure type="value"><num>2.1</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>) from late (<measure type="value"><num>7.0</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>) progressive disease under standard chemotherapy will necessarily be challenged by the improvement of PFS due to new treatments such as bevacizumab (or trastuzumab, not used here and not reported in the series by Cristofanilli et al.). Accordingly, our results indicate that the CTC positivity threshold should be ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> rather than ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num></measure> CTC/<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>, when used for prognostic purpose at baseline in our setting. Secondly, we also suggest that the use of bevacizumab may change the intravasation abilities of cancer cells, due to its effect on the vessels endothelium. For comparison purposes, in colorectal cancer studies, <measure type="list"><num>56</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>100</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of patients were treated with bevacizumab in the studies by Cohen et al. (n = <measure type="value"><num>430</num></measure> patients) <!-- [22] --> and Tol et al. (n = <measure type="value"><num>467</num></measure> patients) <!-- [23] --> studies, respectively. These <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> studies exhibited a similar baseline CTC positivity rate. However, CTC positivity rates reported under treatment were rather different (<measure type="value"><num>12</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> versus <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num>-<num atMost="6">6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure>), inversely correlated with bevacizumab use. Intravasation impairment is a hypothesis to explain why CTC counts dropped off under treatment. This hypothesis may explain how CTC count (i) retains a significant prognostic value at baseline, as already described in metastatic colorectal cancer patients treated with bevacizumab combined with chemotherapy <!-- [24] -->; but (ii) has less individual significance as an early surrogate marker of TtP when assessed under treatment. The impact of bevacizumab on tumoral vessels has been reported in many ways since the original report of bevacizumab use in rectal cancers <!-- [25] --> but our analysis is the first, to our knowledge, to indicate that it may impair tumor cell intravasation in patients.</p>
		<p>Published data about CECs are highly heterogeneous, obtained by various CEC-sorting techniques, in many different tumor types, and commonly reported in a small sample size <!-- [26][27][28] -->. To further complicate the survey on CECs, these cells can be divided into mature CECs and progenitor CECs, whereas some chemotherapy regimens (metronomic chemotherapy) are believed to exert antiangiogenic effects beyond their cytotoxic effects. More recently, it has also been shown that some standard chemotherapies (especially taxanes) have a stimulating effect on an endothelial progenitor which supports their combined use with an antiangiogenic agent <!-- [29] -->. CEC sorting by the CellSearchÒ system is based on a CD146(+), CD105(+), DAPI (+) and CD45 (2) phenotypes of CECs <!-- [17] -->. It has been also validated through gene expression profiling which verified that expression of endothelial genes such as vascular endothelial cadherin was present in the population of sorted cells <!-- [30] -->. Our analysis is the first to report that CEC count, by the CellSearchÒ automated system, could be a significant early surrogate marker of TtP for breast cancer patients treated by bevacizumab combined with standard chemotherapy. Among many models tested, <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> could be compared in a validation study: (i) a threshold-based model ( ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>); (ii) a relative variation model (<measure type="value"><num>+50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), both using the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> CEC counts (baseline and <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>42</num></measure>); and (iii) a threshold-based model at <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure> <num>42</num></measure> ( ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>). Interestingly, the barely lower statistical significance of the nearby thresholds of ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="25">25</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> and ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="15">15</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure> and P = <measure type="value"><num>0.07</num></measure>, respectively) strongly indicated that the statistical significance of the ‡<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num></measure> CEC/<measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure> threshold was not due to a random multiple testing artifact. Our results are in line with previous reports (using other CEC-sorting techniques) which indicated that tumor progression under antiangiogenic treatment combined with chemotherapy was associated with a significant CEC decrease <!-- [28] -->. In this exploratory, hypothesis-generating study, we did not attempt to establish a combinatory model using both CTC and CEC levels.</p>
		<p>Finally, if our results are confirmed by another independent prospective study, CTC counts by the Food and Drug Administration-approved CellSearchÒ system should be interpreted carefully by clinicians when treating metastatic breast cancer patients with first-line chemotherapy combined with bevacizumab: clinically relevant baseline prognostic threshold may be different in this setting, and CTC changes during treatment may not be an early surrogate marker of survival. Contrarily, CECs are a promising early surrogate marker of TtP in such patients, and a validation study is required to further investigate the different CEC threshold proposals.</p>
		<p>This study has been funded by Roche. The funding source had no role in study design.</p>
		<p>We thank Mustapha Khazour (Institut Curie) for technical assistance and Delphine Etienne (Lincoln biostatistics) for statistical analyses.</p>
	</text>
</tei>