<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Copyright Springer Verlag</p>
		<p>The trajectory design of a solar sail based mission is usually addressed in an optimal framework (Dellnitz et al., 2009;Racca, 2003). Because the solar sail uses no propellant, the aim of the optimization process is to find suitable relationships between the sail performance, as the maximum propelling acceleration at A. A. Quarta · G. Mengali Dipartimento di Ingegneria Aerospaziale, University of Pisa, Via G. Caruso 8, I-56122 Pisa, Italy A. A. Quarta E-mail: a.quarta@ing.unipi.it · G. Mengali, corresponding author, E-mail: g.mengali@ing.unipi.it launch, and the total flight time. Apart from the mathematical approach used to tackle the problem (Betts, 1998), the results of an optimal analysis are generally obtained in numerical form. In fact, in most cases the solar sail trajectory cannot be computed analytically, as it arises from a fairly involved optimal steering law (Mengali and Quarta, 2005c;).</p>
		<p>The propelling acceleration direction and magnitude of a solar sail depend on the sail attitude and on the sailcraft distance from the Sun. However, when the sail attitude is held fixed, the propelling acceleration direction is a constant of motion in an orbital frame, whereas its magnitude changes with the distance from the Sun in the same way as the solar radiation pressure does. If one neglects the potential anisotropy in the Sun's irradiation (McInnes and Brown, 1990), and assumes that the sail nominal plane is normal to the incoming sunrays, the propelling acceleration is, in its turn, purely radial, with a magnitude directly proportional to the local gravitational pull.</p>
		<p>The motion of a constant mass spacecraft under a radial thrust inversely proportional to the square of the distance from the primary body has been studied by Boltz (1991), and then further investigated by McInnes (2003) and Yamakawa (2006). From a practical point of view, a pure radial thrust can be obtained with a passive control by means of a sail having a slightly conical form, and whose apex is directed sunward (McInnes, 2003;Mengali and Quarta, 2005b). The use of a passive control system provides a substantial simplification to the whole mission design process, because it avoids the complex task of continuously varying the sail attitude, which represents one of the most challenging mission goals (Kirpichnikov et al., 1995;Koblik et al., 2003). In most cases, however, a passive control is too restrictive as it does not guarantee the fulfilment of some minimum performance criteria. In fact, the use of a Continuous Radial Thrust (CRT) provides unnecessarily conservative results in terms of required maximum thrust level to accomplish a given mission. Not surprisingly, some compromise solutions are often adopted as, for example, the use of a piecewise-constant steering law (Otten and McInnes, 2001;Mengali and Quarta, 2009c).</p>
		<p>In this paper a different compromise solution is chosen. More precisely, it is assumed that the sailcraft attitude motion is purely passive with the exception of a finite number of reorientation maneuvers whose aim is to rotate the sail such as to set the thrust to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> and generate suitable coasting arcs along the trajectory, see Figure 1. Each maneuver is nearly instantaneous, as the time interval necessary to complete the sail reorientation is negligible with respect to the characteristic mission time. Such a Modulated Radial Thrust (MRT)</p>
		<p>strategy, applied at a constant-thrust-level propulsion system, has been recently investigated by Quarta and Mengali (2009), who have shown that a MRT guarantees a substantial reduction in the performance required to fulfil a given mission when compared to a CRT case. The aim of this paper is to extend the analysis of Quarta and Mengali (2009) to a solar sail spacecraft, whose propelling acceleration is modulated and varies as the inverse square distance from the Sun. The resulting sailcraft trajectory is a sequence of either propelled or ballistic conic arcs. The peculiarity of such a trajectory allows one to calculate analytically the characteristics of each conic arc, in terms of both eccentricity and semimajor axis length. In addition, for a given geometry of the initial sailcraft orbit and a given value of solar sail lightness number β (the ratio of the maximum solar radiation pressure acceleration to the solar gravitational acceleration), it is shown that the geometrical characteristics of any conic arc depend only on the distances at which the reorientation maneuvers are performed. As a result, for a given value of β and an assigned number of mission arcs, it is possible to calculate the sequence of reorientation maneuvers that optimize a given performance index.</p>
		<p>Firstly, the strategy that maximizes the semimajor axis length of the final propelled arc is studied.</p>
		<p>It is shown that the corresponding control law consists in setting the thrust on as long as the sail moves away from the Sun, and setting it to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> when the sailcraft approaches the Sun. As a special case of the above strategy, the escape problem for a propelled trajectory is investigated. It is well known that, for a solar sail subjected to a CRT, there exists a minimum value of lightness number β min below which the sail cannot attain an escape condition (McInnes, 2003). Using an optimal MRT strategy the escape condition can be obtained even if β is substantially less than β min. Moreover, some simple analytical relationships are found that link the number of trajectory arcs with the minimum necessary value of β, the total mission time, and the minimum perihelion distance.</p>
		<p>As a second mission scenario, the minimum value of β required to reach a ballistic arc with a given value of semimajor axis is studied. The resulting optimal control law turns out to be the symmetric counterpart of the previous steering law, that is, the sail thrust is on when the sailcraft approaches the Sun and is off when it moves away from it. This steering law is applied to study flyby missions to outer planets and to generate Earth resonant Keplerian orbits.</p>
		<p>Consider a solar sail spacecraft moving in an elliptic parking orbit with semimajor axis a 0 and eccentricity e 0. Assume that the solar sail provides a pure radial thrust whose magnitude is</p>
		<p>where µ ⊙ is the Sun's gravitational parameter and r is the Sun-sailcraft distance. The value of the lightness number β &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num></measure> quantifies the sailcraft performance and is a function of the sail reflecting area, the total spacecraft mass and the optical properties of the reflective film (Wright, 1992;).</p>
		<p>An equivalent parameter that can be used to quantify the performance of a solar sail is the characteristic acceleration a c , i.e., the maximum propelling acceleration at <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> distance from the Sun. Substituting</p>
		<p>When subjected to a pure radial thrust, the sailcraft trajectory describes a generalized orbit, that is, an orbit obtained through a modulated, inverse square thrust (McInnes, 2003;).</p>
		<p>The resulting trajectory is actually a conic, as the sailcraft moves under the effect of a gravitational force whose magnitude is reduced with respect to the solar gravity. In addition, the sailcraft propulsion is switched off at some points along the trajectory, by suitably re-orienting the solar sail, to create a sequence of mission phases, characterized by either a propelled or a coasting arc, as schematically shown in Fig. 2. By assumption the passage P-C from a propelled arc to a coasting arc (or, viceversa C-P, from a departure propelled arc coasting arc arc number</p>
		<p>Fig . 2 MRT mission strategy for a n-arc trajectory (∆t k is the k-th arc length).</p>
		<p>coasting to a propelled arc) is performed with an instantaneous reorientation maneuver, thus implying a continuity in both the sailcraft position and velocity just before and after the maneuver accomplishment.</p>
		<p>During a propelled arc the sailcraft describes a <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-body motion subjected to a reduced gravitational parameter 񮽙 µ ⊙ given by (McInnes, 2003)</p>
		<p>Consider now a mission constituted by a total of n distinct arcs, and let k be the generic mission arc.</p>
		<p>With the symbology of Fig. 2, k = <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> corresponds to the starting sailcraft orbit with eccentricity e 0 and semimajor axis a 0 , while k = <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> is the first propelled arc. Consider the problem of finding the value of a 1 , that is, the semimajor axis of the orbit in the first phase. Let r 0 ∈ a 0 [(1 − e 0 ), (1 + e 0 )] be the sailcraft distance at which the maneuver is performed. From the mechanical energy equation one obtains:</p>
		<p>Substituting Eq. (3) into (4), and solving for a 1 yields:</p>
		<p>Because 2 a 0 /r 0 &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure>, Eq. (5) implies that a C-P maneuver increases the semimajor axis (that is, a 1 &gt; a 0 ).</p>
		<p>The orbit eccentricity e 1 of the first arc is obtained by observing that a radial thrust does not change the magnitude of the sailcraft angular momentum h. In fact, from h = √ µ ⊙ p 0 = constant, one obtains:</p>
		<p>or</p>
		<p>The orbit eccentricity is, therefore</p>
		<p>From Eqs. (5) and (8) the orbital characteristics of the first arc are closely related to the value of β and to the distance r 0 at which the maneuver is performed. Consider now the second arc k = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> (a coasting arc, see Fig. 2) and assume that the second maneuver is performed at a solar distance r 1 ≥ a 1 (1 − e 1 ).</p>
		<p>From the energy equation, the relationship between a 2 and a 1 is:</p>
		<p>In this case, because 2 a 1 /r 1 &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure>, a P-C maneuver implies a reduction of the semimajor axis (a 2 &lt; a 1 ).</p>
		<p>Substituting Eq. (5) into (9), the semimajor axis can be expressed as a function of the parking orbit characteristics (a 0 ) and of the sailcraft system (β). The result is:</p>
		<p>Equation (10) shows that a 2 /a 0 can be either positive or negative, depending on the magnitude of the second term in the denominator (the latter is a function of r 0 and r 1 , that is, of the points at which the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> maneuvers are performed). From the angular momentum conservation one has</p>
		<p>Recalling Eq. (7) one obtains</p>
		<p>from which</p>
		<p>where a 2 is given by Eq. (10).</p>
		<p>The generalization to a generic k (with k = 1, 2,. .. , n) is straightforward, because the expressions for the semimajor axis a k , the semilatus rectum p k , and the eccentricity e k of the k−th arc depend only on whether k is odd (propelled arc) or even (coasting arc). More precisely, one has</p>
		<p>and</p>
		<p>where</p>
		<p>Note that for a given a k , the corresponding F k is obtained from Eq. (14). Therefore, from Eq. (16), the eccentricity e k depends only on β and a k. This result is not at all surprising, as it arises implicitly from the conservation of the angular momentum h. Using the polar equation of a conic section, an equivalent expression for F k is given by:</p>
		<p>where ν i is the sailcraft true anomaly at the maneuver point. In a n-arc mission, Eqs. (14) and (16) can be used to find the sailcraft performance (in terms of lightness number β) required to reach an orbit of given characteristics. In fact, the values of a n and e n of the final orbit depend both on β and on the summation in Eq. (18) (with k = n). The latter, in its turn, depends on the points (ν i ) at which the maneuvers are executed. Therefore, the values ν i constitute a set of n control parameters whose choice defines the final value of a n and e n through Eqs. (14) and (16). In particular, an interesting class of trajectories is found by looking for the sequence of maneuvers that either maximize or minimize F n. For example, as shown later, the maximization of F n is useful for calculating the minimum value of β that allows a sailcraft to reach an escape condition after n arcs. In principle such a problem could be tackled by looking for the extrema of a function of n independent variables. For example, from Eq. (17) the maximum of F n is obtained by performing the maneuver when the Sun-sail distance r i is at a minimum (maximum) when i is even (odd). By symmetry, the minimum of F n is obtained when r i is at a maximum (minimum)</p>
		<p>if i is odd (even). The same result can also be obtained following a different approach, with the aid of the calculus of variations. This allows one to introduce the mathematical model that will be used in the trajectory simulations. The details are discussed in the next section.</p>
		<p>The problem of minimizing or maximizing the function F n of Eq. (18) is now investigated using an indirect approach. To this end, introduce the sailcraft equations of motion in vector form, viz.</p>
		<p>where r and v are the sailcraft position and velocity vectors (with r 񮽙 r), and τ = (<measure type="list"><num>0</num>, <num>1</num></measure>) is the switching function (τ = <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> when the sail nominal plane is perpendicular to the incoming sunrays, and τ = <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> during a coasting arc) that models the reorientation maneuver.</p>
		<p>Consider first the problem of optimizing F n. This amounts to looking for the steering law τ = τ (t)</p>
		<p>that maximizes (or minimizes) the specific mechanical energy E at a given final time instant t f. The</p>
		<p>where λ r and λ v are the vectors adjoint to r and v, respectively. Their time derivatives are given by the</p>
		<p>Euler-Lagrange equations (Bryson and Ho, 1975;Kim and Hall, 2005), that is:</p>
		<p>The <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> first order differential equations (22) and (23) can be merged into a single second order differential equation involving the primer vector λ v alone (Lawden, 1963):</p>
		<p>Bearing in mind the equations of motion (19) (20), the solution of Eq. (24) is (Lawden, 1963):</p>
		<p>where c 񮽙 = <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> is a constant parameter. The sign of c depends on the transversality condition. When the problem is to maximizing the final specific mechanical energy E, the transversality condition is (Bryson and Ho, 1975;Stengel, 1994):</p>
		<p>If, instead, the control problem aims at minimizing the value of F n , (equivalently, minimizing E at a given t f ), the transversality condition becomes:</p>
		<p>Comparing Eqs. (25), (26) and (27), one concludes that the primer vector satisfies the following relationships:</p>
		<p>where F max n (F min n ) is the maximum (minimum) value of F n .</p>
		<p>We are now in a position to obtain the optimal steering law as a function of the primer vector direction. From Pontryagin's maximum principle, the optimal control law τ (t) is such that, at any time,</p>
		<p>the Hamiltonian H of Eq. (21) is an absolute maximum. Because H is linear in the control variable τ , a bang-bang control law is optimal (Stengel, 1994). According to Lawden (1963) the result is:</p>
		<p>and</p>
		<p>The previous relationships state that when F n = F max n , the sail must provide a propelling thrust as long as the sailcraft moves away from the Sun and that the thrust must be set to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> when the sailcraft approaches the Sun. The opposite happens when F n = F min n (the thrust is set to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> when the sailcraft moves away and is set on when it approaches the Sun). Note that Eq. (29) is a special case of the optimal control law for both an ideal sail model (Sauer, 1976), and a solar sail with optical force model Mengali and Quarta, 2005b,c;Dachwald et al., 2006a).</p>
		<p>Having found the steering law that either maximizes or minimizes F n , it is now possible to apply the above results for analyzing some specific mission scenarios.</p>
		<p>As a first example, consider an escape mission from the Solar System. For a given switching strategy, that is, for a given value of F n , the problem is to find the value of lightness number β = β esc , that allows a sailcraft to reach a parabolic orbit within n maneuvers. The condition a n → ∞ (parabolic orbit)</p>
		<p>corresponds to the value of β such that the denominator of Eq. (14) vanishes, viz.</p>
		<p>Clearly, for a given n, the value of β esc corresponds to F n = F max n . Also note that the minimum value of β to reach an escape condition is obtained when the last trajectory arc is a propelled arc (i.e., n is odd). In fact, as previously stated, a P-C maneuver produces a decrease of the semimajor axis. Therefore, the fulfilment of the condition a n → ∞ with a minimum value of β takes place necessarily when the semimajor axis increases, that is, with a C-P maneuver.</p>
		<p>The optimal control law (29) implies that a C-P maneuver is performed at the orbit perihelion, while a P-C maneuver occurs at the orbit aphelion. Therefore, according to McInnes (2003), the optimal sequence of maneuvering points ν i = ν ⋆ i is:</p>
		<p>From Eq. (18), the maximum value of F k , or F max</p>
		<p>where a i and e i are obtained from Eqs. (14) and (16)</p>
		<p>The particular structure of the above equations provides an immediate generalization to a generic value of k ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure>. The result is:</p>
		<p>and</p>
		<p>In addition, the recursive substitution of Eqs. (36) and (37) into Eq. (33) yields</p>
		<p>The minimum lightness number β ⋆ esc 񮽙 min (β esc ) in a trajectory constituted by n arcs, is found by substituting Eq. (38) (with k = n, β = β esc and n odd) into Eq. (31) and solving for β esc. The result is</p>
		<p>Equation (39) links in a simple and effective way the minimum sailcraft performance required to reach an escape condition with the eccentricity of the parking orbit e 0 and the number of trajectory arcs n. Note that the same result can be found also from Eq. (36) (with k = n and n odd), by setting the denominator to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>.</p>
		<p>The lack of dependence on a 0 in Eq. (39) implies that the minimum performance is related to the orbit shape only. This extends the results found by Mengali and Quarta (2009a) for a spacecraft subjected to a constant radial thrust. Finally, note that for a circular parking orbit (e 0</p>
		<p>The presence of n in the denominator of Eq. (39) suggests the possibility of a reduction of β esc at will, by simply increasing the number of trajectory arcs. Although this is in principle true, there are, however, a couple of constraints that must be taken into account. On one side an increase of n implies a corresponding increase in the total flight time ∆t esc , that is, the time interval between the first and the last maneuver.</p>
		<p>In fact, ∆t esc is simply equal to the sum of the half-orbital periods ∆t k , with k = 1, 2,. .. , (n − 1), of the elliptic arcs that constitute the trajectory between the first and the last maneuver. Accordingly:</p>
		<p>where a k is given by Eq. (36).</p>
		<p>In addition, an increase of n tends to reduce the minimum perihelion distance from the Sun. In fact, the perihelion of any arc is r p k = p k /(1 + e k ), and from Eqs. (15) and (37) it may be verified that the perihelion distance decreases monotonically as long as k is increased. Therefore, the total trajectory perihelion distance is obtained in correspondence of the last C-P maneuver (that is, when k = n − 1 and n is odd). The result is</p>
		<p>Note that, when β = β ⋆ esc , Eq. (41) yields</p>
		<p>In particular, in the limit as n → ∞, the perihelion radius reduces to</p>
		<p>which corresponds to the minimum theoretical value of perihelion distance reachable during an optimal escape trajectory.</p>
		<p>The practical consequence of Eq. (42) is that there exists an explicit relationship between the number of arcs n and the maximum temperature experienced by the sail during the mission ( Rowe et al., 1978;Stimpson et al., 1978). In fact, using the model discussed in Mengali and Quarta (2009b) and Dachwald et al. (2006b), the maximum sail equilibrium temperature is given by</p>
		<p>where r ⊕ 񮽙 <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> and 񮽙 Θ 񮽙 <measure type="value"><num>263.56</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure><!--"񮽙" equal + delta up symbole correspond to "definied as"--> is a reference temperature depending on the optical properties of the reflecting material (McInnes, 1999). Because during the mission the sail temperature cannot exceed a given sail film maximum tolerable limit Θ lim (Mengali and Quarta, 2009b), upon combining Eqs. (42) and (44) one obtains the following relationship involving an upper limit on n:</p>
		<p>where ⌊·⌋ is the floor function.</p>
		<p>Recall that the previous expressions for the total flight time, the minimum perihelion distance, and the maximum sail temperature are all obtained under the assumption of minimum value of lightness number necessary to reach an escape condition. Accordingly, ∆t esc , r p and Θ max can be thought of as being the outputs of the optimization process whose performance index is β. In the following example Eqs. (40), (42), and (44) will be used to check that the simulation results meet the typical mission constraints.</p>
		<p>Assuming a parking orbit equal to the Earth's heliocentric orbit, that is, a 0 = a ⊕ 񮽙 <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> and e 0 = e ⊕ 񮽙 <measure type="value"><num>0.01671</num></measure>, with the aid of the previous relationships the results summarized in Table 1 are obtained. In this and all of the examples discussed below the total mission time is constrained to not exceed <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>The information summarized in Table 1 allows one to find a compromise solution between the flight time and the minimum lightness number required to obtain an escape from the Solar System with a sailcraft deployment on a parabolic Earth-escape trajectory, that is, with <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> hyperbolic excess energy with respect to the planet. Using a limit temperature Θ lim = <measure type="value"><num>513.15</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> ( Dachwald et al., 2006b), the temperature constraint does not affect the sailcraft trajectory. In fact, from Eq. (43) the minimum peri</p>
		<p>Note, in passing, that Eq. (46) coincides with the locally optimal control law, that is, the control law that maximizes the time derivative of the specific mechanical energy (Macdonald and McInnes, 2005;Macdonald et al., 2007;Quarta, 2004, 2005a). The simulation results for n = <measure type="value"><num>3</num></measure> have been summarized in Fig. 3. In the figure the specific mechanical energy E (which is made dimensionless with its initial value E 0 񮽙 −µ ⊙ /(2 a 0 )) during the propelled arcs is calculated by taking into account the reduced gravitational parameter, that is:</p>
		<p>where v is the sailcraft velocity magnitude. The specific mechanical energy, which has a stepwise behaviour, increases during any C-P maneuver. Note the consistency between the results of Table 1 shown in Fig. 3 regarding the flight time (∆t esc ≃ <measure type="value"><num>1.849</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) and the perihelion radius (r p ≃ <measure type="value"><num>0.66</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>).</p>
		<p>The sailcraft trajectory is actually a sequence of conic arcs, as shown in Fig. 4.</p>
		<p>As a second example, consider now the escape problem from the heliocentric Mercury's orbit (a 0 = a ≃ <measure type="value"><num>0.387</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> and e 0 = e ≃ <measure type="value"><num>0.2056</num></measure>). This example allows one to investigate the impact of the starting orbit eccentricity and the perihelion distance on the mission performance. However, we explicitly maintain that a direct comparison with the previous example (escape from an Earth's parking orbit) is not possible, as the following results do not take into account the transfer time from Earth's to Mercury's orbit.</p>
		<p>From Table 2, the optimal escape strategy requires a single maneuver (n = <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>), otherwise the sail film would be exposed to a temperature greater than the limit temperature of <measure type="value"><num>513.15</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. For example, assuming n = <measure type="value"><num>11</num></measure>, the minimum lightness number required to reach an escape condition is β ⋆ esc ≃ <measure type="value"><num>0.066</num></measure> only, see Table 2 Optimal performances for a Solar System escape starting from the Mercury's heliocentric orbit.</p>
		<p>Eq. (39), and the total flight time is about <measure type="value"><num>3.7</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. However, the corresponding maximum temperature is Θ max ≃ <measure type="value"><num>591.5</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure> and the resulting trajectory is rather complex, as shown in Fig. 5. Note that, as a consequence of Eq. (15), for all of the conic arcs the semilatus rectum is constant and, accordingly, all the arcs intersect at <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> points. As previously pointed out, an increase of the number of trajectory arcs implies a decrease of both the minimum perihelion distance and the minimum characteristic acceleration required to attain an escape condition. Such a behavior is essentially due to the substantial increase of radial acceleration that a sailcraft experiences when it approaches the Sun. For comparative purposes, it is possible to calculate the performance of a CRT spacecraft with constant thrust using the mathematical model discussed in Quarta and Mengali (2009). It can be verified that, the total flight time being the same, the characteristic acceleration required by a solar sail is much smaller than that of a CRT spacecraft. For example, assuming a flight time of <measure type="value"><num>3.7012</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, a CRT spacecraft requires a characteristic acceleration a c = <measure type="value"><num>1.162</num> <measure type="ACCELERATION" unit="mm.s^-2">mm/s 2</measure></measure> to reach an escape condition, against about <measure type="value"><num>0.4</num> <measure type="ACCELERATION" unit="mm.s^-2">mm/s 2</measure></measure> of a solar sail spacecraft, see Tab. 2.</p>
		<p>As a second scenario, consider now a mission whose aim is to reach a final Keplerian orbit with a given (finite) value of semimajor axis a f &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num></measure>, starting from a parking orbit with semimajor axis a 0 and eccentricity e 0 ∈ [<measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>). The problem here is to find the minimum value of β required to accomplish such a mission. Recall from Eqs. (14) and (16) that the final orbit eccentricity is univocally obtained as a function of a f. Assume that the (final) n−th trajectory arc starts with a P-C maneuver and that the sailcraft, once reached the final orbit, jettisons the propulsion system. This scenario corresponds to a transfer orbit constituted by an even number n of elliptical arcs. Recalling from Eq. (15) that p f = p 0 , the final eccentricity is</p>
		<p>Therefore, the final aphelion distance r a is:</p>
		<p>Note that r a increases monotonically with increasing a f. As a result, the minimum lightness number necessary to obtain a given a f corresponds to the minimum value required to reach a given aphelion distance r a. In particular, Eq. (49) can be used to express a f as a function of r a in a dimensionless form.</p>
		<p>In fact, solving Eq. (49) for a f , yields:</p>
		<p>The value of β required to fulfil the sailcraft transfer is obtained from Eq. (14) by setting a n = a f and choosing an even value of n. The result is:</p>
		<p>As in the previous escape case, the lightness number is a function of F n and, therefore, it depends on the choice of the n control parameters ν i , see Eq. (18). Since the lightness number is, by definition, a positive parameter, from Eq. (51) the minimum (superscript ⋆) lightness number β a f necessary to complete the transfer within n arcs is</p>
		<p>where F max n is given by Eq. (38) with k = n. Also recall that F min n corresponds to the minimum value of F n with respect to the n control parameters ν i .</p>
		<p>The expression for F min n is found by selecting the perihelion distance for a P-C maneuver and, viceversa, the aphelion for a C-P maneuver, see Eq. (18). Such a control law, can be thought of equivalent to the symmetric counterpart of the previous strategy required to obtain F max n . Using the same approach as that employed to obtain F max n [see Eq. (38)], the expression of F min n is found to be:</p>
		<p>if n is odd (53) Note that, if a f &lt; a 0 , Eq. (52) implies that F min n &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0">0</num></measure>. From Eq. (53) this is possible only provided that</p>
		<p>Finally, substituting (38) and (53)</p>
		<p>from which one concludes that the minimum value of a f cannot be less than p 0. In particular, if a f = p 0 , Eq. (48) states that the final orbit is circular with a radius equal to p 0 .</p>
		<p>If, instead, a f &gt; a 0 , an increase of n implies a corresponding decrease of β ⋆ a f , in accordance to</p>
		<p>Eq. (54). Similarly to the previously discussed case of mission escape, an increase of n also increases the total mission time and decreases the perihelion distance r p. The latter can be obtained from the following expression:</p>
		<p>The above results can be used to investigate, for example, the minimum performance necessary to reach a heliocentric distance equal to the semimajor axis of Mars' orbit (r a = a ♂ ≃ <measure type="value"><num>1.523</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>) or to the semimajor axis of Jupiter's orbit (r a = a ≃ <measure type="value"><num>5.203</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>), starting from an Earth's heliocentric orbit (a 0 = a ⊕ and e 0 = e ⊕ ). These examples are representative of flyby missions towards an outer planet under the assumption that both the inclination and the eccentricity of the target planet orbit are neglected.</p>
		<p>The mission performance for these <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> cases are summarized in Tables 3 and 4 as a function of n. The tables show that although in both cases the minimum perihelion distance is tolerable, unfortunately the flight times for a mission to Jupiter are rather long. In fact the optimal trajectory (that is, with a minimum value of β) when n = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> needs a flight time of about ∆t a f = <measure type="value"><num>3.5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> with a lightness number The optimal trajectory for a Mars flyby, with n = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> and n = <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure> is shown in Fig. 6. Note that if n = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure>, see Fig. 6(a), the sailcraft transfer is close to a more familiar circle-to-circle Hohmann transfer (recall that e ⊕ ≪ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="1">1</num></measure>). According to McInnes (2003), when n = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> the sailcraft trajectory shows one propelled arc only, which connects the initial and final circular orbits in a quasi-Hohmann fashion. In fact, from Eqs. (50) and (54), the corresponding lightness number</p>
		<p>is the minimum value required to put the aphelion of the transfer trajectory on the target circular orbit. This corresponds to obtaining, at the end of the last propelled arc, a flyby with hyperbolic excess speed v ∞ (with respect to the target planet)</p>
		<p>given by:</p>
		<p>When the number of arcs increases, see Fig. 6(b) where n = <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>, the transfer trajectory becomes more involved but the aphelion still lies on the final target orbit. Note that the change from n = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> to n = <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure> in an Earth-Mars flyby mission, entails a saving of about <measure type="value"><num>75</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in the lightness number and an increase of <measure type="value"><num>410</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in the flight time, see Table 3. The same reduction in β ⋆ a f (<measure type="value"><num>75</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) occurs in an Earth-Jupiter flyby mission, see Figure 7, when the strategy switches from n = <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> to n = <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>, whereas the flight time doubles.</p>
		<p>A further interesting employment of the above theory is given by the creation of an orbital resonance with the departure orbit. Resonant orbits can be used for scientific purposes or to generate multiple flyby maneuvers with Earth. An example is shown in Table 5, which summarizes the optimal performance required to reach a <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>:<measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> resonant orbit, having a semimajor axis equal to a f = 3 √ 4 a ⊕ = <measure type="value"><num>1.5874</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>. The resulting resonant orbit and the transfer trajectory towards that orbit are illustrated in Fig. 8.</p>
		<p>The dynamics of a sailcraft subjected to a modulated radial thrust, whose magnitude varies as the inverse square distance from the primary body, have been thoroughly studied. When the thrust is on, the sailcraft experiences a gravitational force whose magnitude is reduced with respect to the local solar Table 5 Optimal performance to reach a <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>:<measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> Earth resonant orbit (a f = <measure type="value"><num>1.5874</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>).</p>
		<p>final orbit gravity. As a result, the sailcraft trajectory is a sequence of either propelled or ballistic conic arcs. The trajectory analysis has been performed in an optimal framework by maximizing or minimizing a suitable scalar performance index. The mathematical structure of the problem guarantees the achievement of some simple analytical relationships that can be used effectively to find compromise solutions between the required maximum thrust level to accomplish a given mission and the total flight time. In particular, the above mathematical model has been applied to a solar sail spacecraft and different mission scenarios have been investigated. For the escape trajectory problem, some analytical relationships are found that link the number of trajectory arcs with the minimum required lightness number, the flight time, and the perihelion distance. In addition, the minimum performance necessary to reach a ballistic arc with a given value of semimajor axis has been discussed. The resulting steering law has been applied to study flyby missions to outer planets and to generate Earth resonant Keplerian orbits. The obtained results confirm that a modulated radial thrust is superior with respect to a continuous radial thrust strategy, and the performance improvements can be calculated analytically.</p>
		<p>This research was financed in part by a "Paolo Manes" grant. Alessandro A. Quarta gratefully acknowledges the support of the Manes family.</p>
	</text>
</tei>