<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Anecdotal reports show that some older athletes nowadays can achieve very high levels of ultra-endurance performance (defined as performance exceeding <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure>, Zaryski &amp; Smith 2005). For example, an <measure type="value"><num>81</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure>-old male athlete was able to finish a <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultra-marathon <!-- case not supported: one atomic value expressed with different values and units --><!--in a time of 19 h 44 min--> ( Knechtle et al. 2009). In the field of multi-sport events, an <measure type="value"><num>80</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> old male triathlete also finished the <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure></p>
		<p>Hawaii Ironman Triathlon consisting of <measure type="value"><num>3.8</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swimming, <measure type="value"><num>180</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycling and <measure type="value"><num>42</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running, in less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="16">16</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> ( ). That same year, and at the same event, a <measure type="value"><num>75</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> old female triathlete finished the race <!-- case not supported: one atomic value expressed with different values and units --><!--in http://ironmanworldchampionship.com/results/ 16h 20min-->. These unique older athletes have begun to push the limits of the interaction between aging and human endurance. They represent a positive example of healthy aging and provide unique insights into a person s ability to maintain physical performance and ' physiological function with advancing age (Tanaka and Seals 2008).</p>
		<p>Age-related declines in endurance performance have been well described in the literature for running (Trappe 2007, Leyk et al 2009, Lepers &amp; Cattagni 2011), swimming (Tanaka &amp; Seals 2008) and triathlon ( Bernard et al. 2010, Baker et al. 2010). Changes in performance across the ages have also been examined for ultra-endurance events, including running events of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure> to <num atMost="161">161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> (Hoffman &amp; Wegelin 2009, Hoffman et al. 2010, Knechtle et al. 2011) and Ironman distance triathlons ( Lepers et al. 2010, Lepers &amp; Maffiuletti 2011).</p>
		<p>Endurance and ultra-endurance performance, in terms of the overall time taken, appears to be maintained until approximately <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="35">35</num> <num atMost="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>of age, followed by modest decreases until <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of age, with a progressive decrease in performance thereafter with the greatest declines occurring after the age of <measure type="value"><num>70</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Physiological factors, both central (maximum heart rate; maximum stroke volume; blood volume) and peripheral (muscle mass; muscle fiber composition, size and capillarization; muscle enzyme activity), contribute to age-related declines in endurance performance in older athletes. However, these physiological factors can be regulated by changing the intensity and volume of the older endurance athletes training (Reaburn &amp; Dascombe 2008, Tanaka &amp; Seals 2008 and there is obviously an interaction between ' training behaviour and performance in older athletes ( Maharam et al. 1999).</p>
		<p>Previous observations have suggested that the endurance performance of elite athletes (age &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> old) had plateaued ( Sparkling et al. 1998, Lepers 2008, Lepers &amp; Cattagni 2011, Knechtle et al. 2011). In contrast, recent studies showed an improvement in endurance running performance of master athletes (age &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> old) over the past <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>. For example, analysis of performance trends at the ' New-York City Marathon showed that the running times of masters athletes significantly decreased, for both males and females over the last <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> ( Jokl et al. 2004, Lepers &amp; Cattagni 2011). To our knowledge, only <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> studies have focussed upon the ultra-endurance participation and performance trends of masters athletes. An increase in participation of both male and female athletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> has been reported for <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultra-marathons in North America over the past <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> ( Hoffman et al. 2010) and for <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running in Switzerland ( Knechtle et al. 2011) during the last <measure type="value"><num>ten</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, but no data are available for a multi-sport ultra-endurance event, such the Ironman triathlon. An increased participation of masters athletes in such ultra-endurance events may inevitably be linked to an increase in training volume, and could be interpreted as a possible strategy for maintaining good health during old age; these older athletes being conscious that regular physical activity may increase life expectancy.</p>
		<p>Ironman triathlon represents an intriguing model to analyse age-related declines in ultra-endurance performance. Indeed, the age-related declines in performance can be analyzed in the same subjects collectively, and also for <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> modes of locomotion (swimming, cycling and running) separately ( Bernard et al. 2010, Lepers et al. 2010, Lepers &amp; Maffiuletti 2011. It has been shown for example, that age-related declines in cycling performance were less pronounced compared to running, presumably due to the non-weight bearing aspect and the concentric type of muscle action during cycling. According to previous investigations on the participation trends conducted on ultra-endurance running events ( Hoffman et al. 2010, Knechtle et al. 2011), we would also expect an increase in the participation of masters triathletes in an ultra-endurance competitions such Ironman triathlon since the emergence of this sport in the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980" to-iso="1989">1980 s</date></measure> (Lepers 2008).</p>
		<p>In accordance with this expected increase in participation, it may also be interesting to see if older Ironman triathletes have shown improvements in their swimming, cycling and running performance over the past <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>A previous study conducted on the Hawaii Ironman triathlon showed that gender differences in total performance time were stable until <measure type="interval"><num atMost="55">55</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> of age but increased thereafter (Lepers &amp; Maffiuletti 2011). However, this study focused only on a recent <measure type="value"><num>three</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> period (<measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2006">2006</date> <date to-iso="2008">2008</date></measure>) and did not examine the possible differences between the genders with age since the beginning of the event in the early <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980" to-iso="1989">1980' s</date></measure>. If the changes in age-related decline in performance differed between males and females over the past <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>, we would also expect some change in the difference between gender performances across the ages.</p>
		<p>Previous studies have focussed mainly upon declines in overall performance with age by comparing older age group performances with younger ones, but have not really investigated if performances within each older age group have increased relatively over the years.</p>
		<p>To date, no data exist regarding the participation and performance trends of masters athletes in a multi-sport ultra-endurance event such as the Ironman triathlon in the last <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Accordingly, the first purpose of this large cross-sectional study was to examine the changes in participation and performance of masters triathletes at the Ironman triathlon World Championship over the last <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>). A secondary purpose was to analyze the gender differences in Ironman triathlon performance as a function of age across the same <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> period. In this study, we focused on the performance of the best master triathletes of each age-group (i.e. the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> performerof each <measure type="value"><num>5</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> age-group) because these athletes present a unique model for studying the effects of high levels of physical training in older age.</p>
		<p>Approval for this study was obtained from the Burgundy University Committee on Human Research. It involved the analysis of publicly available data so content was waived. Age and time performance data for all triathletes completing the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> were obtained through the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon web site:</p>
		<p>. In the http://ironmanworldchampionship.com/results/ present paper, we focus our attention on the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon, which has become the Ironman World Championship i.e. the premier race in the field of long distance triathlon (Lepers 2008). In order to participate at the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon, all triathletes must earn a qualifying slot at one of the qualifying Ironman triathlons held worldwide during the previous year (http://ironman.com/events</p>
		<p>To analyze the changes in participation across the years, we quantified the number of female and male finishers in each age-group category annually from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>. We considered only the age groups with at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num></measure> finishers per annum for the analysis of performances. Averaged swimming, cycling, running and total time performances of the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> finishers of each age group for both females and males were analyzed from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>. Taking the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> performers in the master categories gave a better comparison with higher performing younger athletes.</p>
		<p>In order to limit the influence of environmental conditions and small changes in the courses in the comparison of performance, the swimming, cycling, running and overall time performances of each triathlete finishing in the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> of each age group were divided by the mean time performance of the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> overall finishers. We considered the mean performance of the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> overall finishers (whose age was always comprised between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> and <num atMost="39">39</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old) as the reference for calculating the relative performance ratio for the master age-groups. Thus, the age-related declines in performance were expressed using a performance ratio calculated between the individual and the mean time performances of the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> overall finishers for each mode of locomotion and total event time ( Lepers et al 2010). This normalization procedure assisted the comparison of age-related declines in performance across the years for both males and females.</p>
		<p>The magnitude of gender differences in total time performance of each age group was examined by calculating the difference in total times between the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> males versus females as a percentage of the average time for the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> males for each year from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>.</p>
		<p>Data is reported as means SD in the text. Linear regressions analyses were used to estimate changes in the selected variables in each ± year of the race. Pearson s correlation coefficients were used to assess the association between various variables using Statsoft (Version ' 6.1, Statistica, Tulsa, OK, USA). Linear regression analyses were used to assess changes in the percentage of finishers in the different age-groups for both sexes across the years, the mean performance ratios for swimming, cycling, running and total event times, for males and females within the different age-groups, and gender differences in total time performances. A significance level of P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure> was used to identify statistical significance.</p>
		<p>From <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>, there were a total of <measure type="value"><num>35,293</num></measure> finishers (<measure type="value"><num>7,825</num></measure> females and <measure type="value"><num>27,468</num></measure> males) at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon. The number of finishers during the studied period is shown in Figure 1.</p>
		<p>of the field over the <measure type="value"><num>25</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> period.</p>
		<p>In <measure type="value"><date when="1986">1986</date></measure>, masters triathletes (i.e. &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure>) represented <measure type="value"><num>31</num></measure> of the total field for the males and <measure type="value"><num>23</num></measure> of the total field for females, while</p>
		<p>Total time records and corresponding split times for male and female age-groups at the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon are presented in Table 1. The results clearly show that the best master age-group performances have been set during the last <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure>, and <measure type="value"><num>eight</num></measure> of them have been set in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure>. An exceptional performance can be seen in the male <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <num atMost="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> total time record that was been set by the <measure type="value"><num>6</num></measure> times HawaiiIronman triathlon winner, Dave Scott, who returned to competition in <measure type="value"><date when="1994">1994</date></measure> at <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of age, after <measure type="value"><num>several</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> break from the race. Table 2.</p>
		<p>The changes across the years in total time gender differences between the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> female and top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> male subdivided by different age groups are presented in Figure 5. There was no significant change in gender difference across the years within the age group <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <num atMost="39">39</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> (r</p>
		<p>The main findings of the present study were first that the participation of masters triathletes at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon increased during the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> period. Second, during that period, female triathletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> and male triathletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>significantly improved their swimming, cycling, running and total time performances in the most recent years, relative to performances recorded at the beginning of the time period studied. Third, gender differences in total Ironman triathlon time decreased over the last <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for masters age-groups while it remained stable for the young age-group, <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <num atMost="39">39</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure>. Our data suggest that similar trends have occurred in Ironman triathlon racing over the last <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> and we can expect that the participation of female master will continue to increase in the future to soon reach <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> of the total female field. Different factors could be used to explain the increase in participation of masters Ironman triathletes. With the increase in life expectancy and training facilities, such as specific masters programs, the increased participation of older athletes described may be a reflection that these athletes, who are perhaps retired, have more available time and resources at their disposal to train and therefore to compete. The relative increase in participation of older Ironman triathletes could result from a relative decrease in Ironman triathletes in the younger age groups (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <num atMost="39">39</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>). Younger triathletes maybe more and more attracted by shorter distances such as short distance and<measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure>-Ironman distance triathlons. Indeed, since <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2000">2000</date></measure> short distance triathlon (<measure type="value"><num>1.5</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>40</num></measure> run) became an Olympic sport and it may have increased the popularity of the short distance especially in the young triathlete field. With advancing age, athletes naturally move towards longer distances where endurance capacities play a greater role in performance than maximal oxygen consumption. It has been suggested that enjoyment, health, fitness benefits, and social factors are the primary drivers for sport involvement with advancing age (Shaw &amp; Ostrow 2005). For masters triathletes that are more achievement-oriented, there is no doubt that competition, personal challenge and skill development may also be strong reasons for their participation in ultra-endurance events. However, among older triathletes, the distinction between people who started training in triathlon later in life (i.e. after <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> age) and people who participated in triathlon at a younger age is not known.</p>
		<p>The present results show that swimming, cycling, running and total performance times decreased over the <measure type="value"><num>25</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> periods studied for male triathletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> yrs age and female triathletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> age. Several reasons may explain the improved performance of masters triathletes, such as a greater participation of the older age groups, which would increase the probability of finding better triathletes in these age groups, increased training facilities for older people, and increases in the competitive spirit in these older groups. These last years, the age-related declines in total Ironman triathlon performance with advancing age until <measure type="interval"><num atMost="70">70</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> of age was about <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="12">12</num><num atMost="13">13</num></measure> per <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> for males and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="14">14</num> <num atMost="15">15</num></measure> per <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> for females, respectively. These values are in accordance with those found by Lepers &amp; %-% Cattagni (2011) for the New-York marathon running, but appear greater compared to those found in <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultra-marathon running (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="7">7</num> <num atMost="8">8</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure></p>
		<p>per <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> for males and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="9">9</num> <num atMost="10">10</num></measure> per <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> for females), by Knechtle et al. (2011). These findings may be explained by the shorter-% duration of <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running compared to Ironman triathlon, and the different level of competitiveness between the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> events: regional one for the <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running World Championship for Ironman triathlon. Our data also confirm previous observations (Bernard et al. vs. 2010, Lepers et al. 2010) showing a lesser age-related decline in cycling performance compared with running and swimming performances in triathlon. Physiological (e.g. concentric muscle contractions) and mechanical (e.g. relation between mechanical power output and velocity, non-weight bearing aspect) specificities of cycling compared with the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> other disciplines may be explained by the lower age-related decline in cycling performance ( Bernard et al. 2010, Lepers et al. 2010). In the context of health promotion, this finding suggests that cycling may represent an optimal activity with advancing age.</p>
		<p>The question of whether the masters triathletes have reached their limits in Ironman triathlon performance can therefore be raised, at least for the age-group categories studied (i.e. between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <num atMost="69">69</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> for males and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <num atMost="69">69</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> for females). For marathon running, it has been</p>
		<p><!-- case not supported: one atomic value expressed with different values and units --><!-- The current Hawaii Ironman triathlon record is <measure type="value"><num>8:54:202</num></measure> for females and <measure type="value"><num>8:04:08</num></measure> for males (see Table 2), corresponding to a gender gap of <measure type="value"><num>10.3</num></measure>.  -->The present results showed that for masters triathletes, the gender differences in Ironman triathlon performance times % decreased over the last <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, suggesting that masters females have reduced the gap to males. During these last years, gender differences in total event performance times remained slightly greater for age groups &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="54">54</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> compared to youngest age groups. This finding corroborates the results of Lepers &amp; Maffiuletti (2011) who showed that gender differences in Ironman triathlon performance times analyzed from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2006">2006</date> to <date to-iso="2008">2008</date></measure> increased with advancing age from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="55">55 </num><measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure>. In contrast, it has been shown that gender difference in New-York marathon running performances did not significantly change across this age group over the past <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> (Lepers &amp; Cattagni 2011). Ironman triathlon is a newer ultra-endurance event with less participants compared to the NYC Marathon, which may explain why gender differences across the ages groups in Ironman triathlon are currently similar to those that were observed for marathon <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> ago.</p>
		<p>There is no doubt that gender differences for older Ironman triathletes would still diminish in the future as it has been observed for marathon running because there is no real evidence that the age-related declines in physiological function differ between males and females. Age-related changes in the physiological determinants of endurance and ultra-endurance performance (e.g. maximal oxygen uptake, lactate threshold, and running economy) between males and females have not received considerable attention. For example, Holloszy and Kohrt (1995) suggested that the relative rates of decline in maximal oxygen consumption with age are similar between the sexes. However, further investigations are required in order to analyse the age-related declines in other physiological parameters such lactate threshold and running economy in males and females.</p>
		<p>Most healthcare providers would agree that racing an Ironman triathlon after <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of age is not good for the body. But most older</p>
		<p>Ironman triathletes will say that training for an Ironman triathlon is one of the healthiest things they can do (Wortley &amp; Islas 2011). Where should the limits be set? If masters athletes performed at such a high-level for so long, it is reasonable to expect that those destined to maintain that intensity could do so because they remained largely injury-free ( Knobloch et al. 2008). The exponential increase in participation of masters athletes especially in the female field in ultra-endurance sporting events such as Ironman triathlon represents an immense opportunity to learn how the aging process is related to physical performance. However, the remarkable growth in ultra-endurance older athletes and varying levels of fitness also represent unique challenges to sports medicine professionals because these individuals are particularly exposed to overuse injuries ( Egermann at al. 2003). A framework for pre-participation evaluation, training program and injury prevention is required to help older athletes reach their participation and performance goals injury free i.e. to maximise the benefits and minimize the risks (Marr 2011). We have much to learn from these ultra-endurance masters athletes that can pursue their passion with greater health and safety once we gain a greater understanding of them (Wortley &amp; Islas 2011).</p>
		<p>Age and ultra-endurance performance</p>
		<p>Age (Dordr). Author manuscript</p>
		<p>Page /</p>
		<p>The participation of older triathletes at the World Ironman triathlon championship has increased over the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> period and it willprobably still grow in the future in Hawaii and other Ironman triathlons worldwide. During that period master triathletes have shown relative improvements of their performances in the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> disciplines and in total event times. The gender differences in Ironman triathlon performance have progressively decreased over the last <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for older age-groups suggesting that female masters triathletes have reduced the gap to males. The question whether older triathletes have yet reached limits in their performance during Ironman triathlon should therefore be raised. Further studies investigating training regimes, competition experience or socio-demographic factors are needed to gain better insights into the phenomenon of the relative improvement in ultra-endurance performance with advancing age.</p>
		<p>Total number of finishers at the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon and number of finishers of each sex from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> to <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>.</p>
		<p>Linear regressions defining the percentages of finishers within different age groups across the period of <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> through <date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>, for females (Panel A) and for males (Panel B). All the slopes of the linear regressions were significantly different (P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>) from <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>.</p>
		<p>Changes in performance ratios for swimming, cycling, running and total times across the years for top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> finishers in each male age group. A performance ratio equal to <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> corresponded to the performance of the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> finishers of the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <num atMost="39">39</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> age group. Solid lines represent</p>
		<p>No funding has been received for this work from the NIH, Wellcome Trust, HHMI or others.</p>
		<p>The authors have no conflict of interests to report.</p>
	</text>
</tei>