<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
        <encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.4" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-13T02:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>As a common feature in strongly correlated electron systems including high-transition-temperature (high-T c ) superconductors, the superconducting (SC) phase emerges adjacent to the antiferromagnetic (AF) phase on carrier doping. The AF order parameter vanishes by carrier doping, and the SC phase commonly manifests as a dome in the electronic phase diagram. On further carrier doping, the normal metallic state approaches a Fermi liquid state. This scenario is also seen in high-T c cuprates and several iron-based pnictides. In fact, a very close analogy between cuprates and pnictides such as Ba(Fe 1−x Co x ) 2 As 2 (Ba122 series)<!-- [1][2][3] --> was suggested in the electronic phase diagram<!-- [4] -->. The AF state appearing in an undoped or lightly doped regime is a stripe-type spin-density-wave (SDW) state<!-- [5] --> arising from interband nesting between hole and electron pockets, which is indicative of a superconducting mechanism via AF fluctuations <!--[6,7]-->. The nesting mechanism is supported by various experiments in the Ba122 series, in which an optimal doping level is located at the AF phase boundary, and therefore AF fluctuations are predominant even in the SC phase. However, LaFeAsO 1−x F x (La1111 series)<!-- [8]--> -->, a prototype of iron-based high-T c pnictides, has an optimal doping level away from the AF boundary and the SC dome is separated from the AF phase boundary, as shown in Fig. 1(a) <!--[8,9]-->. Relatively high T c (∼ <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>) is maintained even in a F-overdoped regime (x ∼ <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num></measure>). These features would lend credence to an electron-phonon mechanism via orbital fluctuations <!--[10,11]-->, another superconducting mechanism that is in debate with the AF fluctuation mechanism.</p>
		<p>The unique features of LaFeAsO 1−x F x are highlighted by the newly-synthesized 1111 compounds CeFeAsO 1−x H x <!--(Ref. [12])--> and LaFeAsO 1−x H x (Ref. * Email:naoki@fujiwara.h.kyoto-u.ac.jp <!--[13]-->). In these compounds, protons act as H − as well as F − , and O 2− can be replaced with H − up to x ∼ <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num></measure>. In the H-overdoped regime (x ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.2">0.2</num></measure>), LaFeAsO 1−x H x undergoes a second superconducting state as shown in Fig. 1(a). Intriguingly, the first SC dome is very similar between F and H doping, suggesting that H doping supplies the same amount of electrons as F doping. The robustness of the second dome was confirmed by ac susceptibility measurements. The SC volume fractions for <measure type="list"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples are almost <measure type="value"><num>100</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>The question is why the double SC domes manifest in this compound and what is the origin of the second SC dome. The primary purpose of this study was to investigate the second SC dome on a microscopic level by using the nuclear-magnetic-resonance (NMR) technique, but we unexpectedly discovered that a new AF phase follows the second SC dome on further H doping, as described below. We investigate the anomalous phase diagram having the double SC domes and <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> AF phases from both experimental and theoretical viewpoints.</p>
		<p>The H-overdoped samples of LaFeAsO 1−x H x (x =<measure type="list"><num>0.53</num>, <num>0.58</num> and <num>0.625</num></measure>) were prepared for the present measurements. The H doping level was analyzed by thermal desorption spectroscopy. The doping level observed by thermal desorption spectroscopy was almost the same with the nominal one for x ≤ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.30">0.30</num></measure>, whereas the deviation between them (∆x) became large with increasing x. For x ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.50">0.50</num></measure>, ∆x reached ∼ <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num></measure>. The powder samples were analyzed by x-ray diffraction. No crystallographical anomalies were observed for each doping level and the lattice constants changed monotonously with increasing x. The SC volume fractions of the <measure type="list"><num>53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>58</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> doped samples were less than <measure type="list"><num>12</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, and <num>16</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, respectively. In the phase diagram, T c s are plotted against the nominal doping level for the samples with the volume fraction of more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. <!--[5,9]-->. The superconducting transition temperatures (Tc) of LaFeAsO1−xFx and LaFeAsO1−xHx were determined from resistivity measurements (closed and open circles) <!--[8,13]--> and the detuning of the NMR tank circuit (triangles). The AF ordering temperature for the heavily H-doped regime (closed blue squares) was determined from the linewidth of the 1 H NMR spectra ing to the large demagnetization when cooled from the metallic state to the SC state. The shifts are plotted as percentages in Figs. 1(b)−1(d) for the <measure type="list"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, and <num>62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples, respectively. One can find the largest shift for the <measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples which mark the optimal T c .</p>
		<p>The 75 As NMR (I = <measure type="value"><num>3/2</num></measure>) spectra for the powder samples are illustrated in Fig. 2(a). The satellite signals (I z = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-3/2">−3/2</num> ⇔ <num atMost="-1/2">−1/2</num></measure> and I z = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1/2">1/2</num> ⇔ <num atMost="3/2">3/2</num></measure>) spread in a wide region of the applied field (H ) depending on the angle between H and the principal axis of the electric field gradient (EFG) V zz at 75 As sites <!--[14]-->. The V zz direction is perpendicular to FeAs planes for iron-based pnictides, and the value is proportional to the nuclear quadrupole frequency ν Q . The central signal (I z = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-1/2">−1/2</num> ⇔ <num atMost="1/2">1/2</num></measure>) splits in <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> edges owing to a large ν Q (∼ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> − <num atMost="11">11</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="MHz">MHz</measure></measure>). The resonance signals should be symmetric with respect to the central signals, and thus the satellite signals (I z = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1/2">1/2</num> ⇔ <num atMost="3/2">3/2</num></measure>) should be observable at high fields. Unfortunately, the satellite signals overlap the 199 La signals (I =<measure type="value"><num>5/2</num></measure>) at the NMR frequency of <measure type="value"><num>35.1</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="MHz">MHz</measure></measure>, as shown in Fig. 2(b). In an ideal case, a central peak (I z = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="- 1 2">− 1 2</num> ⇔ <num atMost="1 2">1 2</num></measure> ) and <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> satellite edges <!--( I z = ± 1 2 ⇔ ± 3 2 and ± 3 2 ⇔ ± 5 2 )--> should be observable for 199 La owing to quadrupole interaction; however, some distribution of EFG makes the edges unclear and the line shape looks like a single broad peak. The relative intensity of the 199 La signals is apparently larger than that of the 75 As signals because the former signals are distributed in a narrow H region owing to small quadrupole interaction.</p>
		<p>where V yy and V xx represent EFGs in FeAs planes, increases with increasing x. On H doping, the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> edges at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="48">48</num>-<num atMost="50">50</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_FIELD_STRENGTH" unit="kOe">kOe</measure></measure> become an asymmetric peak, and the satellite signal at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="41">41</num>-<num atMost="42">42</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_FIELD_STRENGTH" unit="kOe">kOe</measure></measure> becomes unclear. The evolution is caused by the increase in η as seen from the powderpattern simulations in Fig. 2(c). We followed the procedure in Ref. 15 to simulate the powder patterns. The values of η are estimated to be <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.1">0.1</num>-<num atMost="0.2">0.2</num></measure> for the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>-<num atMost="40">40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples, whereas they are ∼<measure type="value"><num>0.6</num></measure> for the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="53">53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>-<num atMost="62.5">62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples. The increase in η is characteristic of the H-overdoped regime; for LaFeAsO 1−x F x , ν Q , namely, V zz increases linearly on F doping, and η remains almost unchanged. The EFGs are determined from the surrounding ions and d electrons in FeAs planes: the contribution of the former remains unchanged on H doping considering the lattice parameters, and thus the increase in η is attributable to the in-plane anisotropy coming from the differentiation of the orbital weight among the d xy , d yz , and d zx orbitals at each Fe site. We will discuss the possibility of orbital ordering later.</p>
		<p>Another remarkable feature of the heavily H-doped regime (x ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.58">0.58</num></measure>) is the revival of some AF ordering, as shown in Fig. 3(a). The broadening of the line shape is not observed for the <measure type="list"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples, whereas it is remarkable at low temperatures for the <measure type="value"><num>62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples. We confirmed the broadening from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure> H NMR (I = <measure type="value"><num>1/2</num></measure>) spectra. The 1 H signals are free from nuclear quadrupole interaction owing to I = <measure type="value"><num>1/2</num></measure>, and thus are sensitive only to AF ordering. Figure 3(b) shows <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> H NMR spectra for the H-overdoped samples. The <measure type="value"><num>62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples exhibit considerable broadening at low temperatures even though the linewidth for the <measure type="value"><num>53</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples is almost unchanged. O 2− can be replaced only with H − in LaFeAsO, and therefore the broadening of the <measure type="value"><num>62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples is intrinsic and demonstrates the emergence of some AF ordering. The ordering temperature is determined from the temperature dependence of the linewidth, as shown in Fig. 3(c). Unlike the AF ordering in the lightly doped regime, the AF ordering in the heavily H-doped regime is not spatially uniform. If the ordered moments were spatially uniform, the line shape would be of the rectangular type <!--[16]-->. We calculated the internal field at a proton nucleus for the nearest neighboring <measure type="value"><num>42</num></measure> iron sites assuming the stripe-type spin configuration in the neighboring FeAs planes and assuming the same spin alignment to the direction normal to the FeAs planes. From the internal fields indicated by arrows in Fig. 3(b), the maximal spin moments are estimated to be <measure type="value"><num>1.3</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_MOMENT" unit="µB">µ B</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>2.4</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_MOMENT" unit="µB">µ B</measure></measure> for the <measure type="list"><num>58</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>62.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples, respectively. These values are remarkably larger than those in the first AF state (<measure type="value"><num>0.36</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_MOMENT" unit="µB">µ B</measure></measure> )<!-- [5] -->. The spin moments in the second AF state are also larger than those for other pnictides (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.3">0.3</num>-<num atMost="0.9">0.9</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_MOMENT" unit="µB">µ B</measure></measure> ) <!--[17][18][19]--> and are comparable to those for K x Fe 2−y Se 2 (<measure type="value"><num>∼2.8</num><measure type="MAGNETIC_MOMENT" unit="µB">µ B</measure></measure> ) <!--[20]-->. The emergence of the second AF ordering is very anomalous for strongly correlated electron systems because, in general, carrier doping breaks AF ordering.</p>
		<p>Next, we investigated the AF ordering from the relaxation rate per temperature 1/T 1 T . The quantity gives a measure of AF fluctuations and is enhanced under strong AF fluctuations. Figures 4(a) and 4(b) show 1/T 1 T of 75 As for the F-underdoped and H-overdoped regimes, respectively, measured at the edge R in Fig. 2(a). For the <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> H-doped samples, 1/T 1 T is almost the same as that for the <measure type="value"><num>14</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> F-doped samples at high temperatures above T c . On H doping up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="40">40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, 1/T 1 T is enhanced remarkably and shows almost the same T dependence as that for the F-underdoped regime (see the <measure type="value"><num>8</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> F-doped samples) <!--[21][22][23][24]-->, indicating that AF fluctuations revive with the approach of the second AF phase on further H doping. The results are consistent with the broadening of the NMR spectra for the heavily H-doped samples.</p>
		<p>The present NMR results revealed the unusual AF ordering. To understand the phenomenon, we calculated the spin susceptibility based on the tight binding model under random phase approximation (RPA). For each doping level, AF ordering is potentially possible for the Coulomb interaction coupling (U ) stronger than the critical coupling U c . Figure 5(a) shows the two-dimensional (2D) color maps of the spin susceptibility calculated for U a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> smaller than U c . For the undoped samples, the nesting between electron and hole pockets, as shown by the arrow in the illustration of Fermi surfaces for x = <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure>, makes a peak at (π, 0) on the 2D map, causing the first AF ordering. The (π, 0) nesting weakens and the other nesting between electron pockets shown by the arrow in the illustration for x = <measure type="value"><num>0.4</num></measure> develops on H doping. The peak position deviates from (π, 0), suggesting an incommensurate SDW state. The incommensurate state is consistent with the cusp-type <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure> H-NMR spectra. As shown in Fig. 5(b), the doping dependence of U c exhibits an upward convex curve due to the change in the nesting condition, leading to the reappearance of AF ordering at x &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.25">0.25</num></measure> if the effective coupling U ef f is constant. In fact, U ef f would moderately decrease with increasing x, because the Kanamori theory predicts <!--[25]-->, where N (x) is the density of states at the Fermi level, and it slightly increases with increasing x in the band calculations <!--[13]-->. U ef f (x) can be approximated by a linear function of x under the condition U N (x) 1. As shown in Fig. 5, one can draw the line of U ef f which crosses the U c curve at <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> AF quantum critical points, and thus Figure 1a is reproduced. In Fig.5, we used <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> experimentally-determined quantum critical points, x ∼ <measure type="list"><num>0.04</num> and ∼ <num>0.58</num></measure>, to draw the line.</p>
		<p>The anisotropy η is enhanced on H doping prior to the second AF ordering. According to the band calculation <!--[13]-->, the partial density of states associated with the d xz,yz and d xy orbitals is almost unchanged for <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.4">0.4</num> ≤ x ≤ <num atMost="0.625">0.625</num></measure>. Furthermore, mixing of the d orbitals tends to make η small. Therefore, the enhancement of η on H doping [ Fig. 2(b)] suggests spontaneous alignment of the d orbitals at each Fe site, being indicative of some orbital ordering. Strong orbital fluctuations can be induced by the charge quadrupole interaction coupling g originating from the many-body effect by U beyond the mean-field level in addition to the electron-phonon interaction.The orbital ordering is realized when the effective coupling g ef f is larger than the critical coupling g c . The doping dependence of g c is also a convex curve, as shown in Fig. 5(c), and therefore orbital ordering tends to manifest in a heavily H-doped regime similarly to the AF ordering. The value of g ef f is estimated to be ∼<measure type="value"><num>0.9</num></measure> for the heavily H-doped regime because the orbital ordering is expected to occur for x ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.53">0.53</num></measure> in the present experiments.</p>
	</text>
</tei>