<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:25+0000">
                    <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting
                        information from scholarly documents
                    </ref>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>Although the nucleus of comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) will safely pass Mars in <measure type="value"><date when="2014-10">October 2014</date></measure>, the dust in the coma and tail will more closely approach the planet. Using a dynamical model of comet dust, we estimate the impact fluence. Based on our nominal model no impacts are expected at Mars. Relaxing our nominal model's parameters, the fluence is no greater than ∼ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10^-7">10 −7</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure> for grain radii larger than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure>. Mars orbiting spacecraft are unlikely to be impacted by large dust grains, but Mars may receive as many as ∼ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10^7">10 7</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="grain">grains</measure></measure>, or ∼ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="100">100</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="kg">kg</measure></measure> of total dust. We also estimate the flux of impacting gas molecules commonly observed in comet comae.</p>
        <p>Comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) will pass Mars with <!--a close approach distance of 1.35 ± <measure type="value"><num>0.05 × 10 5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>-->, and a relative speed of <measure type="value"><num>55.96</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km.s^-1">km s −1</measure></measure> on <measure type="interval"><date type="base" when="2014-10-19T18:29Z">2014 Oct 19 at 18:29</date>±<num type="range">:03</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min"> UTC</measure></measure> (3-σ uncertainties; Farnocchia et al. 2014). The nucleus will miss the planet, its moons, and orbiting spacecraft. However, given the right combination of ejection velocity, ejection time, and response to radiation pressure, dust grains from the comet can reach the planet. Farnocchia et al. (2014) predict that Mars will miss the comet's orbit by <measure type="value"><num>2.7 × 10 4</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> at <measure type="value"><date when="2014-10-19T20:10Z">20:10 UTC</date></measure>. This second close approach potentially reduces the energy required to place dust grains on impacting orbits. We present models of the dust and gas based on the summary of the comet's activity by Farnham et al. (in preparation) and estimate the impact hazard for Mars and its satellites as well as the comet gas flux at Mars.</p>
        <p>To assess the impact hazard, we generated <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> simulations of <measure type="value"><num>10 9</num></measure> particles each, picked from broad parameter ranges. These raw simulations act as guides to determine which combinations of size, ejection speed, and ejection time may result in impacts. Next, we define more limited parameter sets that are carefully chosen to match known parameters of the comet. We select and weight particles from the raw simulations that match those sets, and use them to estimate the fluence at Mars. Below we describe our dynamical model, the raw simulations, and <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> parameter sets used to estimate the impact hazard.</p><p>The circumstances of the encounter are simulated with the dynamical model of Kelley (2006). For this study we msk@astro.umd.edu use the JPL ephemeris solution #46 ( Farnocchia et al. 2014). In order to reduce the required computational time, we modified the model to use the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-body (Keplerian) propagation functions from NASA's Navigation and Ancillary Information Facility SPICE toolkit. Dust grains are parameterized by β, the ratio of the force from solar radiation pressure to the force from solar gravity: β = 0.57Q pr /ρa, where Q pr is the radiation pressure efficiency, ρ is the grain density in units of g cm −3 , and a is the grain radius in units of µm ( Burns et al. 1979). In the Keplerian solution, the gravitational force from the Sun is reduced by the factor (1 − β).</p>
        <p>The magnitude of the error introduced by neglecting planetary perturbations can be estimated by comparing <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>-ejection velocity syndynes (lines of constant β with variable ejection times; Finson &amp; Probstein 1968) generated using the Keplerian solution to those generated using the original code. The distances between the syndynes define the error. For grains ejected up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="4">4</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> before the closest approach, the error is at most <measure type="interval"><num atMost="300">300</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> for dust found within <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10^6">10 6</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> from the nucleus. We also considered whether the gravitational pull of Mars is significant. Ignoring the atmosphere, particles grazing the surface are displaced &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="100">100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> at closest approach, and the cross-section enhancement factor from gravitational focusing by Mars is <measure type="value"><num>1.008</num></measure> (Jones &amp; Poole 2007). The Keplerian solution is sufficient for our purposes.</p>
        <p>Simulation 1 contains <measure type="value"><num>10 9</num></measure> particles selected from the following parameters, based on observations of the comet with a generous conservative margin: ages range uniformly from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num> to <num atMost="4">4</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yr</measure></measure> (out to r h = <measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>); expansion speeds range uniformly from <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> to v ref (a/1 mm) −0.5 (r h /5 AU) −1 , where v ref = <measure type="value"><num>1.9</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m.s^-1">m s −1</measure></measure> is the expansion speed of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> grains ejected at <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> from the Sun; ejection velocities are radial and isotropically distributed around the nucleus; and, radii are selected from a distribution uniform in log-space (dn/d log a ∝ 1) ranging from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> to <num atMost="10^4">10 4</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure>. The logarithmic distribution ensures our final results will have a statistically uniform representation of each size decade. For the conversion from radius to β we assume a grain density of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="g.cm^-3">g cm −3</measure></measure> , and Q pr = <measure type="value"><num>1</num></measure>. J.Y. Li et al. (in preparation) imaged Siding Spring at <measure type="list"><num>4.6</num>, <num>3.8</num>, and <num>3.3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> from the Sun with the Hubble Space Telescope WFC3 instrument. The high spatial resolution of the images (<measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="RESOLUTION" unit="mas.pixel^-1">mas per pixel</measure></measure>, corresponding to ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num> <measure type="RESOLUTION" unit="km.pixel^-1">km per pixel</measure></measure>) resolve the inner coma, and allow investigations of the dust grain expansion velocities. Farnham et al. (in preparation) analyzed those images and found that the dust that comprises the bulk of the coma and tail has speeds best matched by v ref (a/1 mm) −0.6 (r h /5 AU) −1.5 , for v ref = <measure type="value"><num>0.42</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m.s^-1">m s −1</measure></measure>. Grains with these speeds are a subset of simulation 1.</p>
        <p>For an alternative scenario we consider the analysis of the Hubble images by Li et al.. Using the distance from the nucleus to the outer edge of the coma in the sunward direction, they find that the heliocentric distance dependence of the resulting speeds follow v ej ≈ 800 r −2 h m s −1 for r h = <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3.3">3.3</num> − <num atMost="4.6">4.6</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>, assuming β = <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="grain">grains</measure></measure> (v ref ≈ <measure type="value"><num>0.76</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m.s^-1">m s −1</measure></measure> ). Speeds based on this relationship for r h &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="2.0">2.0</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> exceed those in simulation 1. Therefore, we ran a second <measure type="value"><num>10 9</num></measure> particle simulation (simulation 2) with speeds picked uniformly from 0 to v ref (a/1 mm) −0.5 (r h /5 AU) −2 for v ref = <measure type="value"><num>1.9</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m.s^-1">m s −1</measure></measure>. However, we note that these speeds, derived from some of the fastest moving grains in the coma, are much higher than the Farnham et al. results, derived from the coma and tail morphologies. Analyses based on the Li et al. speeds will serve as upper-limit cases for fast moving grains not accounted for in the Farnham et al. approach. In order to transform the simulations into an impact hazard at Mars, we first rotate the position vectors from the ecliptic J2000 coordinate frame into a reference frame defined at closest approach: the x-axis is given by the comet-Mars position vector, the y-axis by the cometMars velocity vector, and the z-axis by the right-hand rule. Simulations 1 and 2 projected into this reference frame is shown in Fig. 1. The relative timing of grains arriving at Mars is based on their y-axis position; <measure type="value"><num>10 5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> corresponds to a time difference of <measure type="value"><num>29.8</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>. We then weight each particle to remove the bias introduced by our raw simulation's grain size distribution, and to provide a real estimate of the grain's frequency of occurrence in the comet coma. The particle weights are based on the parameter sets in Table 1.</p>
        <p>Set A is the nominal case, directly based on the results of Farnham et al. (in preparation). Sets B, C, and D are variations chosen to provide upper-limit estimates on the impacting dust. First, consider that the tail analysis of Farnham et al. best describes the smallest grains (a <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure>) and closest heliocentric distances (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure> ≤ r h <num atMost="5">5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>), and is extrapolated to larger a and r h. Therefore, as an alternative scenario, we have defined set B using a radius and heliocentric distance dependence in closer agreement to theoretical predictions:</p>
        <p>Set C has the same parameters as set B, but the dust is shifted closer to Mars according to the ephemeris's 3σ error ellipse ( Farnocchia et al. 2014). In our closest approach reference frame described above, the dust is displaced by ∆X = <measure type="value"><num>4471</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>, ∆Z = <measure type="value"><num>−1722</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>.</p>
        <p>Set D is based on our nominal case, but uses simulation 2 and the ejection speeds found by Li et al. (in preparation). As described above, these speeds are representative of the fastest moving grains, and not the whole coma.</p>
        <p>The future activity of comet Siding Spring is challenging to predict, but must be based on our present set of observations. <!--The gas production rates, Q(CO 2 ) = (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">3.52</num> ± <num type="range">0.03</num></measure>) × <measure type="value"><num>10 26</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="molecules.s^−1">molecules s −1</measure></measure> at r h = <measure type="value"><num>3.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>, and Q(H 2 O) = (1.7 ± 1) × <measure type="value"><num>10 27</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="molecules.s^−1">molecules s −1</measure></measure> at r h = <measure type="value"><num>2.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>, were measured by Farnham et al. (in preparation) and Bodewits et al. (2014), respectively, based on photometric imaging of the comet with the Spitzer Space Telescope and the Swift satellite.--> We make <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> predictions of the gas production rate at Mars, based on these measurements of CO 2 and H 2 O.</p>
        <p>First, we propagate the measured CO 2 production rate from <measure type="value"><num>3.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>1.4</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>, then compute the water production rate using an assumed CO 2-to-H 2 O mixing ratio. The mean mixing ratio, based on Table 1 To estimate the gas fluence and peak volume density at the top of the Martian atmosphere, we modeled the coma with a modified three-generation Haser model (Festou 1981; Combi et al. 2004;Bodewits et al. 2011), considering H 2 O, CO 2 , CO, and CN. The relative abundances of CO and CN are based on the mean CO-to-H 2 O mixing ratio (<measure type="value"><num>0.07</num></measure>) from A' Hearn et al. (2012), and the "typical" composition of dynamically new comets from A' Hearn et al. (1995). We also include OH, H, and O as photodissociation products of H 2 O. Our results are given in Table 2.</p>
        <p>The raw simulations provide a guide to understanding what combination of grain size, ejection velocity, and age results in an impact hazard at Mars. We define impacts at Mars as any particle found within a distance of <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10000">10,000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> from the center of the planet. This distance includes the orbit of Phobos (<measure type="value"><num>9400</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> semi-major axis), and the apoapsis of the MAVEN spacecraft's nominal science orbit (<measure type="value"><num>6000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>; provided by NASA JPL). We also investigate a <measure type="value"><num>5000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> region centered on the posi Table 1 Model parameters and results.</p>
        <p>Set A Set B Set C Set D</p><p>Gas production rate at <measure type="value"><num>3.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>, Qg (kg s −1 ) <measure type="value"><num>25.7</num></measure> tion of Deimos (<measure type="value"><num>23,000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> semi-major axis) at the time of closest approach. A third region of interest is based on the <measure type="value"><num>48,000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> apoapsis of MAVEN 's orbit, assuming a <measure type="value"><num>5</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="week">week</measure></measure> delay in science operations. Given these criteria, the grain parameters that yield impacts are presented in Fig. 2. The only particles in simulation 1 that reach the Martian system are those ejected with speeds of a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m.s^-1">meters per second</measure></measure>, have radii of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.7">0.7</num>-<num atMost="3.6">3.6</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, and are ejected at least <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yr</measure></measure> prior to the encounter.</p>
        <p>3.2. Impact Hazard For each parameter set, the impact hazards are computed by taking the set of particles found in each region of interest, removing those speeds outside the set's range, and weighting remaining particles according to the set's total production rate, grain size distribution, etc. Table 1 lists, for Mars, the raw number of impacting grains (i.e., before particle weighting), the impact fluence (i.e., after particle weighting), and the start and stop times of the hazard. No impacts are expected based on our nominal model, nor the v ej ∝ r −2 h model (sets A and D) because the ejection speeds of dust grains at r h &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> are too low to place particles within the vicinity of Mars (Fig. 2). In addition, displacing the comet dust in these <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> models according to the ephemeris 3-σ uncertainty ellipse does not result in any impacts.</p>
        <p>In order to attain impacting particle trajectories, higher ejection speeds are needed at r h &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="3">3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>. This requirement is accomplished with the size-r h-speed relationship of parameter set B, resulting in a total fluence of <measure type="value"><num>1 × 10 −7</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure>. Based on the comet's current predicted closest approach time, the grains arrive between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-10-19T19:57Z">19:57</date> and <date to-iso="2014-10-19T20:17Z">20:17 UTC</date></measure> (time at Mars), nearly centered on the epoch at which Mars crosses the comet's orbital plane (Farnocchia et al. 2014). Note that nongravitational forces frequently act upon comet nuclei, but we can neglect these effects because the dust is ejected at heliocentric distances where activity and resulting nongravitational forces were low (see Fig. 5 of Farnocchia et al. 2014). However, the current nucleus ephemeris uncertainty is still valid for the dust. Displacing the dust in parameter set B closer to Mars (set C) shifts the arrival time <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> earlier and increases the fluence by a factor of <measure type="value"><num>4</num></measure>.</p>
        <p>The fluence results are summarized for Mars and MAVEN in Fig. 3. The grains are limited to <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num> to <num atMost="3">3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> in radius, due to the combined effects of radiation pressure, grain age, and ejection speed. The timing of the hazard at MAVEN 's distant apoapsis is <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> later than the hazard at Mars, and the fluences are a factor of <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> higher. In all simulations, the Deimos region of interest remained dust free. Gas outflow and nucleus gravity limits the size of dust grains that can be placed into heliocentric orbit. Meech &amp; Svore˘ n (2004) present the critical dust radius, a crit , that can be lifted off a spherical nucleus by estimating the drag force on a spherical grain, and integrating the resulting equation of motion,</p>
        <p>where µ is the atmoic weight of the driving gas, m H is the mass of hydrogen, Q is the gas production rate (molecules s −1 ), v th is the expansion speed of the gas, ρ g and ρ n are the grain and nucleus densities, R n is the nucleus radius, and G is the gravitation constant. Let v th = 0.6 (r h /3.8 AU) −0.5 km s −1 to be consistent with Farnham et al. (in preparation), and let the nucleus density be <measure type="value"><num>0.3</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="g.cm^-3">g cm −3</measure></measure>. The radius of the nucleus has not been measured, but Bodewits et al. (2014) estimate R &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.34">0.34</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> based on water projection rates from Swift photometry. Therefore we consider <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> values: <measure type="list"><num>0.5</num> and <num>2.0</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>. For our adopted parameters, CO 2 can lift grains larger than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> at heliocentric distances inside of <measure type="list"><num>14</num> and <num>8</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> for R n = <measure type="list"><num>0.5</num> and <num>2.0</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>, respectively. However, our parameter set ejection speeds only place particles on impacting trajectories for r h &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="11">11</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> (Fig. 2). Thus, given this simplistic model, an impact hazard may not be expected if the nucleus radius is ∼ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> or larger.</p>
        <p>Overall, we do not expect any impacts on Marsorbiting spacecraft. Based on the cross-sectional area of Mars and our <measure type="value"><num>10,000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> average fluence, the planet may receive up to ∼ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10^7">10 7</num></measure> grain impacts from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num>-to <num atMost="3">3</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>-radius grains, totaling ∼ <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="kg">kg</measure></measure>, based on our models. At most, a few impacts may be expected on Phobos ( <measure type="interval"><num atMost="100">100</num></measure>), and no impacts at Deimos. (in preparation) data, the same as our investigation, but with slightly different interpretations. They both predict little to no risk of impacts for the Mars-orbiting spacecraft, despite their independent approaches. In particular, Ye &amp; Hui (2014) used observations of Siding Spring and the similarly bright comet C/2012 S1 (ISON) to derive the dependence of ejection speed on size and r h :</p>
        <p>best matched their data, assuming a <measure type="value"><num>2.5</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>-radius nucleus and <measure type="value"><num>0.3</num>-<measure type="DENSITY" unit="g.cm^-3">g cm −3</measure></measure> dust, resulting in no impacts for a &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.1">0.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, and a fluence of <measure type="value"><num>2.6 × 10 −6</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure> for grains down to <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> in radius. In our parameterization, these speeds correspond to v ref = <measure type="value"><num>1.0</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m.s^-1">m s −1</measure></measure> , higher than our set B. Using their speeds and our production rate history, we find the same fluence, <measure type="value"><num>2 × 10 −6</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure> , but all impacts are millimeter sized. Finally, we compare our results to the natural background of meteoroids estimated for the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter. Over a <measure type="value"><num>5</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> period, the total fluence for meteoroids with a &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> is <measure type="value"><num>0.0021</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure> , and for a &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.1">0.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, it is <measure type="value"><num>3.1</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure> (Newell 2005 of magnitude smaller than these values, and we conclude the comet poses little additional hazard to the spacecraft.</p>
        <p>The neutral coma gases will enter the atmosphere with a relative velocity of <measure type="value"><num>56</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km.s^-1">km s −1</measure></measure>. The kinetic energies of these molecules greatly exceeds their dissociation energies, e.g., for H 2 O, the kinetic energy is <measure type="value"><num>293</num> <measure type="ENERGY" unit="eV">eV</measure></measure>, and the dissociation energy (H 2 O → OH + H) is <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="ENERGY" unit="eV">eV</measure></measure> (Darwent 1970). The upper atmosphere of Mars consists of CO 2 , with few percent contributions from N 2 and Ar, and trace amounts of several other species (Krasnopolsky 2002). The comet gases will collide with the Mars gases, and quickly dissociate into atoms, erasing any molecular trace of the comet in the Martian atmosphere. The peak total particle and kinetic energy fluxes in Table 2</p>
        <p>Based on the observations of Farnham et al. (in preparation) and Li et al. (in preparation), we simulated the coma and tail of comet Siding Spring for grains with radii between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure> and <num atMost="1">1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> (ρ = <measure type="value"><num>1.0</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="g.cm^-3">g cm −3</measure></measure> ), and particle ages out to <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>13</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>) before closest approach to Mars. We predict no dust impacts at Mars from the close flyby of the comet in <measure type="value"><date when="2014-10">October 2014</date></measure>. Variations of our nominal comet model suggest a total fluence of <measure type="value"><num>10 −7</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="grain.m^-2">grains m −2</measure></measure> is possible, with radii ranging from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num> to <num atMost="3">3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, and encounter times between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-10-19T19:52Z">19:52</date> and <date to-iso="2014-10-19T20:17Z">20:17 UTC</date></measure> (time at Mars). Mars orbiting spacecraft are unlikely to be impacted by any large dust grains, but Mars may receive as many as ∼ <measure type="value"><num>10 7</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="grain">grains</measure></measure> (∼ <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="kg">kg</measure></measure>). Following Vaubaillon et al. (2014), the meteor shower at Mars is an Earth-equivalent zenith hourly rate <measure type="value"><num>600</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="h^-1">h −1</measure></measure> (assuming a human perception correction factor of <measure type="value"><num>3</num></measure> given our meteor size range; Koschack &amp; Rendtel 1990). The gas coma will reach the upper atmosphere of Mars with peak fluxes of order <measure type="value"><num>10 12</num> <measure type="DIFFUSION_FLUX" unit="molecules.m^-2.s^-1">molecules m −2 s −1</measure></measure> , and the molecules will be quickly dissociated, due to the high impact speeds. This research was supported by a contract to the University of Maryland by the NASA JPL Mars Critical Data Products Program.</p>
        <p>The work of D. Farnocchia was conducted at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology under a contract with NASA.</p><p>Simulations were performed on the YORP cluster administered by the Center for Theory and Computation, part of the Department of Astronomy at the University of Maryland.</p>
        <p>This research made use of Astropy, a communitydeveloped core Python package for Astronomy (Astropy Collaboration et al. 2013).</p>
    </text>
</tei>
