<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.1" ident="GROBID" when="2016-02-29T12:30+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>The Near-Earth Object Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer (NEOWISE) mission observed comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> times at <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> as the comet approached Mars in <measure type="value"><date when="2014">2014</date></measure>. The comet is an extremely interesting target since its close approach to Mars in late <measure type="value"><date when="2014">2014</date></measure> will be observed by various spacecraft in-situ. The observations were taken in <measure type="list"><date when="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date>, <date when="2014-07">Jul.</date> and <date when="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure> when the comet was at heliocentric distances of <measure type="list"><num>3.82</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="au">AU</measure>, <num>1.88</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="au">AU</measure>, and <num>1.48</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="au">AU</measure></measure>. The level of activity increased significantly between the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-01">Jan.</date> and <date to-iso="2014-07">Jul.</date></measure> visits but then decreased by the time of the observations in <measure type="value"><date when="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure>, approximately <measure type="value"><num>4</num><measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure> prior to its close approach to Mars. In this work we calculate Af&#x3C1; values, and CO/CO 2 production rates.</p>
		<p>Comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) presents both risk and opportunity at its close approach to Mars on <measure type="value"><date when="2014-10-19">2014 Oct. 19</date></measure>. It will pass approximately <measure type="interval"><num type="base">135,000</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure> &#xB1; <num type="range">5000</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> from the planet's center (Farnocchia et al. 2014) -close enough for detailed observations by spacecraft at Mars but also close enough for ejected dust and gas to reach Mars' atmosphere, potentially affecting spacecraft in orbit. The potential risk posed by the dust has been downgraded through careful dynamical modeling. Early studies suggested relatively high amounts of dust would reach the Martian atmosphere (Ye &amp; Hui 2014; Moorhead et al. 2014). Later studies that included lower ejection velocities and radiation pressure effects showed only a low fluence of old, larger dust grains is expected to reach the atmosphere (Tricarico et al. 2014; Kelley et al. 2014). However, it is possible that the gas coma may sufficiently excite the atmosphere of Mars to cause increased drag on orbiting satellites (Yelle et al. 2014). The comet is also interesting in its own right as a long period comet on a near-parabolic retrograde orbit, bringing primitive material in from the Oort Cloud. In this paper we use data from the Near-Earth Object Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer reactivation (NEOWISE; Mainzer et al. 2014) mission to characterize the comet's activity on <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> occasions in <measure type="list"><date when="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date><date when="2014-07">Jul.</date> and <date when="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure> as the comet approached Mars. We derive dust and gas production rates using near-infrared wide-field images and examine the evolving morphology of the coma.</p>
		<p>The NEOWISE mission utilizes the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) spacecraft (Wright et al. 2010), which completed an all-sky survey at <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> wavelengths of <measure type="list"><num>3.4</num>, <num>4.6</num>, <num>12</num>, and <num>22</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2010-01">January</date> to <date to-iso="2010-08">August 2010</date></measure> using a <measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> cryogenically-cooled telescope. After the depletion of the spacecraft's solid hydrogen, the mission could still operate at the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> shortest wavelengths of <measure type="value"><num>3.6</num></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>. This phase of the mission was renamed NEOWISE (Mainzer et al. 2011) and continued for several months until <measure type="value"><date when="2011-02-01">Feb 1, 2011</date></measure> after which the spacecraft was placed into hibernation. The spacecraft was then reactivated in <measure type="value"><date when="2013-12">Dec 2013</date></measure> for the start of the NEOWISE reactivation mission (Mainzer et al. 2014 ). The telescope is conducting an all-sky survey in a low- Earth orbit, taking images of the sky every <measure type="value"><num>11</num><measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure><!-- issue #49 --><!-- at a solar elongation of &#x223C;<measure type="value"><num>92<measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">&#xB0;</measure>.5</num></measure>. The images have an effective exposure time of <measure type="value"><num>7.7</num><measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure>, and effective point-source full-width half-maxima (FWHM) of <measure type="value"><num>6<measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure> .25</num></measure>-->. There is approximately <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> overlap between successive frames, allowing for the linking of moving object detections. The images, which are <measure type="value"><num>47</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> on a side, undergo instrumental and astrometric calibration, followed by source extraction at at the Infrared Processing and Analysis Center (IPAC) at the California Institute of Technology (Wright et al. 2010). All data from the WISE prime mission in 2010 have been publicly released via NASA's Infrared Science Archive (IRSA) 1 , and the first data release from the NEOWISE reactivation mission will be in <measure type="value"><date when="2015-03">March 2015</date></measure> through IRSA. The motion of comet Siding Spring meant that it was observed by NEOWISE on <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> separate occasions, hereafter referred to as " visits " <!--, on <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-01-16">2014 Jan. 16</date>-<date to-iso="2014-01-17">17</date></measure>, <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-07-28">Jul. 28</date>-<date to-iso="2014-07-29">29</date></measure>, and <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-09-21">Sep. 21</date>-<date to-iso="2014-09-22">22</date></measure>-->. Observing details are given in Table 1.</p>
		<p>We used predicted positions from the Jet Propulsion Laboratory's Horizons service 2 and the Moving Object Search Tool 3 (Cutri et al. 2012) to identify the images covering comet Siding Spring. Trailing during each <measure type="value"><num>7.7</num><measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure> exposure was at most under than <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure>, which is significantly less than the FWHM. We coadded the images of the comet in the moving reference frame for each visit using the ICORE image co-addition package that includes outlier-rejection (Masci 2013). This improved the signal-to-noise ratio and resampled the pixel scale from <!-- issues 49 & 43--><!--<measure type="value"><num>2<measure type="ANGLE" unit="&#x2032;&#x2032;pixel-1">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure>.75</num><measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="&#x2032;&#x2032;pixel-1">&#x2032;&#x2032;pixel&#x2212;1</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>1<measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="&#x2032;&#x2032;pixel-1">&#x2032;&#x2032;pixel&#x2212;1</measure>.0</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="&#x2032;&#x2032;pixel-1">pixel&#x2212;1</measure></measure>-->. The coadded images were centered on the predicted position of the comet. Two-band color images of comet Siding Spring from each visit are shown in Figure 1. The comet appeared active at each visit.</p>
		<p>We used circular apertures with radii of <measure type="value"><num>11</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> to perform photometry on each coadded image. Counts were converted to fluxes using instrumental zero points using the same method as used for WISE catalog source data (Wright et al. 2010). The background was estimated and subtracted using the modal value in an aperture of at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1,4">1.4</num><measure type="SOLID_ANGLE" unit="square arcminute">square arcminutes</measure></measure> located &#x2265; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="am">&#x2032;</measure></measure> from the nucleus, and far from the coma. The dominant source of error is the uncertainty on the absolute calibration. We fit a reflected light model to the observed data at <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>, making the assumption that the flux observed is due to reflected light from dust grains, the grains have a neutral reflectance. The reflected light is thus effectively the solar flux scaled to the <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="μm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> signal. We neglected light reflected or emitted by the nucleus, the size of which is unknown at this time because it has been obscured by dust since discovery. If the nucleus is on the order of <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> in radius, it would contribute a <measure type="value"><num>few tenths</num> of a <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="µJy">&#xB5;Jy</measure></measure> to the fluxes observed during the <measure type="value"><date from-iso="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date></measure> visit when the comet was least active and the nucleus likely contributed the largest fraction of the light. This is significantly less than the uncertainty in the flux measurements and we conclude that the nucleus contributes a negligible amount of light. We also computed a theoretical thermal contribution to the flux by calculating the blackbody radiation that would be emitted by the quantity of dust estimated from the <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> flux. We used a Planck function and assumed an emissivity&#x223C;0.9, so that the temperature of the grains scaled as 286K &#xD7; r &#x2212;1/2 H . It is entirely possible that the grain spectral energy distribution is more complicated, but the singular data point at <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> only allows for a simplified dust model constraint. The measured fluxes for each visit are listed in Table 1 and shown in Figure 2 with the reflected light and predicted thermal light models.</p>
		<p>We converted the flux measured at <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> to the quantity Af &#x3C1; -a proxy for the dust production rate discussed in A'Hearn et al. (1984) -using equation 1.</p>
		<p>where A is the Bond albedo of the dust at the phase angle of observation, f is the filling factor of the dust grains within the aperture, &#x3C1; is the aperture size in cm, &#x2206; and r H are the geocentric and heliocentric distances in cm and AU, respectively, and F comet and F &#x2299; are the flux from the comet and the Solar flux at <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>, respectively. As before, we used <measure type="value"><num>11</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> radius apertures. We estimate the uncertainties on our measurements by examining the spread of results obtained when using apertures of radii <measure type="list"><num>9</num>, <num>11</num>, and <num>22</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="as">&#x2032;&#x2032;</measure></measure> since, ideally, the quantity calculated should be independent of chosen aperture size. However, it is quite possible that the spread in these values may in part be due to non-ideallized behavior, i.e. that the coma flux does not drop off as &#x3C1; &#x2212;1. Residuals from the removal of inertial background sources from the co-added image may contribute to the Af &#x3C1; uncertainty as well. We measure Af&#x3C1; as <measure type="interval"><num type="base">432</num> &#xB1; <num type="range">21</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> during the <measure type="value"><date when="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date></measure> visit, <measure type="interval"><num type="base">726</num> &#xB1; <num type="range">40</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> during the <measure type="value"><date when="2014-07">Jul.</date></measure> visit, and <measure type="interval"><num type="base">724</num> &#xB1; <num type="range">40</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> during the <measure type="value"><date when="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure> visit. These Af&#x3C1; values are provided for comparison with each other. The values are not corrected for phase angle effects since these effects are poorly constrained for infrared wavelengths, nor do the uncertainties include the component from the uncertainty in the absolute photometric calibration. We report these values in Table 1 and show how Af&#x3C1; varied with heliocentric distance in Figure 3.2. The Af&#x3C1; value reported by Bodewits et al. (2014) from observations in late <measure type="value"><date when="2014-05">May</date></measure> falls between our Af&#x3C1; values when using the same phase-angle correction method 4 . Because the phase-angle correction at <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> is not wellconstrained for comet dust, we hesitate to make any further direct comparisons between the optical and infrared Af &#x3C1; values when they are not simultaneous.</p>
		<p>At <measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> the observed flux exceeds that predicted by the combined reflected and thermal light models. In <measure type="value"><date when="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date></measure> we find that the excess emission is at the 3 &#x3C3; level, while it drops to 2.5&#x3C3; and &#x3C3; in the <measure type="list"><date when="2014-07">Jul.</date> and <date when="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure> visits, respectively. We note that the uncertainties are dominated by systematics that correlate with the signal at <measure type="value"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> and thus the uncertainties at <measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> are likely overestimated. The September band-excess detection is notably weak. However, the <measure type="list"><num>3.4</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure> and <num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> relative photometry are better constrained, since the relative uncertainties are &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (Cutri et al. 2012), considerably less than the uncertainties listed in Table 1. The NEOWISE bandpass at <measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> contains emission features from CO 2 (&#x3BD; 3 band) at <measure type="value"><num>4.26</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> and CO (v=1-0 band) at <measure type="value"><num>4.67</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure>. Both species have sufficiently long photodissociation lifetimes to be responsible for the observed excess flux. We therefore interpret the excess emission as being due to optically thin gaseous emission and convert the excess flux, F , to an average column density, N , using equation 2:</p>
		<p>where symbols have the same meanings as in equation 1, &#x3BB; is the wavelength of observation, h is Planck's constant, c is the speed of light, and g is the fluorescence efficiency for the chosen gas species. F is the excess flux density in the <measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">&#xB5;m</measure></measure> bandpass is integrated over the CO/CO 2 band, after the in-band dust signal contribution has been removed, as described in Pittichov&#xE1; et al. (2008). We are unable to distinguish between CO and CO 2 emission with just the NEOWISE data since the bandpass spans both features and therefore present two scenarios in Table 1 where <measure type="value"><num>100</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the excess flux is due to CO emission or it is entirely due to CO 2 emission. We assume fluorescence efficiencies at a heliocentric distance of <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> for the CO v=1-0 and the CO 2 &#x3BD; 3 bands of <measure type="list"><num>2.46 &#xD7; 10 &#x2212;4</num><measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="s^-1">s &#x2212;1</measure> and <num>2.86 &#xD7; 10 &#x2212;3</num><measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="s^-1">s &#x2212;1</measure></measure> , respectively (Crovisier &amp; Encrenaz 1983). We then use the average column densities to calculate the production rates, Q in molecules s &#x2212;1 , using equation 3:</p>
		<p>in which N and &#x3C1; have their previous definitions, v is the ejection velocity of the gas in km s &#x2212;1 and <measure type="value"><num>10 5</num></measure> is a conversion factor (Pittichov&#xE1; et al. 2008). We take the ejection velocity to be <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num><measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km.s^-1">km s &#x2212;1</measure></measure> during the <measure type="value"><date when="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date></measure> visit when the comet was at a heliocentric distance of <measure type="value"><num>3.82</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> and assume that the velocity scales as &#x221A; r H (Delsemme 1982). The production rates calculated are given in Table 1 and show that gas production increased overall by a factor of &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>3.5</num></measure> between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-01">2014 Jan.</date> and <date to-iso="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure>. For these heliocentric distances, this kind of increase, proportional to &#x223C; r &#x2212;1.8 is comparable to a Q CO2 &#x223C; r &#x2212;2 , possibly coinciding with a fixed source of constant area (Meech and Svoren 2004). There was a decrease between the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-07">Jul.</date> visit and the <date to-iso="2014-09">Sep.</date></measure> visit which may be attributable to a decrease in overall activity. Figure 3.2 shows the evolution of the Af &#x3C1; quantity and CO 2 production as the comet moves toward perihelion. There are comparatively few published H 2 O values for Siding Spring, but Q H2O was measured to be &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>2 &#xD7; 10 27</num><measure type="EMISSION_RATE" unit="molecules.s^-1">molecules s &#x2212;1</measure></measure> when the comet was at &#x223C; <measure type="value"><num>2.5</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> (Bodewits et al. 2014). This would suggest a lower bound of Q CO2 /Q H2O of <measure type="value"><num>15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> assuming water production increased with decreasing heliocentric distance from <measure type="interval"><num atMost="3.8">3.8</num> to <num atLeast="2.5">2.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>We have used data from the NEOWISE reactivation mission to monitor the activity of comet Siding Spring over <measure type="value"><num>9</num><measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> as it approaches Mars on a trajectory that will bring it within &#x223C;<measure type="value"><num>135,000</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> of the planet. Our conclusions from this work are as follows:</p>
		<p>1. NEOWISE observed comet Siding Spring to be active from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-01">January</date> to <date to-iso="2014-09">September, 2014</date></measure>. The quantity Af&#x3C1; and CO/CO2 production rates initially increased as the comet reached a heliocentric distance of <measure type="value"><num>1.88</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="AU">AU</measure></measure> but then decreased slightly even as the comet moved further inwards.</p>
		<p>2. The activity of the comet decreased between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2014-07">July</date> and <date to-iso="2014-09">September</date></measure>, possibly due to depletion of volatile deposits on or near the surface.</p>
		<p>3. The decrease in activity suggests the risk to assets at Mars was reduced since activity diminished as the comet approached Mars.</p>
	</text>
</tei>
