<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>We analyzed data from <measure type="value"><num>120</num></measure> LGG patients treated between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1999">1999</date> and <date to-iso="2007">2007</date></measure>. <!-- 12 --> Data included information on tumor size in all patients and on up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="3">three</num></measure> molecular (genetic) characteristics in <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> patients: 1p/19q chromosomal codeletion, p53 overexpression (a surrogate marker for TP53 missense mutations <!-- 17 --> ), and IDH mutation status. The model was built using the data from these <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> patients. Among these patients, information on all molecular characteristics was available for <measure type="value"><num>42</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>54.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), and information on at least one item of molecular characteristic in <measure type="value"><num>35</num></measure> patients (<measure type="value"><num>45.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). The data from the <measure type="value"><num>43</num></measure> patients without molecular information were used as an external dataset to evaluate model quality.</p>
		<p>Tumor sizes were measured manually from printed MRI images and expressed as mean tumor diameter (MTD) in millimeters, according to the formula MTD 5 (2V) 1/3 , where</p>
		<p>is the approximated tumor volume with D 1 , D 2 , and D 3 referring to the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> largest perpendicular diameters. The total median duration of the posttreatment follow-up period for a single patient, which included several follow-up observations, was <measure type="value"><num>21</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure> at minimum and <num atMost="9.5">9.5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> at maximum). We analyzed a total of <measure type="value"><num>952</num></measure> MTD observations with, on average, <measure type="value"><num>12</num></measure> observations per patient (minimum <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4">4</num> observations and maximum <num atMost="28">28</num></measure>). Histology consisted of grade II oligodendrogliomas (<measure type="value"><num>56</num></measure> patients, <measure type="value"><num>73</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), oligoastrocytomas (<measure type="value"><num>16</num></measure> patients, <measure type="value"><num>21</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), and astrocytomas (<measure type="value"><num>5</num></measure> patients, <measure type="value"><num>6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). All patients received TMZ as first-line treatment. The drug was administered for <measure type="value"><num>5</num> consecutive <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> (day 1 to day 5) every <measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> at a daily dose of <measure type="value"><num>200</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mg.m^2">mg/m 2</measure></measure> .</p>
		<p>We recently proposed a mathematical model to describe MTD dynamics in LGG patients before, during, and after chemotherapy. <!-- 16 --> The model, which distinguishes between disease-specific and treatment-specific parameters, relies on the hypothesis that LGG tumors are made up of both quiescent and proliferative cells, and that both cell types are sensitive to treatment. <!-- 18,19 --> Chemotherapy is assumed to act by damaging cells' DNA. The DNA damage leads proliferative cells to die, whereas quiescent cells with DNA damage can either repair their lesions and return to a proliferative state or die. Thus, we consider <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> compartments: proliferative tissue, denoted P; nondamaged quiescent tissue, denoted Q; and damaged quiescent tissue, denoted Q p. The sum of the values attributed to the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> compartments (P Ã Þ represents the size of the lesion and is compared to the MTD observations.</p>
		<p>To allow for MTD increase during TMZ treatment, we extended the previously proposed model <!-- 16 --> by taking into account the possibility that proliferative cells can repair their DNA lesions during the division process, instead of immediately dying, and thus acquire resistance to TMZ. In line with previous works, <!-- 9 --> we implemented acquisition of resistance by assuming that the effect of TMZ concentration on tumor tissues decreases exponentially with the amount of time since the beginning of treatment. Both proliferative and quiescent tissues were considered as having the potential to acquire resistance to TMZ.</p>
		<p>The model was developed in a population context, <!-- 20 --> and the values of individual-level parameters were assumed to be log-normally distributed; i.e., for a parameter w i corresponding to an individual patient i, w i =w.expg i where w is the "typical" (population) value of the parameter, and g i represents the contribution of the individual i. The values of g are normally distributed with mean <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure>. Population and individual parameter values were estimated with the SAEM (Stochastic Approximation of the Expectation Maximization) algorithm implemented in Monolix 4.2 (Lixoft) using the full MTD time-course in the <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> patients. We assumed a constant error model, with parameter value a. Model selection was carried out according to the usual criteria; in particular, models that achieved lower values of the objective function <!--encoding problem "-2x3" -> 22 3--><!-- (22 3 log likelihood) --> were considered to provide a better fit to the data.</p>
		<p>The data from the <measure type="value"><num>42</num></measure> patients with complete molecular status (codeletion 1p/19q, p53, and IDH mutations) was used as a training dataset to obtain statistics on this genetic information. We computed the percentage of patients with a given genetic profile and derived the probability to exhibit it. So for patients with <measure type="list"><num>one</num> or <num>two</num></measure> missing covariates, we could compute the probability to exhibit the lacking mutation status(es), knowing the other(s) one(s). We therefore attributed genetic characteristics for patients with missing covariates. In our training dataset, in line with previous literature, <!-- 12 --> 1p/ 19q codeletion and the p53 mutation were mutually exclusive. We incorporated the molecular information into the model and identified the effect of each status on the tumor size kinetic parameters. For a given fixed-effect parameter f, the model used for covariate analysis was of the following form:</p>
		<p>where status j corresponds to the value of the characteristic j. As we considered binary variables only, Eq. 1 could be simplified:</p>
		<p>where n 0 denotes the population value of the parameter for the reference group of patients (with non-codeleted 1p/19q or wild p53), and n 1 is the population value for the group of patients with mutated covariate. Using this framework, only fixed-effect parameters can depend on the covariate status while (interindividual) variability is not concerned, i.e., parameters n 0 and n 1 will have the same variability.</p>
		<p>We used a stepwise forward/backward modeling strategy based on progressive inclusion and then exclusion of covariates, where the decision to include or exclude a covariate was dependent on the covariate's effect on the objective function through a log-likelihood ratio test. <!-- 21 --> Empirical Bayes estimates to predict LGG response to temozolomide Following a Bayesian approach in which population parameter estimates constituted prior information, we analyzed each patient's data individually, considering only the MTD observations prior to treatment and the first MTD observations obtained after treatment onset, i.e., the observations obtained in the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment. If, for a given patient, no observations were available prior to treatment, we used only the MTD observations obtained within the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> after treatment onset. Patients for whom no information was available for the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment were excluded from the analysis. Overall, data from <measure type="value"><num>45</num></measure> patients were analyzed. Among these, <measure type="value"><num>31</num></measure> patients had a single MTD observation during the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment, and <measure type="value"><num>14</num></measure> patients had <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> MTD observations. When possible, MTD observations before treatment onset were used to estimate empirical Bayes estimates (EBEs) of the disease-specific parameters of the model. The MTD observations after treatment start were then used to estimate the treatment-specific parameters of the model. EBEs were calculated using MatLab (MathWorks, Natick, MA) after the population parameters were estimated with Monolix.</p>
		<p>To evaluate the capacity of the model to predict individual tumor response to TMZ treatment, <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> clinically relevant metrics were calculated: the duration of response, i.e., the length of time during which MTD decreases, and the minimal tumor size reached as a result of TMZ effect.</p>
		<p>In the analysis described above, the model's predictive capacity was assessed on patients whose full time-course data were used to estimate the population parameters; these population parameters constituted prior information for the calculation of EBEs. To explore whether this caused a bias, we subsequently performed predictive analysis on the <measure type="value"><num>43</num></measure> "external" patients whose data had been excluded from the initial model-building process, owing to a lack of genetic information. In this case, we used early MTD observations as in the original predictive analysis, but without covariates.</p>
		<p>We then used population parameters to simulate <measure type="value"><num>200</num></measure> new virtual patients, and we made predictions for these patients using the model without covariates in a first step, and we incorporated genetic statuses into the predictions in a second step.</p>
		<p>Tumor size time-course in patients treated with temozolomide Figure 1 depicts the time-course of tumor size (mean tumor diameter) in the <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> LGG patients included in the analysis. Patients received a median of <measure type="value"><num>18</num></measure> TMZ cycles (minimum <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num> cycles, maximum <num atMost="24">24</num></measure>). Table 1 shows a summary of the characteristics of the <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> patients. Tumor size increased linearly before treatment. <!-- 22 --> <!--encoding problem "5 58" is in fact "= 58)--><!-- After TMZ onset, an initial MTD decrease followed by a MTD reincrease was observed (n <measure type="value"><num>5 58, 75</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>).  -->Median time to tumor progression was <measure type="value"><num>18</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>. In <measure type="value"><num>34</num></measure> patients MTD a reincrease occurred during TMZ treatment while in <measure type="value"><num>24</num></measure> patients it occurred after TMZ discontinuation. We separated the patients to present tumor profiles in a clear manner, but it did not impact data analysis.</p>
		<p>Inclusion of a resistance term for the proliferative tissue resulted in a significantly better model fit (drop of <measure type="value"><num>200</num></measure> points in the objective function) compared with exclusion of the resistance term. The model with the inclusion of a resistance term for the quiescent tissue performed worse. However, because quiescent cells have the capacity to repair their DNA lesions, they also contribute to the emergence of resistance by repopulating the proliferative compartment. Thus, the final selected model incorporated a resistance term for the proliferative tissue only:</p>
		<p>The term res denotes the resistance parameter. Given the time scale of data collection compared to the time scale of TMZ delivery scheduling, we represented a single TMZ cycle (actually composed of <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> daily administrations) as a single bolus administration with corresponding concentration, C, assumed to undergo exponential decay at a constant rate KDE (a so-called K-PD approach <!-- 23 --> ). <!--encoding problem "8.3 month 21" is in fact "month^-1"--><!-- The population value of KDE parameter was fixed to 8.3 month 21 corresponding to a half-life of <measure type="value"><num>2.5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure>, allowing for a residual active concentration of TMZ after <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> of treatment.  -->The parameter c is the constant rate for proliferative tissue death (also referred to as the TMZ efficacy parameter). A schematic view of the model is presented in Figure 2. The full mathematical equations of the model are:</p>
		<p>Overall, the model includes <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> parameters and <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> initial conditions. <measure type="value"><num>Two</num></measure> parameters are disease-specific and related to tumor growth: the proliferation rate (k P ) and the transfer constant rate (k PQ ) from proliferation to quiescence. The <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> remaining parameters are related to TMZ action and effect and are called treatment-specific parameters. In particular, the constant rate of death of quiescent cells is denoted d Qp and k Qp P is the constant rate of transition from quiescence to proliferation following repair of TMZ-induced DNA damage. For identifiability reasons, we assumed that the initial drug effect is the same on P and Q. This is consistent with the biology, as TMZ acts on cells regardless of their stage in the division process.</p>
		<p>The covariate analysis performed with the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> molecular status characteristics showed that p53 mutation could be included as a covariate of the TMZ efficacy parameter (c). On the basis of the stepwise forward/backward analysis, we further determined that chromosomal 1p/19q codeletion could be included as a covariate on the constant rate k Qp P (transition from quiescence to proliferation following repair of TMZ-induced DNA damage. The inclusion of these <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> model covariates led to a significant drop in the objective function (<measure type="value"><num>126</num></measure> points; P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.01">0.01</num></measure>, likelihood-ratio test). In the Figure 1 Typical tumor size dynamics for the <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> patients included in the analysis. <!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!-- Top, left: MTD time-course before treatment onset (n 5 77).  -->Top, right: In <measure type="value"><num>21</num></measure> patients, an ongoing MTD decrease after treatment discontinuation was observed. Bottom, left: Acquired resistance occurs in <measure type="value"><num>34</num></measure> patients. MTD time-course shows initial decrease followed by progression during TMZ treatment. <!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!-- Bottom, right: MTD time-course exhibits initial decrease followed by progression before or after treatment cessation (n 5 58).  -->Mazzocco et al. stepwise analysis procedure, IDH mutation status identified as having an effect on model parameters when tested independently from the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> other covariates was not identified as a significant covariate in the presence of p53 and 1p/ 19q information. This is in agreement with the known redundancy of the genetic information <!-- 24 --> and indicates that, in our model, p53 and 1p/19q information intrinsically integrate IDH information. The parameter estimates of the final model (including covariates) are presented in Table 2.</p>
		<p>Among p53-mutated patients, the value of the TMZ efficacy parameter is <measure type="value"><num>45</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> lower than among p53-nonmutated patients, suggesting that TMZ therapy is almost <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> times less effective in the former population. This is consistent with preclinical evidence that p53 mutations decrease sensitivity to TMZ in gliomas. <!-- 25,26 --> Likewise, among patients with the 1p/19q codeletion, the value of k Qp P is <measure type="value"><num>15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> lower than among non-codeleted patients, suggesting that among patients in the former group, DNA-damaged quiescent cells have less capacity to repair themselves. This finding is consistent with the longer duration of response reported in codeleted patients. <!-- 12 --> Figure 3 shows goodness-of-fit (visual predictive check) plots for the <measure type="value"><num>77</num></measure> patients included in the model-building Figure 2 Schematic view of the model with model's parameters. P is the proliferative tissue, Q is the nondamaged quiescent tissue, and Q p is the damaged quiescent tissue. The sum of the values corresponding to the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> compartments, P Ã , is compared to the MTD observations. Proliferative tissue (P) can become quiescent (Q). TMZ treatment affects both proliferative and quiescent tissues. Damaged quiescent tissue can either repair its DNA lesions and return to a proliferative state or die due to treatment-induced lesions. dataset and for the <measure type="value"><num>43</num></measure> patients included in an external dataset. These diagnostics indicate good quality of the model, with and without covariates. The proposed model is able to capture the variability in patients' response to TMZ, including prolonged response after therapy discontinuation or emergence of acquired resistance to TMZ during treatment.</p>
		<p>Prediction of response to TMZ chemotherapy Figure 4 shows predictions regarding individual patients' response durations (left-hand side), represented by KaplanMeier curves, together with observed response durations that fall in the <measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> confidence interval (CI) for almost <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> after treatment onset. Beyond <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, the model predictions are incorrect, which is not surprising given that only information until month 3 is taken into account. Notably, beyond <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> predicted times to progression are earlier than the actual times to progression. In this respect, the modeling framework shows a tendency for underestimating the effect of the treatment. The early part of the KaplanMeier curve also indicates a tendency to predict progression at a very early time. <!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!-- For a small subset of patients (n <measure type="value"><num>5 4</num></measure>), the unique MTD point during the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment was greater than the MTD at treatment onset, while successive MTD points showed a significant response.  -->Integrating this point in our modeling framework resulted in predicting very early progression. However, removing these <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> patients resulted in correcting the early part of the Kaplan-Meier curve. Figure 4 also shows predicted vs. observed minimal tumor size (right-hand side). We evaluated prediction bias (mean prediction error) and precision (root mean squared prediction error). <!-- 27 --> Prediction bias was <measure type="value"><num>1.89</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CI (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-0.22">-0.22</num>, <num atMost="3.99">3.99</num></measure>)) and precision was <measure type="value"><num>7.18</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CI (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4.52">4.52</num>, <num atMost="9.10">9.10</num></measure>)). For <measure type="value"><num>90</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the patients<!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!--  (n <measure type="value"><num>5 40</num></measure>) -->, the observed minimal tumor size was predicted correctly, with less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="25">25</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> relative error (relative to tumor size at treatment onset); this corresponds, approximately, to an error of about <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> in MTD. Notably, for each of the <measure type="value"><num>14</num></measure> patients with <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> MTD observations within the <measure type="value"><num>3</num></measure> first months of treatment, the minimal tumor size was predicted with an error of less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="15">15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (about <measure type="value"><num>6</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>).</p>
		<p>Individual predictions for <measure type="value"><num>six</num></measure> patients with repeated measurements during the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment are displayed in Figure 5 as an illustration of the method proposed herein. It shows that the model is also able to predict tumor time-course, especially for these patients. For the <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of patients <!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!-- (n 5 5)  -->for whom predictions of minimal tumor size were incorrect, we observed that, for <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> of them, tumor size reduction was unexpectedly characterized by <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> phases: an initial moderate decrease in tumor size within the first <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment, followed by a more pronounced decrease after <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>. For these <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> patients, the model underevaluated the response. Inclusion of a second MTD observation (obtained after <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment) yielded correct minimal tumor size predictions for these patients. Tumor response for <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> additional patient could not be predicted owing to his/her prolonged response to treatment (more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>). The model may not be able to capture such extreme behavior. We then performed predictive analysis on the <measure type="value"><num>43</num></measure> "external" patients. The model successfully predicted the minimal tumor size for <measure type="value"><num>75</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of these patients (bias <measure type="value"><num>24.41</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-7.14">-7.14</num>, <num atMost="21.67">21.67</num></measure>)). To evaluate whether the reduction in predictive capability was due to the lack of genetic information or to the fact that these patients' data were not incorporated as prior information in model-building, we made predictions for <measure type="value"><num>200</num></measure> virtual patients. Without covariates, the minimal tumor size was successfully predicted for <measure type="value"><num>76</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the virtual patients. When we incorporated genetic statuses, predictive capacity rose to <measure type="value"><num>87</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (bias <measure type="value"><num>0.31</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="-0.86">-0.86</num>, <num atMost="1.49">1.49</num></measure>)). These observations lead us to believe that the reduction in the model's predictive capacity for the <measure type="value"><num>43</num></measure> external patients was mainly due to the absence of genetic information.</p>
		<p>Molecular profiling of tumors is a well-known strategy to personalize anticancer treatments. Another approach is mathematical modeling. <!-- 28,29 --> Mathematical models of tumor growth and response to treatment allow characterizing quantitatively the efficacy and toxicity of anticancer agents and can be used to predict clinical response. <!-- 7,30 --> In the present study, we show that combining longitudinal tumor size measurements through the use of quantitative modeling with a tumor's genetic characterization is a promising strategy to personalize treatments in patients with lowgrade gliomas.</p>
		<p>Using p53 mutation and 1p/19q codeletion as covariates significantly improved the model accuracy. In agreement with the literature, p53 and 1p/19q molecular statuses significantly impacted the dynamics of LGG response to treatment: p53 mutation impaired TMZ efficacy and 1p/19q codeleted tumors had less ability to repair TMZ-induced DNA lesions in quiescent tissue, thus increasing the overall efficacy of treatment. IDH mutation status did not provide useful information on tumor size dynamics beyond the combined information provided by p53 and 1p/19q status. However, it would be relevant to introduce IDH status as a model covariate in cases in which p53 and 1p/19q information is not available for a given patient.</p>
		<p>Molecular information (p53 and 1p/19q status) and tumor observations obtained during the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> after TMZ treatment onset were sufficient to correctly predict the amplitude of response and its duration for almost <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, especially in those patients in whom precise assessment of early tumor response was available. An adaptive approach, consisting of updating the model predictions at each new MTD observation, could be implemented to prolong the validity period of the prediction and to enhance the percentage of patients for whom the minimal tumor size is successfully predicted. These results, however, need to be confirmed in a larger set of external patients. It would also be interesting to evaluate the relationship between the predictive performance of the model and the timing of MTD observations used for predictive purposes. In this study, we focused on MTD observations obtained during the first <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> of treatment because we wanted to obtain a reference or rational value for the predictive potential of the model. In the area of brain tumor, numerous studies have used partial differential equation models integrating both time dynamics and spatial aspects of these highly diffusive malignancies (see refs. 31,32 for examples). It would also be important to apply the same prediction framework with these types of models, which capture more precisely glioma evolution.</p>
		<p>Emergence of acquired resistance, defined as progression after initial benefits, is a critical issue in clinical oncology and model-based approaches should be used to better understand, characterize, and predict this phenomenon. Mechanisms of acquired resistance can be pharmacological resulting from decreased drug uptake into the cell, intracellular drug inactivation, or repair of drug-induced damages. This is the case of the LGG response to TMZ, for which it has been shown that more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="90">90</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of recurrent gliomas show no response to a second treatment with TMZ. <!-- 33  -->One of the key elements in TMZ resistance is MGMT, an enzymatic protein with the faculty to repair the principal O 6meG-alkylation site to TMZ, <!-- 34  -->thus resulting in decreased efficacy of drugs during treatment. MGMT could not be tested as a covariate in our model since for most patients only formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissue was available for DNA tests, whereas MGMT methylation testing ideally needs frozen tissue. Of note, resistance to TMZ is also responsible for significant therapeutic failures in melanoma. <!-- 35  -->Following this biological knowledge, we modeled acquisition of resistance by decreasing drug efficacy on LGG proliferative tissue with time following therapy onset. Since all patients received the same TMZ doses with the same scheduling, we believe that modeling resistance as a function of actual drug exposure would not have led to significantly different results. For identifiability reasons, we could not model all transitions between the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> compartments, especially the possibility for quiescent cells to directly return into proliferation, as it could occur without treatment. However, during treatment quiescent cells do have the capacity to repair their DNA and become proliferative. Therefore, this model is a relevant tool to characterize tumor response to TMZ but does not aim to faithfully mimic natural tumor growth. Our model is flexible enough to reproduce the variability of patients' response to standard TMZ protocol and has the capacity to mimic both tumor regrowth during treatment as a result of acquired resistance to TMZ and prolonged response to treatment. Finally, our model could constitute a rational tool to optimize the duration of temozolomide therapy in low-grade glioma patients. Up to now, there are no clear rules or guidelines regarding the optimal number of cycles or treatment duration in patients treated with TMZ. <!-- 15 --> Many neurooncologists prolong the duration of the treatment beyond <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="12">12</num></measure> cycles if an ongoing decrease in tumor size is observed at this time. However, there are downsides to prolonging TMZ treatment, including side effects and costs. An even greater concern is that TMZ therapy might drive the evolutionary path to high-grade glioma. <!-- 36 --> Consequently, determining the optimal duration of TMZ therapy and maximizing the duration of the response is a critical challenge in the management of</p>
		<p>LGG. Using our model as a simulation tool to determine the optimal number of TMZ cycles each patient should have received, we found that for <measure type="value"><num>47</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the <measure type="value"><num>45</num></measure> patients analyzed<!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!--  (n 5 21) -->, the model would have recommended, by month 3 after treatment onset, administration of additional TMZ cycles beyond what these patients actually received; i.e., in these patients delivery of additional TMZ could have resulted in tumor shrinkage exceeding what was ultimately achieved. In contrast, the model predicted that <measure type="value"><num>33</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the patients <!--encoding problem: "n 5" is in fact "n ="--><!-- (n 5 15)  -->could have benefited if their treatment had been stopped earlier than it actually was.</p>
		<p>Mandonnet et al. suggested that knowledge of the glioma growth rate prior to treatment can be used to optimize patient management and follow-up. <!-- 22 --> Our approach proposes to leverage early tumor dynamical information together with the a tumor's genetic characteristics to predict tumor size response. We believe that this framework can be used as a template for other diseases whose response to treatment is characterized by emergence of acquired resistance.</p>
	</text>
</tei>