<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Due to the lack of macromolecular fossils, the enzymatic repertoire of extinct species has remained largely unknown to date. In an attempt to solve this problem, we have characterized a cyclase subunit (HisF) of the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase (ImGP-S), which was reconstructed from the era of the last universal common ancestor of cellular organisms (LUCA). As observed for contemporary HisF proteins, the crystal structure of LUCA-HisF adopts the () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel architecture, one of the most ancient folds. Moreover, LUCA-HisF i) resembles extant HisF proteins with regard to internal <measure type="value"><num>twofold</num></measure> symmetry , active site residues, and a stabilizing salt bridge cluster, ii) is thermostable and shows a folding mechanism similar to that of contemporary () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel enzymes, iii) displays high and specific catalytic activity, and iv) forms a stable and functional complex with the glutaminase subunit (HisH) of an extant ImGP-S. Furthermore, we show that LUCA-HisF binds to a reconstructed LUCA-HisH protein with high affinity. Our findings suggest that the evolution of highly specific enzymes and enzyme complexes has already been completed in the LUCA era, which means that sophisticated catalytic concepts such as substrate tunneling and allosteric communication existed already <measure type="value"><num>4 billion</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> ago.</p>
		<p>Modern enzyme complexes are elaborate molecular machineries that have been optimized in the course of evolution for the efficient and specific processing of their substrates. One prominent example is the imidazole glycerol phosphate synthase (ImGP-S), a bi-enzyme complex which belongs to the family of glutamine amidotransferases <!--1--> and constitutes a branch-point connecting amino acid and nucleotide biosynthesis. ImGP-S consists of the cyclase subunit HisF and the glutaminase subunit HisH. HisF binds the substrate PRFAR and performs a cycloligase/lyase reaction that generates ImGP and AICAR, which are further used in histidine and de novo purine biosynthesis, respectively <!--2--> ( Figure 1). The ammonia molecule required for this transformation is produced by the glutaminase subunit HisH and transported to the active site of HisF through an extended molecular channel. This channeling hampers diffusion of ammonia into bulk solvent and thus presumably prevents its protonation to the non-productive ammonium ion. Another special feature of the HisF/HisH complex is the tight coordination of the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> enzymatic activities: Binding of PRFAR (or its analogue N′[(5′-phosphoribosyl) formimino]-5-aminoimidazole-4carboxamide-ribonucleotide; ProFAR) to HisF results in an allosteric signal that leads to a <measure type="value"><num>several hundred-fold</num></measure> stimulation of the glutaminase activity of HisH <!--[3][4][5]--> . This property precludes the hydrolysis of glutamine by HisH in the absence of an acceptor substrate at the active site of HisF <!--6--></p>
		<p>We were interested to find out whether the characteristics of modern HisF enzymes were already present in those species that colonized earth in a very early phase of biological evolution. A straightforward answer to this question is difficult due to the lack of macromolecular fossils. However, computational techniques of amino acid sequence reconstruction <!--7,8--> make it possible to travel back in time and to study extinct proteins <!--[9][10][11][12][13][14][15][16]-->. In extreme cases, these algorithms enable us to study enzymes from the last universal common ancestor of cellular organisms (LUCA), which preceded the diversification of life and existed in the Paleoarchean era, i. e. at least <measure type="value"><num>3.8 billion</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (Gyr) and presumably <measure type="value"><num>4.5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="Gyr">Gyr</measure></measure> ago <!--17--> .</p>
		<p>Along these lines, we have previously computationally reconstructed the amino acid sequence of HisF from the LUCA era (LUCA-HisF) <!--18--> . To this end, a set of <measure type="value"><num>87</num></measure> extant HisF and HisH proteins from the <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> phylogenetic clades Crenarchaeota, Actinobacteria, Chlorobi, Cyanobacteria, Firmicutes, Proteobacteria, and Thermotogae has been used to determine a phylogenetic tree t HisF_HisH based on the CAT model <!--19--> ( Figure 1). After having rooted this tree between the superkingdoms Archaea and Bacteria, we reconstructed a predecessor of HisF from Bacteria and Crenarchaeota as described <!--19,20--> . Thus, although the precise lineage of the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-2 Figure 1. Reaction catalyzed by the heterodimeric ImGP synthase complex. The synthase subunit HisF catalyzes the reaction of N`-[(5`phosphoribulosyl)formimino]-5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide-ribonucleotide (PRFAR) with ammonia (NH 3 ) to imidazole glycerol phosphate (ImGP) and 5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide ribotide (AICAR). ImGP is further utilized in the synthesis of histidine, whereas AICAR is an intermediate in de novo purine biosynthesis, rendering HisF a branch-point enzyme of amino acid and nucleotide biosynthesis. The ammonia molecule required for the HisF reaction is produced by the glutaminase subunit HisH (catalytic triad residues are depicted as spheres) and subsequently channeled to the active site of HisF (catalytic aspartate residues are depicted as spheres). In the absence of HisH, HisF can also use external ammonia that is added as ammonia salts. HisF adopts the () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel fold, an ubiquitous and catalytically versatile protein architecture <!--21--> , which is considered one of the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> most ancient protein folds <!--22--> . HisH adopts the  hydrolase fold <!--23--> . superkingdoms is still under debate <!--24--> , LUCA-HisF is among the oldest so far reconstructed proteins, if not the oldest hitherto calculated predecessor <!--16,25,26--> . Among the <measure type="value"><num>87</num></measure> descendants of LUCA-HisF used for reconstruction, <measure type="value"><num>78 of the 250</num></measure> residues are less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="50">50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> conserved, whereas <measure type="value"><num>49</num></measure> residues are strongly conserved. Accordingly, LUCA-HisF differs in <measure type="value"><num>55</num></measure> amino acids (<measure type="value"><num>22</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) from the closest BLAST match <!--27--> , which is HisF from Thermovibrio ammonificans. The nucleotide and amino acid sequences of LUCA-HisF are given in the Supporting Information.</p>
		<p>We have now produced LUCA-HisF in Escherichia coli, and analyzed its crystal structure, conformational stability, folding mechanism, and catalytic activity. The observed molecular characteristics of LUCA-HisF turned out to be similar to contemporary HisF proteins. Moreover, LUCA-HisF activates an extant HisH protein and thus comprises all elements required for allosteric interaction. Finally, we have also reconstructed and produced a LUCA-HisH protein and could show that it binds to LUCA-HisF with high affinity. Taken together, our results suggest that the protein inventory of the LUCA already contained elaborate enzyme complexes.</p>
		<p>Cloning, expression, and purification of LUCA-HisF. The gene coding for LUCA-HisF was optimized for its expression in E. coli, synthesized (GeneArt), and cloned into the vector pET24a(+)(Stratagene) using the terminal restriction sites for NdeI and XhoI. Since the addition of a C-terminal hexahistidine tag to LUCA-HisF might influence its interaction with HisH proteins, a stop codon was integrated at the end of the gene. The gene was expressed in E. coli T7-Express cells (New England Biolabs) transformed with pET24a(+)LUCA-hisF. To this end, <measure type="value"><num>four</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">liters</measure></measure> of Luria Broth (LB) medium supplemented with <measure type="value"><num>75</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="µg/ml">µg/ml</measure></measure> kanamycin were inoculated with a pre-culture and incubated at <measure type="value"><num>37</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. After an OD <measure type="value"><num>600</num></measure> of <measure type="value"><num>0.6</num></measure> was reached, the temperature was lowered to <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. Expression was induced by adding <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> IPTG, and growth was continued overnight. Cells were harvested by centrifugation (Sorvall/RC5B, GS3, <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>4000</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="rpm">rpm</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>), washed with <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>, and centrifuged again. The cells were suspended in the same buffer, lysed by sonification (Branson Sonifier W-250D, <measure type="value"><num>2 x 2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> in <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">sec</measure></measure> intervals, <measure type="value"><num>45</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> pulse, <measure type="value"><num>0</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>), and centrifuged again (Sorvall/RC5B, SS34, <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>13.000</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="rpm">rpm</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>) to separate the soluble from the insoluble fraction of the cell extract. In a first step, the soluble supernatant was subjected to ion exchange chromatography using a MonoQ column (HR 16/10, <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>, Pharmacia), which had been equilibrated with <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>. The column was washed with equilibration buffer, and bound LUCA-HisF was eluted by applying a linear gradient of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0">0</num>-<num atMost="1.5">1.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure> NaCl. Proteincontaining fractions were pooled, dialyzed against <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>, and subjected to ammonia sulfate precipitation. After <measure type="value"><num>80</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> saturation with ammonia sulfate, precipitated protein was centrifuged (Sorvall/RC5B, SS34, <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>13.000</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="rpm">rpm</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>), dissolved in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, , <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure><measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium chloride, and finally purified via size exclusion chromatography. For this purpose a Superdex200 column (HiLoad 26/60, <measure type="value"><num>320</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>, GE Healthcare) was operated with <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium chloride at <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. Fractions with pure protein were pooled and dialyzed against <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris/HCl, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>. According to SDS-PAGE (<measure type="value"><num>12.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> acrylamide), LUCA-HisF was more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="95">95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> pure. About <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="mg">mg</measure></measure> of protein were obtained per liter of culture.</p>
		<p>In order to determine the binding properties of LUCA-HisF to HisH proteins via fluorescence titration, all tryptophan residues of LUCA-HisF were replaced by tyrosines. Hence, LUCA_hisF_W138Y+W156Y was generated via overlap extension PCR 28 using pET24a(+)-LUCA-hisF as a template (see Supporting Information for oligonucleotide sequences), and subsequently cloned into pET24a(+) via the terminal restriction sites for NdeI and XhoI. Expression and purification were performed as described for LUCA-HisF, yielding a comparable amount and purity of LUCA-HisF_W138Y+W156Y.</p>
		<p>Cloning, expression, and purification of zmHisH. Genomic DNA of Zymomonas mobilis (DSM424) was ordered from the Leibniz Institute DSMZ. In order to remove the internal restriction site for NdeI, the zmhisH gene was amplified by overlap extension PCR <!--28--> (see Supporting Information for oligonucleotide sequences) and cloned into pET24a(+) using the terminal restriction sites for NdeI and XhoI. After transformation of E. coli strain BL21(DE3) (Stratagene), expression was carried out at <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> overnight in <measure type="value"><num>four</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">liters</measure></measure> of LB medium, supplemented with <measure type="value"><num>75</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="µg/ml">µg/ml</measure></measure> kanamycin. Protein purification was performed as described for LUCA-HisF including-3ion exchange chromatography using <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris/HCl, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>9</num></measure>, as buffer, ammonia sulfate precipitation, size exclusion chromatography, and final dialysis against <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris/HCl, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>. According to SDS-PAGE (<measure type="value"><num>12.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> acrylamide), zmHisH was more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="95">95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> pure. About <measure type="value"><num>8</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="mg">mg</measure></measure> of protein were obtained per liter of culture.</p>
		<p>Sequence reconstruction, cloning, expression and purification of LUCA-HisH. As for LUCA-HisF, the reconstruction of LUCA-HisH was based on the tree t HisF_HisH (Figure S1), which is close to an accepted organism phylogeny. In comparison to the multiple sequence alignment (MSA) of extant HisF sequences, the <measure type="value"><num>87</num></measure> extant HisH sequences exhibit a significantly higher variability. In fact, <measure type="value"><num>140 of 226</num></measure> residues are less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="50">50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> conserved. Furthermore, the MSA (HisH ext ) contains several gaps. Recently, it has been shown that a novel algorithm for the phylogeny-aware gap placement named PRANK <!--29--> improves MSA quality. This is why we used PRANK with the option-showanc to deduce LUCA-HisH from the MSA HisH ext under the control of t HisF_HisH ( Figure S2). The nucleotide and amino acid sequences of LUCA-HisH are given in the Supporting Information. The protein shares <measure type="value"><num>123 of 226</num></measure> residues (<measure type="value"><num>54</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) with the closest BLAST <!--27--> match, which is HisH from Syntrophothermus lipocalidus.</p>
		<p>The gene coding for LUCA-HisH was optimized for its expression in E. coli, synthesized (GeneArt), and cloned into the vector pET24a(+)(Stratagene) using the terminal restriction sites for NdeI and XhoI. (The gene encodes a Cterminal hexa-histidin tag; see Supporting Information). Subsequently, pET24a(+)-LUCA-hisH was used to transform E. coli strain BL21-Gold (DE3) (Stratagene). Protein expression, harvesting of cells, and cell lysis were performed as described for LUCA-HisF. As LUCA-HisH showed a high thermal stability, most of the host proteins could be removed by heat denaturation (<measure type="value"><num>70</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) followed by centrifugation (Sorvall/RC5B, SS34, <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>13.000</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="rpm">rpm</measure></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>). For further purification, the supernatant of the heat step was loaded onto a HisTrapFF crude column (<measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>; GE Healthcare), which had been equilibrated with <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium chloride and <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> imidazole. After washing with equilibration buffer, the bound protein was eluted by applying a linear gradient of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num><num atMost="375">375</num><!--"10-375" character "-" erased from OCR--> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> imidazole. Fractions with pure protein were pooled, and LUCA-HisH was dialyzed against <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>. As judged by SDS-PAGE, the protein was more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="95">95</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> pure. About <measure type="value"><num>26</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="mg">mg</measure></measure> LUCA-HisH were obtained per liter of culture.</p>
		<p>Crystallization, data collection, and refinement of LUCAHisF. Crystallization trials were carried out using the PEG/Ion screen (Hampton Research). The hanging drop vapor diffusion method was performed in <measure type="value"><num>96</num></measure>-well plates (Greiner) at <measure type="value"><num>291</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. Drops contained <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="nl">nl</measure></measure> of the respective reservoir buffer mixed with <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="nl">nl</measure></measure> of LUCA-HisF (<measure type="value"><num>13.9</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="mg/ml">mg/ml</measure></measure>) in <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>. In each well equilibration was performed against <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="µl">µl</measure></measure> of reservoir buffer. Crystals were obtained with <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure> sodium phosphate monobasic monohydrate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>4.7</num></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> wt/vol PEG 3350. After flash freezing in liquid nitrogen, data of single crystals were collected at the synchrotron beamlinePX2 (SLS) at <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="K">K</measure></measure>. Data were processed using XDS <!--30--> and the data quality assessment was done using phenix.xtriage <!--31--> . Molecular replacement was performed with MOLREP within the CCP4i suite <!--32--> . A homology model of LUCA-HisF with HisF from Thermotoga maritima (tmHisF) (PDB ID 1THF) was built with MODELLER <!--33--> and served as a search model. Initial refinement was performed using REFMAC <!--34-->. The model was further improved in several refinement rounds using automated restrained refinement with the program PHENIX <!--31--> and interactive modeling with Coot <!--35--> . The data collection and refinement statistics are summarized in Table S1. The final model was analyzed using the program MolProbity <!--36--> .</p>
		<p>Analysis of the thermal stability of LUCA-HisF and LUCAHisH. Differential T DSC). Thermal denaturation traces of LUCA-HisF and LUCA-HisH in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>, were monitored with a JASCO J-815 circular dichroism (CD) spectrometer in a <measure type="value"><num>0.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="cm">cm</measure></measure> cuvette by following the loss of ellipticity at <measure type="value"><num>220</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>. Unfolding was induced by raising the temperature in <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> increments at a ramp rate of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> min</p>
		<p>The thermodynamic stability of LUCA-HisF was determined by GdmClinduced equilibrium unfolding transitions. The loss of tertiary structure was probed by protein fluorescence, the loss of secondary structure by far-UV CD. Samples with <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> protein were prepared in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris/HCl buffer (<measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>) containing different concentrations of GdmCl. GdmCl (ultrapure) was purchased from MP Biomedicals (Illkrich, France) and its concentration was determined by the refractive index of the solution <!--37--> . To reach equilibrium, LUCAHisF was preincubated at the indicated concentration of GdmCl for <measure type="value"><num>24</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure> at <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>The fluorescence emission signal at <measure type="value"><num>320</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> (bandwidth <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>) after excitation at <measure type="value"><num>280</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> (bandwidth <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>) was monitored with a JASCO model FP-6500 spectrofluorimeter. The equilibrium unfolding transition of LUCA-HisF obtained by monitoring fluorescence is shown in Figure S4A in comparison to tmHisF and its artificially designed precursors Sym1 and Sym2, which were constructed by duplication and fusion of the C-terminal half-barrel HisF-C followed by the optimization of the initial construct <!--[38][39][40]-->. The transitions were analyzed according to the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-state equilibrium model, assuming a linear dependency of the free-energy of unfolding on the GdmCl concentration Table S2.</p>
		<p>The far-UV circular dichroism (CD) signal at <measure type="value"><num>225</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> was monitored using a JASCO model J815 CD spectrophotometer (path-length <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>; bandwidth <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>). The equilibrium unfolding/refolding transitions of LUCA-HisF obtained by Kinetics of refolding of LUCA-HisF in Figure S4B were obtained by following the far-UV CD signal for <measure type="value"><num>200</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">seconds</measure></measure> in manual mixing experiments at various concentrations of GdmCl and extrapolating the exponential curve to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> time. The observed amplitude was plotted as function of the GdmCl concentration and is shown in Figure S4B as closed triangles. It was significantly lower than the amplitude observed in the refolding equilibrium transitions, indicating that the major part of the CD change occurred within the dead time of the manual mixing experiment. This is interpreted with the formation of a compact burst-phase refolding intermediate with a high content of secondary structure.</p>
		<p>Fluorescence titration of zmHisH and LUCA-HisH with LUCA-HisF. Fluorescence titration was used to determine the binding stoichiometry and affinity of the LUCAHisF/zmHisH and LUCA-HisF/LUCA-HisH complexes, as in the course of complex formation a tryptophan residue lying at the HisH-interface is shielded from the solvent <!--5--> . Hence, when titrating either <measure type="list"><num>7</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure> zmHisH or <num>5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> LUCA-HisH in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure> with LUCAHisF_W138Y+W156Y, the emission maxima shifted from <measure type="value"><num>345</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>325</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> and from <measure type="value"><num>345</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>329</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, respectively (excitation at <measure type="value"><num>295</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>). The decreases in fluorescence emission at <measure type="value"><num>318</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> were plotted against the added amounts of LUCA-HisF_W138Y+W156Y and the resulting curves were analyzed with a quadratic fit. Both titrations were performed in triplicate.</p>
		<p>Analysis of enzymatic activity in vitro, and in vivo. In vitro enzymatic activities were determined by steady-state kinetics. The ammonia-and glutamine-dependent conversions of PRFAR into ImGP and AICAR (HisF reaction) were measured spectrophotometrically at <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> as previously described <!--5--> .</p>
		<p>At <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>, entire progress curves at <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> different PRFARconcentrations were recorded either in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris-acetate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>8.5</num></measure> in presence of <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> ammonium acetate (ammoniadependent cyclase reaction) or in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris-acetate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>8.0</num></measure> in presence of <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> glutamine and <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> zmHisH (glutamine-dependent cyclase reaction). In both cases an excess of HisA from T. maritima was added in order to synthesize PRFAR in situ from ProFAR</p>
		<p>, and <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> of LUCA-HisF were used to initiate the measurements. Data were analyzed with the integrated form of the Michaelis-Menten equation using the program COSY 45 to obtain k cat and K M PRFAR. In case of the LUCA-HisF/LUCA-HisH complex (<measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>), no glutamine-dependent cyclase activity could be determined in presence of <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> glutamine and <measure type="value"><num>100</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> ProFAR. The glutaminase activity of zmHisH (<measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>) in complex with liganded LUCA-HisF (<measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>; <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> ProFAR) was measured in a coupled enzymatic assay as previously described <!--5--> . At <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>, produced glutamate was oxidized by a molar excess of glutamate dehydrogenase (Roche) in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tricine hydroxide, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>8.0</num></measure>. Thus, the reduction of the coenzyme NAD + to NADH could be monitored spectrophotometrically at <measure type="value"><num>340</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>. <measure type="value"><num>Three</num></measure> glutamine saturation curves were recorded and fitted with the Michaelis-Menten equation to obtain k cat and K M Gln. In an identical setup, no glutaminase activity (<measure type="value"><num>12</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> glutamine) could be detected for LUCA-HisH (<measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>) in complex with ligand-bound LUCA-HisF (<measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure>; <measure type="value"><num>200</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> ProFAR). The extent to which LUCA-HisF liganded with ProFAR activates zmHisH had to be determined in a discontinuous assay, since NAD + also exhibits a stimulating effect on glutaminase activity <!--6--> . To this end, <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> glutamine were incubated at <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> with <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> zmHisH and <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> LUCA-HisF either in the absence of ProFAR or in the presence of <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> ProFAR. <measure type="value"><num>150</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="µl">µl</measure></measure> aliquots of the reaction mixture were collected after , , <measure type="list"><num>15</num><num>30</num><num>45</num> and <num>60</num> (only in the absence of ProFAR) <measure type="TIME" unit="min">minutes</measure></measure> and spun through a <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="kDa">kDa</measure></measure> filter (Roth) to remove the enzymes. The stimulation factor is the quotient k cat (ProFAR saturated)/ k cat (without ProFAR) v max was calculated from the linear increase of glutamate production with time, which was determined with the help of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="DENSITY" unit="mg/ml">mg/ml</measure></measure> glutamate dehydrogenase and <measure type="value"><num>0.7</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> APAD + (Sigma) (the reaction mixture was diluted <measure type="value"><num>1:7.5</num></measure>, and absorption was measured at <measure type="value"><num>363</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>). All measurements were performed in triplicates. ProFAR to PRFAR isomerisation activity (HisA reaction) was measured with the enzymatic assay described for the ammonia-dependent HisF reaction, however in presence of an excess of HisF 46 . PRA to CdRP isomerisation activity (TrpF reaction) was followed at <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> by a fluorimetric assay (excitation at <measure type="value"><num>350</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>, emission at <measure type="value"><num>400</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>) <!--47,48--> . The substrate PRA was generated in situ by <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> yeast anthranilate phosphoribosyl transferase from anthranilate and PRPP, which was provided in a <measure type="value"><num>30-fold</num></measure> molar excess. Moreover, <measure type="value"><num>2.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> indole-3-glycerol phosphate synthase from T. maritima were added to prevent product inhibition. To test for enzymatic activity in vivo, the gene coding for LUCA-HisF was subcloned into the pTNA vector, which allows for constitutive expression in E. coli <!--49--> . The resulting pTNA-LUCA-hisF plasmid was used to transform cells of auxotrophic hisF, hisA or trpF E. coli strains <!--50,51--> . These strains lack the hisF, hisA, or trpF gene on their chromosome and are, therefore, unable to grow on medium without histidine or tryptophan, respectively. Growth experiments and controls were performed as described <!--50--> .</p>
		<p>Structure determination of LUCA-HisF. The gene coding for LUCA-HisF was synthesized, cloned into a plasmid, and expressed in E. coli. The LUCA-HisF protein was predominantly found in the soluble fraction of the host cell extract, and purified in a <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> step process using ion exchange chromatography, ammonia sulfate precipitation, and size exclusion chromatography. Purified LUCA-HisF was crystallized and its <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure>-dimensional structure was determined at <measure type="value"><num>1.48</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure></measure> resolution by molecular replacement based on the structure of tmHisF <!--52--> ( Figure 2, Table S1). LUCA-HisF (PDB ID 4EVZ) adopts the conserved () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel structure observed in the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> extant HisF proteins from Pyrobaculum aerophilum (PDB ID 1H5Y), Thermus thermophilus (PDB ID 1KA9), and T. maritima (PDB ID 1THF), for which crystal structures have been previously determined. The superposition of LUCA-HisF with each of these structures by means of STAMP <!--53--> resulted in an overall root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) ranging from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.14">1.14</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure> to <num atMost="1.43">1.43</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure></measure>. In agreement with the postulated evolution of the () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel fold from a () <measure type="value"><num>4</num></measure>half-barrel <!--54,55--> , LUCA-HisF displays a clear <measure type="value"><num>two-fold</num></measure> symmetry: The superposition of its N-terminal <!--encoding problem--><!--[() [1][2][3][4] ]-->and Cterminal <!--encoding problem--><!--[() [5][6][7][8] ]-->halves yielded an RMSD of <measure type="value"><num>1.68</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure></measure>, which is similar to the corresponding values for the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> extant HisF proteins (<measure type="list"><num>1.27</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure> for 1H5Y, <num>1.52</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure> for 1KA9, and <num>1.69</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="Å">Å</measure></measure> for 1THF). Consistent with the internal symmetry, the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> catalytically important aspartate residues <!--5--> are found on opposite sides of the active site at the C-terminal ends of β-strand 1 and β-strand 5. Likewise, the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> co-crystallized phosphate groups, which represent the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> phosphate groups of the substrate PRFAR (Figure 1), are anchored by the C-terminal ends of β-strands 3 and 4, and β-strands 7 and 8, respectively (Figure 2A). Moreover, a stabilizing salt-bridge cluster at the N-terminal end of the β-barrel, which contains <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> charged and invariant residues, which form the gate to the cyclase ammonia channel <!--6,,3843--> , is also present in LUCA-HisF ( Figure 2B).</p>
		<p>Stability and folding mechanism of LUCA-HisF. The thermal stability of LUCA-HisF was determined by differential scanning calorimetry (DSC), which monitors overall unfolding, and the heat-induced decrease of the far-UV CD signal, which indicates the loss of secondary structure. The combination of both methods showed that thermal unfolding of LUCA-HisF is a <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-step process with apparent transition Figure 3. GdmCl-induced equilibrium unfolding/refolding transitions of LUCA-HisF. The transitions were followed by Trp/Tyr fluorescence (excitation at <measure type="value"><num>280</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>; emission at <measure type="value"><num>320</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>) in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> Tris/HCl buffer, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>. Closed symbols represent the unfolding experiment, started with folded protein, and open symbols represent the refolding experiment, started with protein that was previously unfolded in <measure type="value"><num>6.0</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure> GdmCl. The continuous line represents a fit to the unfolding transition on the basis of the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-state model. The dashed lines indicate the baselines for the pure N and U states. The thermodynamic parameters deduced from the analysis are given in the text and listed in Table S2. midpoints of about <measure type="list"><num>70</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure> and <num>100</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> ( Figure S3A+B). These results characterize LUCA-HisF as an enzyme with a high resistance to heat. Interestingly, even higher denaturation temperatures were previously observed for enzymes from the common ancestors of Bacteria, Archaea and Archaea/Eukaryota <!--16--> . These findings and our results are in agreement with rRNA and protein sequence analyses which have provided independent support for the increase of thermotolerance from the LUCA to the ancestors of Bacteria and Archaea-Eukaryota</p>
		<p>. Furthermore, the conformational stability of LUCA-HisF was analyzed by GdmCl-induced equilibrium unfolding and refolding transitions. The loss or gain of tertiary structure was probed by protein (Tyr/Trp) fluorescence. The equilibrium unfolding and refolding curves superpose well, which proves the reversibility of unfolding (Figure 3). Moreover, the transitions are adequately described by the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-state model <!--41--> , indicating that no significant amounts of stable equilibrium intermediates are populated. <!--the unit should be "kJ mol^-1 M^-1" but M is absent + problem with the powers of -1--><!-- The analysis yielded an m-value of ~ <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="ENERGY" unit="kJ">kJ</measure></measure> mol --></p>
		<p>, a transition midpoint ( [D]1/2) at <measure type="value"><num>1.2</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="M">M</measure></measure> GdmCl, and a free energy of unfolding in the absence of denaturant (G D ) of <measure type="value"><num>18</num> <measure type="ENERGY" unit="kJ/mol">kJ mol-1</measure></measure>. LUCA-HisF has a lower G D but a comparably high mvalue as tmHisF and its artificially designed precursors Sym1 and Sym2 <!--39,40--> , indicating that it is comparably compact as these proteins but less stable ( Figure S4A, Table S2). Folding and unfolding kinetics followed by Tyr/Trp fluorescence, showed that the reduced stability of LUCA-HisF is due to strongly increased unfolding rates of LUCA-HisF in comparison to tmHisF ( Figure S5A). The comparison of the refolding kinetics of LUCA-HisF, tmHisF, Sym1, and Sym2 followed by fluorescence and far-UV CD (Supporting Information) showed that all <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> proteins share a common sequential folding mechanism including a non-productive burst-phase intermediate ( Figure S4B) and <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> productive intermediates ( Figure S5). The rate-limiting step that synchronizes folding is conserved ( Figure S6). (Table 1). As ancient enzymes have been proposed to be less specific (more promiscuous) than their modern descendants 57 , we tested LUCA-HisF for its ability to catalyze related metabolic reactions. The homologous enzyme HisA, which precedes HisF in the histidine biosynthesis pathway, catalyzes the Amadori rearrangement of ProFAR to PRFAR. HisA shares with HisF the overall () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel fold as well as the location of the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> symmetry-related catalytic aspartate residues and phosphate binding sites <!--52--> . Phosphoribosyl anthranilate (PRA) isomerase (TrpF) catalyzes an Amadori rearrangement in tryptophan biosynthesis analogous to HisA in histidine biosynthesis <!--49-->. Remarkably, a single amino acid exchange in the HisA and HisF proteins from T. maritima leads to TrpF activity, suggesting that these <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> phosphate-binding () <measure type="value"><num>8</num></measure>-barrel proteins have evolved from a common precursor <!--48,58--> . We examined LUCA-HisF for the isomerisation activity towards ProFAR and PRA. However, no substrate turnover could be detected, even in the presence of <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> protein. These findings were complemented by assessing catalytic activity in vivo using metabolic selection. For this purpose, a plasmid harboring the LUCA-HisF gene was used to transform auxotrophic E. coli strains lacking either the intrinsic hisF, hisA, or trpF gene. When plated on minimal medium without histidine or tryptophan, the hisF cells formed visible colonies within <measure type="value"><num>24</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure>, whereas the hisA and trpF cells did not grow within <measure type="value"><num>one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">week</measure></measure>. Taken together, these results demonstrate that LUCA-HisF is a monofunctional enzyme.</p>
		<p>whether LUCA-HisF contains all structural elements required for complex formation, substrate channeling and allosteric communication, we assayed its functional interaction with the extant zmHisH enzyme from Zymomonas mobilis. For this purpose, zmHisH was produced in E. coli and purified. The binding of zmHisH to LUCA-HisF was analyzed via fluorescence titration 5 , which showed that the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> proteins form a stoichiometric complex with a thermodynamic dissociation constant (K D ) of <measure type="value"><num>113</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> ( Figure 4A).</p>
		<p>The steady-state kinetic constants k cat and K M PRFAR of LUCAHisF in presence of zmHisH and saturating concentrations of glutamine (glutamine-dependent cyclase activity) compare well with the above reported ammonia-dependent cyclase activity (Table 1). This outcome confirms the functionality of the LUCA-HisF/zmHisH complex, as ammonia produced at the active site of HisH by means of glutamine hydrolysis is used as efficiently by LUCA-HisF as externally added ammonia. Moreover, this finding suggests that ammonia is transported from HisH to the active site of the synthase through a molecular channel formed by the central -barrel of HisF Figure 4. Fluorescence titration curve of zmHisH and LUCAHisH with LUCA-HisF and activation of zmHisH by LUCAHisF. (A) LUCA-HisF_W138Y+W156Y was added to <measure type="value"><num>7</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="μM">μM</measure></measure> zmHisH in <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> potassium phosphate, <measure type="value"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">pH</measure> <num>7.5</num></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. Fluorescence emission at <measure type="value"><num>318</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure> was determined following excitation at <measure type="value"><num>295</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="nm">nm</measure></measure>. Quadratic fits of the obtained data points resulted in a K D value of <measure type="interval"><num type="base">113</num> (± <num type="range">1</num>) <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure>. The stoichiometry is slightly deviating from a <measure type="value"><num>1:1</num></measure> complex, indicating that a small fraction of zmHisH is not active. (B) Glutaminase activity of the LUCA-HisF/zmHisH complex in the absence (circles) and presence (triangles) of ProFAR was tested in a discontinuous assay (see Supplementary Materials for detailed information). Mean values and standard deviations of triplicate measurements are shown. <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="mM">mM</measure></measure> glutamine were incubated with <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> zmHisH and <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> LUCA-HisF at <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> in both cases. Glutaminase activity is enhanced <measure type="value"><num>13-fold</num></measure> in the presence of ProFAR (see Table 1). (C) Titration of <measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="µM">µM</measure></measure> LUCAHisH with LUCA-HisF_W138Y+W156Y was performed and analyzed analogous to (A), yielding a stoichiometric complex with a K D value of <measure type="interval"><num type="base">4</num> (± <num type="range">2</num>) <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>LUCA, as observed for extant HisF enzymes <!--43,59--> . Furthermore, glutamine hydrolysis by zmHisH in presence of LUCAHisF and saturating concentrations of the substrate analogue ProFAR (glutaminase activity) is as efficient as glutaminase activity of HisH from T. maritima (tmHisH) in complex with ProFAR-liganded tmHisF <!--4--> (Table 1). The comparison of the zmHisH activity in the presence and absence of ProFAR indicates a <measure type="value"><num>13-fold</num></measure> stimulation by the HisF-ligand in this nonnative complex ( Figure 4B), which is <measure type="value"><num>23-fold</num></measure> lower than the stimulating effect of ProFAR in the native tmHisF/tmHisH complex (Table 1).</p>
		<p>Following the characterization of LUCA-HisF, we also reconstructed the amino acid sequence of the corresponding glutaminase LUCA-HisH. Again, we used the tree t HisF_HisH , but opted for the phylogeny-aware gap placement of PRANK <!--29--> to deduce LUCA-HisH from the MSA HisH ext , which contains several insertions and deletions. The gene coding for LUCAHisH was synthesized, cloned into a plasmid, and expressed in E. coli. The produced protein was soluble and could be purified by a combination of heat denaturation and Ni 2+ affinity chromatography. As observed for LUCA-HisF, LUCAHisH exhibits a high thermotolerance. Unfolding followed by CD resulted in a single transition with a midpoint of about <measure type="value"><num>79</num> <measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> ( Figure S3C). Complex formation between LUCA-HisH and LUCA-HisF was probed by fluorescence titration <!--5--> . Both proteins interacted stoichiometrically with very high affinity as demonstrated by a K D value of <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="CONCENTRATION" unit="nM">nM</measure></measure> ( Figure 4C). However, when testing the LUCA-HisF/LUCA-HisH complex for glutamine-dependent cyclase activity or LUCA-HisH for the hydrolysis of glutamine in the presence of LUCA-HisF and saturating concentrations of ProFAR, no enzymatic turnover could be determined. Thus, other than LUCA-HisF, LUCAHisH is catalytically inactive. As outlined in the following, uncertainties in the reconstruction process are probably responsible for this finding.</p>
		<p>The evolutionary models underlying reconstruction consider each residue-position independently of all other positions. Thus, the reliability of a given reconstruction is not limited by sequence length, but by the composition of the MSA and the topology of the deduced phylogenetic tree. In the case of LUCA-HisF, <measure type="value"><num>49 out of 250</num></measure> residues are strictly conserved, among them are the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> active site aspartate residues <!--5--> and amino acids contributing to the central ammonia channel <!--38,43--> ( Figure 2). Furthermore, the <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> central nodes of t HisF_HisH ( Figure S1) possess posterior probabilities ≥ <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.88">0.88</num></measure>. Taken together, these features suggest that tree topology and choice of the most likely residues for the corresponding predecessors and LUCA-HisF is largely unambiguous. In contrast, in the case of LUCA-HisH, only <measure type="value"><num>21 out of 226</num></measure> residues are strictly conserved, which makes the reconstruction much more prone to uncertainties.</p>
		<p>Even more than a certain conservation of amino acid sequence composition, conservation of sequence length is an important prerequisite for a valid reconstruction. Along these lines, the sequence lengths of extant and reconstructed thioredoxins, which is the only other example for a fully functional enzyme from the LUCA era <!--16--> , are very similar. In contrast, MSA HisH ext contains several gaps. Nonetheless, the phylogeny-aware gap placement by means of PRANK did allow us to reconstruct a stable LUCA-HisH protein with a fully functional protein-protein interface, albeit lacking enzyme activity. Obviously, t HisF_HisH was sufficiently informative to reconstruct ancestral residues at positions whose role did not change during evolution such as the catalytic triad <!--3--> and residues involved in binding of the substrate glutamine,-8as deduced from the structure of tmHisH <!--6--> . In contrast, reconstruction seems to have failed at residue-positions that underwent frequent changes during evolution due to insertions and deletions. It has to be shown that highly articulated phylogenetic trees will enable us to reconstruct the correct series of indels and to further improve reconstruction for such difficult cases.</p>
		<p>Taken together, LUCA-HisF, which presumably existed about <measure type="value"><num>4 billion</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> ago, is similar to extant HisF proteins with respect to structure, stability, folding, and activity. Since similar results were obtained for predecessors of thioredoxin, <!--16--> .experimental evidence accumulates for the existence of highly effective and non-promiscuous enzymes in the LUCA era. In addition, LUCA-HisF forms a stable complex with LUCA-HisH and a functional enzyme complex with the extant glutaminase zmHisH. It is therefore plausible to assume that the evolution of the ImGP-S complex, including ammonia channeling and allosteric communication, has been completed in the LUCA era. Thus, our experimental findings are in line with the hypothesis that the LUCA had already a rather diverse metabolism, which was as sophisticated as are the metabolisms of its archaeal and bacterial successors <!--60--> .</p>
		<p>Nucleotide and amino acid sequences of LUCA-HisF and LUCA-HisH. Oligonucleotides used for the construction of LUCA_hisF_W138Y+W156Y and for the genomic amplification of zmHisH. Comparison of the folding mechanism of LUCA-HisF, T. maritima HisF, and its artificial precursors Sym1 and Sym2. Crystal structure determination of LUCAHisF (PDB ID 4EVZ): Data collection and refinement statistics (Table S1). Thermodynamic unfolding parameters of LUCA-HisF, T. maritima HisF, Sym1, and Sym2 (Table S2). Phylogenetic tree t HisF_HisH used for the reconstruction of LUCA-HisF and LUCA-HisH ( Figure S1). PRANK output for the reconstruction of LUCA-HisH ( Figure S2). Thermal denaturation of LUCA-HisF and LUCA-HisH ( Figure S3). Equilibrium unfolding transitions of LUCA-HisF, T. maritima HisF, Sym1, and Sym2, and formation of a burst-phase intermediate by LUCA-HisF ( Figure S4). Apparent rate constants () and amplitudes of refolding and unfolding kinetics of LUCAHisF ( Figure S5). Unifying folding mechanism for LUCAHisF, T. maritima HisF, and Sym1 and Sym2 ( Figure S6). References for Supporting Information.This material is available free of charge via the Internet at http://pubs.acs.org.</p>
		<p>Rainer.Merkl@ur.de and Reinhard.Sterner@ur.de</p>
		<p>The first <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> authors contributed equally. All authors have given approval to the final version of the manuscript.</p>
		<p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
		<p>B.R. and J.S. were supported by fellowships from the Cusanuswerk and the Fonds der Chemischen Industrie, respectively.</p>
	</text>
</tei>