<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>The Tour de France is one the world"s largest sports events. The <measure type="value"><num>three</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="week">week</measure></measure> race attracts <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10000000">10</num> to <num atMost="15000000">15 million</num></measure> (non-paying) spectators along the roads each year and individual stages are watched by <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="15000000">15</num> to <num atMost="20000000">20 million</num></measure> TV viewers worldwide (see chapter 5). Although generally cycling races are not lucrative, the Tour de France organiser"s balance sheet reveals that the Tour has always been profitable in the past <measure type="interval"><num atMost="2">two</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure><!--see issue 63-->.</p>
		<p>How can this attractiveness and the economic success story be explained? Most sports economists are used to turn to a contest"s outcome uncertainty as a first explanatory variable for success. However, fans of the Tour de France are not often surprised by the name of the final winner of the race, usually not even by the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> riders sharing the podium. Nobody needs more than a few riders" names to predict with great certainty who the winner will be. Thus, explaining Tour de France success by outcome uncertainty and its usual metrics in terms of competitive balance must be checked carefully.</p>
		<p>Tour de France attendance and TV audience do not seem to be seriously threatened and surely not definitely affected by recurring doping scandals either. This was neither the case after big doping issues <measure type="value"><num>many</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> ago (for example when Tom Simpson died during the climb of the Mont Ventoux in <measure type="value"><date when="1967">1967</date></measure>), nor in the past <!-- see issue 63 --><measure type="interval"><num atMost="20">twenty</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (from the Festina affair in <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1998">1998</date> up to Lance Armstrong being stripped from all his Tour de France wins in <date to-iso="2012">2012</date></measure>). Although doping seems not to be an immediate threat to the popularity of the Tour de France, it is clear that doping detection and doping sanctions have not been efficient and effective enough so far to clean this sport contest from the use of forbidden doping substances and practices. This raises the issue of what could be a better way to combat the use of doping in the Tour de France or in cycling in general.</p>
		<p>The chapter goes as follows. In the first section it is demonstrated how the Tour de France is a high quality product. This is a result from its accurate design, its management, its economic model and its finance structure, both in comparison to other mega-sporting events and with reference to tournament theory. It is not easy to assess the competitive balance in the Tour de France since, as was demonstrated in chapter 10, it is at the same time an individual and a team sport contest. After reviewing some results published in literature so far, a new metrics for evaluating competitive balanced in the Tour de France is presented in section 2. Finally, the Tour de France cannot ignore doping as a potential threat to fan attendance and TV viewing. We therefore discuss the issue of doping and a new procedure to deal with doping in section 3.</p>
		<p>A top sports event offered for free will automatically attract a significant demand. Beyond this basic and quite obvious cause of Tour de France attractiveness, its design and management are also explanations of its success. As we will show below, the latter may be due, to some extent, to the Tour fitting with the recommendations derived from tournament theory and to basically sticking to a modern model of professional sport finance.</p>
		<p>The Tour de France is managed by Amaury Sport Organisation (ASO). ASO also organises other professional cycling races (such as Paris-Roubaix or the Critérium du Dauphiné Libéré) as well as golf tournaments, track and field events, car races and horse-riding contests. Professional road cycling accounts for close to <measure type="value"><num>70</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of ASO revenue, mainly because of the success of the Tour de France (Desbordes, 2006). Since ASO is a privately-owned company, it aims at profit maximising and designs its strategy accordingly. A first strategic tool consists in multiplying the number of trophies within a race. This process started up in <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1919">1919</date> with introducing the yellow jersey and lasted until <date to-iso="1989">1989</date></measure> when the number of trophies has nearly stabilised, respectively rewarding the best rider overall (yellow jersey), the best climber (polka-dot jersey), the best sprinter (green jersey), the best young rider (any rider aged below <measure type="interval"><num atMost="25">25</num></measure>, white jersey), and the best-ranked team. From time to time other trophies appeared and vanished again after <measure type="value"><num>some</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. By creating "different races within the race", ASO attempted and succeeded in making the Tour de France a more vivid contest with multiple opportunities for duels between riders or teams competing for a given trophy and changes in the tactics adopted by riders or teams during the course of the race.</p>
		<p><measure type="value"><num>Two</num></measure> other factors that attract people to see riders on the Tour de France roads are linked together. The first one is the riders" performance, the second one lies in the hardness of the race. Based on the number of racing days and the number of rest days per racing day, the Tour de France became much harder after the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1920" to-iso="1929">1920s</date></measure> with the number of racing <measure type="interval"><measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure> stabilising up to about <num atMost="20">20</num></measure> <!-- case not supported: similar to unit embedded in numerical value --><!-- while <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> rest day per <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> racing days became the usual ratio -->. <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by interval --><!-- Before the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1920" to-iso="1929">1920s</date></measure>  -->the number of stages was usually <measure type="interval"><num atMost="15">15</num></measure> at most and the riders enjoyed at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> of rest after each stage. The overall riding distance was <measure type="value"><num>2,428</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">kilometers</measure></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="1903">1903</date></measure> and rose to a maximum of <measure type="interval"><num atMost="5745">5,745</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">kilometers</measure></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="1926">1926</date></measure>. Since then the distance shortened to about <measure type="value"><num>3,500</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">kilometers</measure></measure> on average. Thus, compared with the initial era of so-called "road"s convicts" (les forçats de la route in French), riders now spend more days on the roads and have less often time to rest. <!-- cases not supported: intervals mixed with intervals, bounded by intervals, etc. --><!-- However, this has been made feasible by reducing the average stage length from over <measure type="value"><num>300</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">kilometers</measure></measure> until <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1926">1926</num> to less than <num atMost="200">200</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">kilometers</measure></measure> since the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1960">1960s</date></measure>. Consequently, the average duration of a stage, i.e. the time actually spent by riders on their bikes, fell from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> to <num atMost="16">16</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure> before the <measure type="interval"><date to-iso="1930">1930s</date></measure> to slightly over <measure type="value"><num>4</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure> in the <measure type="value"><date when="2000">2000s</date></measure>.  -->The race also became harder due to the introduction of mountain stages. The first mountain ever climbed in the Tour de France was the Ballon d"Alsace in the Vosges region in <measure type="value"><date when="1905">1905</date></measure>. A <measure type="value"><num>handful</num> of <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> later, high-mountain stages in the Pyrenees (<measure type="value"><date when="1910">1910</date></measure>) and the Alps (<measure type="value"><date when="1911">1911</date></measure>) were introduced. However, the number of passes over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1000">1,000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">meters</measure></measure> in a given Tour de France has not increased significantly on average <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by interval --><!-- since the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1920">1920s</date></measure> -->.</p>
		<p>Apart from the physical hardness of the Tour de France, it is also the increase in riders" performances that has made the Tour attractive to spectators. The overall average speed of the yellow jersey winner was between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="25">25</num> and <num atMost="30">30</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km/h">kilometers per hour (km/h)</measure></measure> <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by interval --><!-- until the late <measure type="interval"><date to-iso="1930">1930s</date></measure> -->. Since World War II it has steadily increased. From <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="25.7">25.7</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km/h">km/h</measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="1903">1903</date></measure> to <num atMost="41.7">41.7</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km/h">km/h</measure></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="2005">2005</date></measure> (the fastest Tour ever) is an improvement of <measure type="value"><num>62</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. Part of this acceleration is due to technical progress affecting riders" bikes such as the introduction of derailleur gears, the increase in the number of gears, lighter bikes, profiled wheels, etc. (Calvet, 1981;Andreff, 1985). Improvement of the road surface, shorter stages, multiple stakes and high effort intensity in the crucial parts of the race have also triggered both higher rider performance and increased attractiveness to spectators. Improved physical and medical preparation, better nutrition, and sometimes doping may have played a role as well. Another index of riders" performance is the withdrawal ratio, the percentage of riders who do not finish all stages of the Tour de France. This ratio decreased from over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="70">70</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1920" to-iso="1929">1920s</date></measure> <!-- case not supported: interval in list --><!-- to <measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1930" to-iso="1939">1930s</date></measure> and about <measure type="value"><num>20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> during the <measure type="value"><date when="2000">2000s</date></measure> -->. The highest withdrawal ratio was reached in <measure type="value"><date when="1926">1926</date></measure> (as explained above the longest Tour de France ever held) <!--with <measure type="value"><num>126</num></measure> withdrawals out of <measure type="value"><num>162</num></measure> riders (<measure type="value"><num>77.8</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>), meaning only <measure type="value"><num>36</num></measure> riders finished the Tour de France that year-->. In <measure type="value"><date when="2009">2009</date></measure>, the lowest withdrawal ratio was recorded with <measure type="value"><num>156 out of 180</num></measure> riders finishing the Tour de France. Only <measure type="value"><num>24</num></measure> riders (<measure type="value"><num>13.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) abandoned the race.</p>
		<p>Last but not least, the Tour de France is a sports event that is supplied for free to <measure type="value"><num>millions</num></measure> of spectators along the roads. However, the demand for it is not infinite. The demand is rationed by various constraints such as the date and location of a stage or the hosting capacity of a geographical site (like the slopes of the Mont Ventoux or Alpe d"Huez), limiting the number of spectators. Nevertheless, from an economic point of view, a free sport event is likely to draw a huge attendance. Indeed, <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10000000">10</num> to <num atMost="15000000">15 million</num></measure> spectators per year attend the race over the course of <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="week">weeks</measure></measure>. This is significantly more than the biggest mega-sporting event in the world, the FIFA World Cup <!-- case not supported: mixed lists --><!-- with an attendance of <measure type="value"><num>3,115,800</num></measure> people in Germany <measure type="value"><date when="2006">2006</date></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>3,224,342</num></measure> in South Africa <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure> -->. Moreover, since all spectators cannot attend the Tour <measure type="value"><num>21</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> long, they also demand a story telling which was first supplied by newspapers, then through radio broadcasts and eventually through TV broadcasts.</p>
		<p>The Tour de France has not always been a profitable business. <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by an interval --><!-- Until the <measure type="value"><date when="1950">1950s</date></measure>, financial deficits were common (Reed, 2010).  -->The deficits vanished with rising TV rights revenues. The first Tour de France TV broadcast was the finish of the last stage at the Parc des Princes stadium in Paris in <measure type="value"><date when="1948">1948</date></measure> whereas the first TV broadcast of a mountain pass was at the Aubisque in <measure type="value"><date when="1958">1958</date></measure>. Nowadays, the Tour is the major sports event in the French broadcasting market with well over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="80">80</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure> of broadcast, ahead of the Roland Garros tennis tournament (<measure type="value"><num>77</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure>), Champions League matches, Formula 1 races and the rugby <measure type="value"><num>Six</num></measure> nations tournament. In <measure type="value"><date when="2013">2013</date></measure>, <measure type="value"><num>24 million</num></measure> French people watched the Tour de France for at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hour</measure></measure> on French television, a TV market share of slightly over <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by an interval --><!-- In chapter 5 it was explained how from the <measure type="value"><date when="1970">1970s</date></measure> on the Tour de France was also broadcast in more and more countries. --></p>
		<p>Today it is a global mega-sporting event. Over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num></measure> TV channels in <measure type="value"><num>190</num></measure> countries now broadcast the Tour de France, with live broadcast in <measure type="value"><num>60</num></measure> countries (www.aso.fr). Consequently, the Tour de France TV rights revenues have increased significantly over the years. In <measure type="value"><date when="1960">1960</date></measure>, the French public TV channel started paying TV rights for broadcasting the Tour de France. The French broadcasting rights equalled or the French professional football league broadcasting rights over <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> season (<measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>668 million</num></measure>). No detailed information on the international TV deals is available, but in chapter 3 it was shown that the global broadcasting rights for the Tour de France probably amount to about <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>50</num> million</measure> a year. As a result, the budget of the Tour de France has literally skyrocketed <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by an interval --><!-- since the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980">1980s</date></measure> -->. <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by an interval --><!-- From <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980">1980</date> to the late <date to-iso="1990">1990s</date></measure>,  -->the Tour operational budget grew from <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>5 million</num></measure> to <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>50 million</num></measure> (Mignot, 2013) primarily due to the growth of TV rights revenues that multiplied by <measure type="value"><num>65</num></measure> over the same period of time (from <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>250,000</num></measure> to <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>16 million</num></measure>). In the past decade<!--to annotate? see issue 63-->, the budget further increased from <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>77 million</num></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="2003">2003</date></measure> up to <measure type="value"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>130 million</num></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="2013">2013</date></measure>. Table 1 illustrates the financing sources of the Tour de France. Basically, <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> types of income can be distinguished: TV broadcasting rights, merchandising and sponsorship revenue, and income from municipalities. The media success story is the basis for the solid economic foundations of the Tour de France because it provided <measure type="value"><num>44</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of its overall budget in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure>. Just like in other professional sports, TV rights are now an important source of revenue, resulting from an organiser"s strategy of using its monopoly power over the Tour de France to increase these rights. <!-- case not supported: intervals bounded by intervals --><!-- From the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1950">1950s</date> to the <date to-iso="1980">1980s</date></measure> <measure type="value"><num>twothirds</num></measure> of Tour de France revenues originated from merchandising and sponsorship.  -->This kind of revenues emerged in <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1925">1925</date>-<date to-iso="1929">1929</date></measure> when the Tour had transformed from a race opposing individual riders into a race between opponent teams sponsored by trademarks and commercial companies. Since <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1930">1930</date></measure>, additional sponsorship income was generated with the introduction of a publicity caravan, i.e. <measure type="value"><num>dozens</num></measure> of vehicles preceding the riders by a <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">minutes</measure></measure> and distributing product samples to spectators (see chapter 1). The share of advertising and sponsorship revenue has declined in the past <!-- interval or value? see issue 63 --><measure type="interval"><num atMost="2">two</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>51</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the budget in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure>. Finally, each year over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="200">200</num></measure> cities are a candidate for hosting a Tour de France stage arrival and/or departure <!--OCR Problem "50,000 and €" rewriten "50, and € 000" => tags would be all mixed up if annotated--><!-- and those who are successful pay between <measure type="interval"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num atLeast="50000">50</num>, and € 000 <num atMost="100000">100,000</num></measure> for this privilege -->. However, because of the rising overall budget the share of the contributions from these cities in the total budget of the Tour de France has decreased from <measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="1952">1952</date></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure>. The Tour de France has thus also evolved towards a contemporary model of professional sports finance and developed from a so-called SSSL (= Spectators, Subsidies, Sponsors, Local) model to a MCMMG (= Media, Corporations, Merchandising, Markets, Global) model with regard to its major sources of finance (Andreff &amp; Staudohar, 2000). In the MCMMG model, media, in particular through TV broadcasting rights, have become a significant source of income for many sports. Furthermore, alongside with sponsors and gate receipts (spectators) whose share in overall finance of sports events has shrunk, new sources of finance have emerged including corporations (investment funds, big companies, Russian oligarchs, Middle Eastern sheiks enriched by oil sales, …), merchandising of non sporting goods (e.g. T-shirts) under a club"s or a player"s label, and markets. With respect to the latter, we see that money is channeled into contemporary professional sports from <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> markets: a labour market for talent in which a club makes money in selling home-educated and trained talented players and a capital market that enables to trade a club"s shares at the stock exchange and collecting money from the fans as shareholders. Most of these new sources of finance are global.</p>
		<p>From table 1 we also see that although the current Tour de France financing model is in line with big professional sports leagues such as the football English Premier League and the French Ligue 1, it remains specific in a way too. For example, its TV-dependence is slightly lower in percentage of overall revenues compared to football and merchandising and sponsorship (<measure type="value"><num>51</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) is still a more important source of income to the Tour de France organisers than TV rights revenues. This may be interpreted as either the Tour de France being in a transition phase between the SSSL and MCMMG models, or as a consequence of the absence of gate revenue which must be compensated for by sponsorship money. In fact, the lack of gate revenue potentially deprives the Tour de France of up to <measure type="value"><num>a quarter</num></measure> (like in English football) of overall revenues. The share of public money received from municipalities is more important in the Tour de France than in European football though it is now reduced to <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> only. At the end of the day, the profitability of the Tour de France is likely to be guaranteed as long as it will attract media, advertisers and sponsors even without any spectatorship income.</p>
		<p>A more theoretical reason may explain why the Tour de France is such a successful sport contest. The tournament theory (Tullock, 1980) was first conceived for analysing the efforts dedicated by competing job seekers to get a job and was then adapted to sporting contests, namely tennis tournaments (Rosen, 1986). Each participant is assumed to independently choose the quantity of resources (physical efforts) he is going to invest in view of winning the tournament and receiving the winner"s prize. His winning probability increases with this quantity. Let V stand for the value of the winner"s prize and n the number of competing participants. Each participant i dedicates an effort e i and his probability of winning p i depends on his share in the overall effort devoted by all participants that is:</p>
		<p>The financial gain of participant i is:</p>
		<p>where c i stands for marginal cost of each participant i"s effort or investment in the tournament and m is a parameter that measures the power of the tournament to discriminate across competing participants,</p>
		<p>i.e. m indicates how much <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> unit of competitor i"s effort increases his winning probability.</p>
		<p>The assumption that the organiser of a sport tournament acts profit maximising implies that the goal is to attract as many spectators as possible by gathering high quality athletes and by securing that these athletes dedicate maximal efforts to win. Therefore the organiser must conceive incentives in such a</p>
		<p>way that athletes maximise their efforts and, consequently, produce a spectacular sporting event. From tournament theory it is mathematically derived (Szymanski, 2003;Andreff, 2012) that:</p>
		<p>a/ When <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> competitor has a very high capacity to win, the tournament practically is without interest for other participants who will dedicate only a minimal effort. The organiser must avoid such a competitive imbalance.</p>
		<p>b/ Individual effort and aggregated effort of all the participants increase with the value of the winner"s prize V.</p>
		<p>c/ Individual effort decreases with the number of participants.</p>
		<p>d/ Aggregated effort increases with the number of competitors.</p>
		<p>e/ Participants" efforts are more intense in a tournament with multiple prizes, where there are several prizes or trophies at stake, as soon as the competitors" abilities to win are different.</p>
		<p>f/ The effort will be more intense the wider the gap between the winner"s prize and the prize rewarding the runner-up, and the wider the gap between the prize for the runner-up and the prize rewarding the third ranked rider, and so on. This is particularly true when the differences between the competitors" winning abilities are small.</p>
		<p>As ASO indeed aims at making a profit from organising the Tour de France, the choice of an appropriate incentive mechanism is crucial. Most of the prerequisites for a successful and attractive between more teams with fewer riders each and fewer teams with more riders each. At the end of the day, the organiser chooses the number of teams and which teams are selected to participate in Tour de</p>
		<p>France each year. As described in chapter 2, this is not without conflicting interests between the organisers of the "grand tours" (ASO, RCS and Unipublic) and the UCI claiming that all the Pro Tour teams must be invited in each "grand tour" (Rebeggiani &amp; Tondani, 2008). Total prize money in the Tour de France is now over <measure type="interval"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num atLeast="2000000">2 million</num></measure> (for a detailed analysis, see chapter 3) which, compared with other cycling races, is rather fulfilling the prerequisite (b). Since the prize money is distributed over multiple trophies, condition (e) is satisfied as well. Only condition (a) is debatable when one witnesses a rider winning the Tour de France <measure type="value"><num>five</num></measure> times like Jacques Anquetil, Eddy Merckx, Bernard Hinault and Miguel Indurain, or, in the case of the later disqualified Lance Armstrong, <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> times in a row.</p>
		<p>Condition (a) is not valid either when the yellow jersey winner is too much ahead of the secondranked rider, like in <measure type="value"><date when="1952">1952</date></measure> when Fausto Coppi won the Tour de France with a lead of over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="28">28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">minutes</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>In fact, condition (a) raises the issue of competitive balance in the Tour de France which is discussed in section 2 below. Finally, prerequisite (f) refers to the distribution of Tour de France prize money across different trophies and best-ranked riders. In the <measure type="value"><date when="2014">2014</date></measure> Tour de France, for every lower position in the general classification the prize money was more or less halved between the first <measure type="value"><num>seven</num></measure> ranked riders: from <measure type="list"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>450,000</num> for the winner over <measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>200,000</num> for the runner-up to <measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>100,000</num> for the third ranked rider, and so on to <measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>11,500</num></measure> for the rider ranked in seventh place. A similar gap is assessed as a strong effort incentive in most individual sports tournaments such as, for example, tennis. With this incentive prize structure a rider who jumps from the seventh to the fifth rank multiplies his financial gains by <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> and the same occurs when a rider jumps from the third to the first place. The prize structure for winning a stage is similar with also approximately a doubling of the monetary reward for <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> rank improvement between the <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> best ranked riders. The prize structure for the other trophies is less in tune with tournament theory. In the race for the green, the white and the polka-dot jerseys, financial gains are not doubled when a rider improves his rank by <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure>. These trophies thus clearly have a less incentive prize structure. If one ASO objective is to "multiply the races within the race" this must not go as far as disturbing the contention for the yellow jersey. That is the reason why incentives are significantly lower (<measure type="list"><measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>25,000</num> for the green and polka-dot jersey winners, <measure type="CURRENCY" unit="euro">€</measure> <num>20,000</num></measure> for the white jersey winner) and less structured according to the tournament theory for trophies that only appeal to specialised riders like sprinters or climbers.</p>
		<p>It should be remarked though that this focus on prize money is not always relevant in the context of cycling races. There are significant indirect financial and non-financial gains too from winning, such as a salary increase and fame. Since, as was shown in chapter 3, to an individual cyclist salaries are much more important than prize money, this incentive could be higher than the pure prize money.</p>
		<p>When economists attempt to explain a successful attendance and/or TV audience for a sports event, they are used to refer to competitive balance. Applying this concept to professional road cycling is not evident but in chapter 12 this issue is discussed in detail. An introduction to competitive balance in the Tour de France and a new tentative metrics is presented here.</p>
		<p>Outcome uncertainty is at the heart of sports economics (Rottenberg, 1956;Neale, 1964). When a big gap between the aggregated players" talent of <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> teams is witnessed, there is a quite low probability to win for <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> team while the other is nearly certain of winning. In such a case, outcome uncertainty is negligible and the game exhibits a competitive imbalance or a weak competitive balance. If, by chance and as it happens sometimes, the underdog defeats the favourite team, the outcome will be assessed as a "surprise". However, the notion of a surprising sporting outcome is still in the cradle (M. &amp; W.</p>
		<p>Andreff, 2014). A similar approach is used to assess the outcome uncertainty of a sport contest or a sports league. Sports economists often assume and then attempt demonstrating that a balanced sport contest or game does attract big audiences while a low attendance signals a weak competitive balance.</p>
		<p>This view has been mitigated in recent years. A distinction between <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> types of sport show consumers has been successfully tested. On the one hand, fans and season ticket holders basically expect the greatest possible number of wins from their favourite team and thus care less about competitive balance. On the other hand, TV viewers and casual spectators often care less about the winning team and are attracted by more balanced games. For example, for NBA basketball it has been shown that fans wish at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2/3">two-thirds</num></measure><!--to check two thirds = 2/3 - see issue 66--> of wins for their favourite team (Rascher &amp; Solmes, 2007).</p>
		<p>This differentiation in the product market for sport shows has recently been integrated in a disequilibrium model of a team sports league (Andreff, 2014a).</p>
		<p>Taking the audience interest as a benchmark, the Tour de France would definitely be considered to be a well-balanced competition given its <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10000000">10</num> to <num atMost="15000000">15 million</num></measure> people attendance. But since this sport show is offered for free, such a conclusion might be misleading. If one wants to really test the concept of competitive balance, a next issue is to develop an accurate metrics. With team sports, the theoretically best competitive balance for a game is when both teams have a <measure type="value"><num>50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> probability of winning. The most used proxy for this probability consists of comparing the win percentages of the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> teams and, for the league as a whole, of designing some sort of win dispersion or concentration indices (Andreff, 2012;</p>
		<p>Groot, 2008), the most famous being the Noll-Scully index. These indices are static as they pertain to just <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> game or <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> season. A dynamic competitive balance index refers to <measure type="value"><num>several</num></measure> seasons in a row or, in the case of Tour de France, to <measure type="value"><num>several</num> consecutive <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Usually dynamic competitive balance is measured by looking at a rank correlation coefficient across seasons.</p>
		<p>The only (albeit serious) problem with aforementioned indices is that just like any other cycling race, the Tour de France is not a bilateral confrontation between <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> teams or <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> riders and the competitive balance indexes for team sports league thus cannot be applied as such. One cannot derive and calculate a win percentage between, for example, Team Sky and Movistar from their performances in previous cycling races since their sporting outcomes are not the result of a bilateral confrontation but of an overall series of contests with many other cycling teams. Since it is not possible to define bilateral win percentages, another metrics has to be developed. This is all the more the case because road cycling is at the same time an individual sport and a team sport. There is just <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> yellow jersey winner but all riders are grouped into teams and no one can win the yellow jersey without the work and effort from his teammates. Moreover, given the multiple trophies that are at stake, <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">two</num></measure> or more teams often divide labour and co-operate (sometimes collude) in view of winning a specific trophy.</p>
		<p>Such division of labour usually alleviates competition, influences the competitive balance, and if it happens too frequently, may offset the organizer"s incentives to solicit more effort from the riders.</p>
		<p><!-- case not supported: list of intervals --><!-- Mignot (2013) 1978-79 and 1981-82), Miguel Indurain (1991-95) and Lance Armstrong (1999)(2000)(2001)(2002)(2003)(2004)(2005).  -->Although this leads to the impression that the Tour is very imbalanced, the conclusion relies on the performance of only <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> rider, making it even less robust than above. Nevertheless, it means that one feature often associated with outcome uncertainty, namely an unforeseeable sporting result (Neale, 1964) is missing or really weak in Tour de France.</p>
		<p>A common limitation to all previous indexes is that they assess competitive balance only on the basis of <measure type="list"><num>one</num> or <num>two</num></measure> riders or, at maximum, of a small number of riders in contention for the yellow jersey as (<measure type="list"><num>2008</num>, <num>2012</num> and <num>2013</num></measure>) out of <measure type="value"><num>seven</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Now, if m 1 , m 2 , …, m n stand for all teams" actual average times (with n the number of teams), then we can determine the actual average team time for the whole peloton (as follows:</p>
		<p>We define  as the standard deviation of the distribution of all actual teams" average times around the mean . The standard deviation is a potential index of competitive balance. For example, one can compare   for Tour de France 1 to    for Tour 2 and conclude from     that Tour 1 is more balanced than Tour 2 since the teams" strengths are more closely matched in the former than in the latter.</p>
		<p>Remind that the famous Noll-Scully index compares the actual standard deviation of win percentages to a theoretical optimal one, the best possible competitive balance when all teams have à <measure type="value"><num>50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure></p>
		<p>probability to win. What would be the best Tour de France competitive balance? It is obvious that when  = <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> all teams have shown exactly the same strength. However such perfect competitive balance is as much theoretical as the Noll-Scully benchmark of all teams having an equal <measure type="value"><num>50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> probability to win. Its practical interest is limited in the real world. Another index is required to qualify how much one specific Tour de France is balanced or imbalanced. Here <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> options exist. One is to refer to the coefficient of variation  = . A statistical distribution is considered as extremely scattered (i.e. the Tour is extremely imbalanced) when ≥<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure>, and the closer to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> the less it is scattered. As a benchmark  may be accepted for concluding that a Tour is balanced. A second option is to compare the observed distribution of team"s actual average times with a Gaussian (or normal) distribution. In the latter, <measure type="value"><num>68.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the population is contained between and . If for a given Tour de France the number of teams comprised within this interval is smaller than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="68.8">68.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, not only the Tour is imbalanced but it must be assessed as abnormally imbalanced since teams" strengths are less concentrated in the central part of the distribution than in a Gaussian population. Such an imbalanced situation could result from having too many weak teams participating in the Tour de</p>
		<p>France. Conversely, if the number of teams in the above interval is bigger than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="68.8">68.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, then the Tour is less imbalanced than it would have been under the conditions of a Gaussian distribution. The <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure> Tour de France with a <measure type="value"><num>68.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of teams within the (; ) interval has a nearly</p>
		<p>Gaussian distribution of teams" strengths and can be taken as a benchmark. Several Tours (<measure type="list"><num>2007</num>,<num>2011</num>,<num>2012</num></measure> <!--deletion of '2013':"(2007,2011,2012 and 2013) concentrate a smaller [...]" see the pdf--><!-- table --><!-- Between brackets: the number of teams common between <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> Tours de France *** significant at <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>; ** significant at <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>; * significant at <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> --></p>
		<p>This leads to a major conclusion. When <measure type="value"><num>multiple</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> are considered, the Tour de France generally shows a dynamic competitive balance, with uncertainty and unpredictability. However, when just <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> Tour is considered, the Tour de France rather exhibits a static imbalance. This implies that in the course of the race it is rather predictable what teams will perform the best, but from one Tour to the other the outcome is much more unpredictable due to team changes, team recruitment, the selection of riders for the next Tour, and the resulting team performance. One could therefore conclude that although each Tour is a new story, for each story the scenario is rather well known to the spectators.</p>
		<p>Nevertheless, the Tour still attracts <measure type="value"><num>tens of millions</num></measure> of people along the roads and in front of television sets. This confirms earlier observations in sports economics research that questioned the importance of competitive balance as the main determinant of viewership interest for a sports event.</p>
		<p>3. Doping did not hinder Tour de France success, but could it be fought better?</p>
		<p>The Tour de France success story has not been disturbed too much so far by its long-lasting association with doping, not even by the doping troubles of the past <measure type="value"><num>decade</num></measure><!-- see issue 63 -->. Does this mean that doping has no impact on the Tour outcome? Or that fans and spectators are unaware of doping? Or that the anti-doping combat has become so effective that doping use is actually on its way down within the peloton? Doping in cycling is discussed in detail in chapter 13. An introduction to doping in the Tour de France and an innovative procedure to better deal with the use of doping is presented below.</p>
		<p>It is very difficult to empirically test the impact of doping on the outcome of a sports contest since there is no available database about who is doped or not in a team, in a sport, or in the Tour de France.</p>
		<p>As a consequence, the above used competitive balance indexes as well as the analyses of sporting success determinants (Torgler, 2007) or team efficiency ( Rogge et al., 2013) in the Tour de France, are for certain distorted to an unknown extent. In fact, they do not include an explanatory or dummy variable supposed to capture the doping effect on rider and team performances. For example, the estimated probability to be ranked among the first <measure type="value"><num>25</num></measure> riders for the yellow jersey trophy calculated by</p>
		<p>Torgler (2007) Despite the overwhelming evidence on doping, the Tour de France audience has not dropped over the years. A recent inquiry in Flanders (Van Reeth &amp; Lagae, 2014) however, did show that most spectators do prefer "clean" performances in the Tour over doping-prone exceptional results. The study shows they are well aware of doping that plagues the Tour de France. But although they think that it is a problem that will never disappear completely from cycling and thus will continue to affect its credibility, cycling fans do not refrain from attending or watching it on TV, as another study ) has demonstrated. A new doping case during the Tour de France appears to have no significant immediate impact on average TV audiences of the Tour de France and triggers a small <measure type="value"><num>7.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> decrease in peak TV audiences. However, the impact of doping seems to have a stronger impact in the year following the unveiling of a major doping case, like the Festina case in <measure type="list"><date when="1998">1998</date> or the Contador case in <date when="2012">2012</date></measure>. A significant <measure type="value"><num>17.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> decline in average TV audience and a <measure type="value"><num>7.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> fall in peak TV audience is recorded for the following Tour de France. This impact seems to temporary though since the effect only lasts for <measure type="value"><num>one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure>. Although apparently it has not strongly affected Tour attendance and TV audiences so far, doping may still be damaging the Tour success story in the long run. This requires new ideas on how to combat doping in cycling more efficiently.</p>
		<p>Anti-doping policy is still very much inspired by a traditional view on doping. In this vision, doping is considered to be fraudulent behaviour and therefore must be analysed based on the theory of the "economics of crime" (Becker, 1968), as it has been applied to sports (Bourg, 2000;Maennig, 2002).</p>
		<p>Detection and sanctioning is then validated by an argument that runs as follows: a/ since it is forbidden by law, doping is fraudulent, and must be controlled; b/ since doping is profitable for an athlete in terms of wins and revenues, even it is forbidden athletes are prone to use it; c/ in order to stop doping, its costs to the athlete must be raised through stronger sanctions (fine, suspension, …) up to a level where it is no longer profitable to dope. In the end, an athlete makes the decision to dope if the expected net gain is positive, i.e. if the extra benefits (revenue, fame, …) that can be expected from the use of doping exceed the costs of using doping (actual costs and expected costs of sanctions if caught).</p>
		<p>A new analytical approach to doping in sports economics relies on game theory. The starting point is to basically assume that riders dope themselves because it corresponds to their deeply rooted economic and financial interests, and not because they are bad by nature, professional cheaters or criminals. <measure type="value"><num>Two</num></measure> papers written in the wake of the Festina scandal (Eber &amp; Thépot, 1999 andBerentsen, 2002) analyse doping as a result of a prisoner"s dilemma, one of the most famous problems in game theory. In a nutshell, the doping game is a prisoner"s dilemma adapted here to cycling where: a/ there is a (financial and health) cost borne by riders when they use doping; b/ the use of doping substances and techniques enables a rider to enhance his performances; c/ if, in an assumed <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>-rider race, both riders dope the final ranking remains unchanged compared to a situation without doping; and d/ if one of the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> riders is caught, he will never denounce the other rider for being doped as well. Cycling the latter behaviour is known as omerta or the "law of silence": it is forbidden to openly talk about doping. In such a prisoner"s dilemma, it can be shown that doping is a dominant strategy which means that it is always much more profitable for both riders to dope. The game theoretic literature about doping has also proposed several new anti-doping policy recommendations, all focused on providing riders reduced incentives to use doping. Eber and Thépot (1999) advocate lower spreads between the prizes (which is in conflict with tournament theory), fewer races, improved testing and better prevention.</p>
		<p>Berentsen (2002) suggests a new rank-based sanctioning mechanism.</p>
		<p>However, as long as the wrong incentives are given to riders also these solutions will be of little help in the fight against doping. We therefore suggest a revolutionary anti-doping regulation in cycling where the riders themselves lose interest in the use of doping, or even have an interest not to dope even when other competitors do. This can be realized by the use of appropriate incentives. The suggested scheme below is to some extent in line with Breivik"s (1992) views, and elaborates on the "drug diary system" put forward in Bird and Wagner (1997), and on Andreff (2012). The device would work as follows:</p>
		<p> At the start of the cycling season, all riders (in accordance with their doctors) must register compulsory the list of all doping substances and techniques they plan or, when necessary, want to use over the whole season. Such a doping diary is secret to the other riders. It could, for example, be deposited in the hands of each rider"s lawyer or with the UCI. Riders fully commit themselves to stick to the self-declared list of doping products.  If,during the season, a rider is tested positive for having taken products listed in his diary, no sanction applies.  However, if a rider is tested positive for having taken products not on this list, the sanction is extremely severe, for example a lifetime ban from professional cycling. A severe sanction is needed because not only did the rider use doping, he also cheated and blurred the transparency required for this scheme to be efficient. Because the rider does not want to comply with the rules of the game, he is excluded from professional cycling forever.  If a rider is performing extremely well, other riders who are suspicious (anyone of them, under the precondition that they are at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">two</num></measure>) are allowed to ask the rider (or his lawyer or the UCI) to unveil his doping diary in order to check whether the rider complies with it.  If it appears from (4) that the suspected rider does not comply with his doping diary, just like under (3) he is banned for life from professional cycling.  If it appears from (4) that the suspected rider does comply with his doping diary, the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">two</num></measure> or more claiming riders have to admit that the suspected rider either is definitely stronger than they are during this season or that his doping diary is more efficient or better programmed than their own.</p>
		<p> As a result of this scheme, in particular at the beginning of such a regulation when there may be many claims against successful riders, other riders would have an incentive to copy the unveiled doping diary of the winners. This would trigger <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> beneficial incentives. First, step by step a doping norm (diary) will prevail in the whole peloton, a typical story of social norm formation. All riders will start to use the same most efficient or best conceived doping programme. Second, because of this social norm formation, riders will soon realize that the differential and artificial competitive advantage of hidden doping is limited and short-lived. Third, the omerta system will vanish because the best doping programme will be publicly known to and consequently openly used by all riders once the most performing doping diaries of suspected winners are unveiled.  Once riders are convinced that doping becomes useless as soon as doping substances and techniques are no longer differential between riders, it will not be very difficult to convince them that a same optimal doping recipe does not imply "the more the better".</p>
		<p>Step by step, the optimal doping programme could be downgraded and freed from its most health threatening substances. In the long run, with the riders" consent only the safest stimulating products, necessary in a hard and demanding sport such as cycling, would be maintained in the programme.</p>
		<p>Moreover, such anti-doping regulation features an incentive scheme where each rider is not interested in more and more doping for himself, but instead is interested in benefiting from a competitor"s decision to over-dope beyond his declared programme. To illustrate this point, imagine a <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure>-rider racing circuit that operates under the above regulation. It will produce the following incentive scheme: He can expect a share increase though when competitors over-dope beyond their diary. The outcome is that each rider"s interest is to let the others over-dope and yield a higher share in wins from their exclusion. The incentive scheme is efficient and works in the right direction. Each rider becomes unwilling to over-dope or cheat whatever the others do and benefits in terms of wins from the wrong over-doping strategy possibly adopted by competitors. Doping thus shows a self-defeating strategy and will ultimately be rejected by most riders.</p>
		<p>Should one be optimistic about the above-suggested anti-doping regulation? For certain, it must not be considered to be a miracle solution. But the proposal at least focuses on a crucial point that could possibly be elaborated a bit further in forthcoming studies: the incentive scheme must convince riders that as soon as doping diaries are not differential between riders, doping is no longer a strategy that enables them to win more than their natural ability warrants. It may happen that there will be significant transition costs between the current anti-doping system and the one proposed here. In the first periods of the new regulation enforcement, some riders may feel or assume that the best performing doping programme is the most overloaded one. These riders might use substances dangerous to their health or life. If this assumption reveals to be true, they will soon be copied by other riders and lose their temporary comparative advantage. If on the contrary the assumption were to be wrong, or after a temporary increase in the number of sicknesses and deaths in the peloton (a sort of transition crisis between the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> anti-doping systems, the hard price to pay for adopting the second one), all riders would be convinced that the best or optimal doping programme is in no way the most comprehensive or dangerous one in terms. It might be difficult though to convince stakeholders in cycling to enforce such a new regulation. Although riders would probably soon understand the mechanics of the embedded incentive scheme, they might be more concerned about the short-term effects of such a scheme on their health, i.e. when dangerous substances are put on the doping diary list (and subsequently used) by a large number of riders. But significant obstacles might also come from cycling governing bodies such as the UCI, Tour de France organisers ASO, and so on. They might especially fear the transparency about doping practices in the peloton that would result under such a regulation and its impact on the image (and thus the economic value) of cycling. Why not try to convince them as well that the good incentives that the proposed scheme creates are always preferable to the current bad incentives?</p>
		<p>The Tour de France is one of the most popular and attractive sport events in the world. It attracts millions of people along the roads and reaches a global TV audience. This results from its nice design and appropriate management, the fact it is a product that is supplied for free, an acceptable fitness with the prerequisites of tournament theory, and a modern model of finance linking its sporting success with TV rights revenues. However, the Tour success story is not decisively associated with an excellent competitive balance. A new metrics of the latter, adapted to the team sport dimension of cycling, exhibits that each Tour de France is basically imbalanced while its dynamic competitive balance over the years is much better. Already for a long time but especially since <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1998">1998</date></measure> does the Tour de France has to deal with doping scandals and rider disqualifications, although so far this did not harm spectator and TV viewership interest for the Tour. However, the long term credibility of the Tour is still at stake. From this point of view, an innovative, more efficient and perhaps controversial antidoping regulation including incentives not to dope is developed here.</p>
	</text>
</tei>