<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>The influences of sex and age upon endurance performance have previously been documented for both running and swimming. <!-- cases not supported, atomic values embedded in intervals--><!-- A number of recent studies have investigated how sex and age influence triathlon performance, a sport that combines <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> disciplines (swimming, cycling and running), with competitions commonly lasting between two (Short distance : <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run) and <measure type="value"><num>eight</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure> (Ironman distance: <measure type="value"><num>3.8</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>180</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>42</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run) for elite triathletes.  -->Age and sex influences upon performance have also been investigated for ultra-triathlons with distances corresponding to several Ironman distances and lasting <measure type="value"><num>several</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure>, and for off-road triathlons combining swimming, mountain biking and trail running. Triathlon represents an intriguing alternative model for analyzing the effects of age and sex upon endurance and ultra-endurance (&gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure>) performance because sex differences and age-related declines in performance can be analyzed in the same persons across the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> separate disciplines. The relative participation of both females and masters athletes (age &gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> old) in triathlon has increased consistently over the past <measure type="value"><num>25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Sex differences in triathlon performance are also known to differ between the modes of locomotion adopted (swimming, cycling or running) for both elite and non-elite triathletes. Generally, time differences between sexes in swimming have been shown to be smaller on average than during cycling and running. Both physiological and morphological factors contribute to explaining these findings. Performance density (i.e. the time difference between the winner and 10 th placed competitor) has progressively improved (time differences have decreased) for international races over the past <measure type="value"><num>two</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> for both males and females, with performance density now very similar for both sexes. For age-group triathletes, sex differences in total triathlon performance time increases with age. The possible difference in age-related changes in the physiological determinants of endurance and ultra-endurance performances between males and females needs further investigation however. Non</p>
		<p>Triathlon is a unique endurance sport that combines <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> disciplines (swimming, cycling and running) over a variety of distances. <!-- [1] --> Triathlon first appeared at the end of <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1970" to-iso="1979">1970"s</date></measure> and in only <measure type="value"><num>one-quarter</num> of a <measure type="TIME">century</measure></measure> has developed into a well-organized sport with global participation.</p>
		<p>The first Hawaii Ironman triathlon consisting of a <measure type="value"><num>3.8</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>180</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>42</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run had <measure type="value"><num>12</num></measure> male participants in <measure type="value"><date when="1978">1978</date></measure>. Currently, more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1700">1700</num></measure> triathletes <!-- encoding problem --><!-- (30% females) -->, most of whom have to qualify at <measure type="value"><num>one of 25</num></measure> Ironman triathlons worldwide, participate in this event which has become the Ironman World Championship. <!-- [2] --> Short or Olympic distance triathlons (<measure type="value"><num>1.5</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>40</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run) have also rapidly grown in popularity during approximately the same period with the first World Championship being held in Avignon (France) in <measure type="value"><date when="1989">1989</date></measure>. Triathlon was officially accepted into the Olympic games as a full sport in Sydney in <measure type="value"><date when="2000">2000</date></measure>. <!-- [3] --> Ultra-triathlons, consisting of distances greater than Ironman distance include double Ironman triathlons (<measure type="value"><num>7.6</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>360</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>84</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run) and decaIronman triathlon (<measure type="value"><num>38</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim, <measure type="value"><num>1800</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycle and <measure type="value"><num>420</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run) also appeared during the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980" to-iso="1989">1980"s</date></measure> with the first double Ironman triathlon held in <measure type="value"><date when="1985">1985</date></measure> in Huntsville (USA). <!-- [4,5,6,7] --> More recently, in addition to conventional road based triathlon, off-road triathlon combining swimming, mountain biking and trail running has also established itself in the field of endurance sports, and has grown very rapidly in popularity. <!-- [8,9] --> Triathlon performance has been studied from numerous perspectives by a number of research groups over approximately the same period that the sport has grown. Research has investigated physiological <!-- [1,,,,,14] --> , biomechanical <!-- [15,16,17] --> , training <!-- [16,,101112131819,20] --> , nutritional <!-- [21] --> or medical <!-- [22] --> aspects of triathlon performance. Although Ironman triathlon is a relatively new ultra-endurance event, recently elite Ironman triathletes appear to have reached their performance limits <!-- [2,23] --> as has been observed in more traditional sports such as marathon running where performance times have plateaued. <!-- [24,25] --> With the increase in popularity of endurance sports worldwide, endurance sports have attract a greater participation of female and masters athletes (age &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) during recent times. <!-- [24,25,26,27] --> This review addresses the specific aspects of: i) sex differences and ii) age-related declines in triathlon performance. Sex differences in performance will be presented and discussed for each of the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> disciplines and total event times for different distances and for both elite and age group triathletes. Age-related declines will be outlined by focusing on the performances of the best master triathletes because these athletes represent a unique model for studying the effects of high levels of physical training in persons of older age.</p>
		<p>Independent of age, the number of females competing in triathlon has increased progressively since the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1980" to-iso="1989">1980"s</date></measure>. For example, between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2000">2000</date> and <date to-iso="2011">2011</date></measure>, female USA Triathlon membership has grown from <measure type="value"><num>27</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total number of annual members to more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="38">38</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. <!-- [28] --> Factors leading to this growth include society"s increasing acceptance of "active" females; females feeling more comfortable living an active lifestyle <!-- [29] --> , and the growth of females-only events, good examples of which are the "Danskin" and "Trek Triathlon" Series in USA.</p>
		<p>The rates of female participation appear to decrease with an increase in distance of triathlon races. For example, in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure> females accounted for <measure type="list"><num>26</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>19</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>13</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of athletes competing at short, half-Ironman and full-Ironman distance triathlons held in the region of Zurich (Switzerland) <!-- [30,31,32] --> . However, for ultra-triathlons, female participation remains relatively low, representing generally less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of overall participant numbers. <!-- [4,5,33] --> The number of females finishing the Hawaii Ironman World Championship increased from <measure type="value"><num>20</num> in <measure type="value"><date when="1981">1981</date></measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of participants) to more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="470">470</num></measure> in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>27</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of participants). <!-- [34] --> In Europe, there was also a progressive rise in the number of female Ironman finishers but overall rates were lower. In <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure>, females accounted for <measure type="value"><num>13</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the field at Ironman Switzerland. <!-- [32] --> Lower rates of female participation in Europe may because European Ironman triathlon is relatively younger compared to the Hawaii Ironman triathlon. Indeed, the first Hawaii Ironman was held in <measure type="value"><date when="1978">1978</date></measure>, while one the first European Ironman, Ironman Switzerland, was held in <measure type="value"><date when="1995">1995</date></measure>. Female participation in Ironman triathlon remains slightly lower compared to traditional endurance events such as marathon running, but greater than ultra-endurance events such as a <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultramarathon. For example, Lepers &amp; Cattagni <!-- [24] --> showed that the relative participation of females at the New-York City Marathon increased over the last <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> from <measure type="value"><num>17</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>33</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the total field. In contrast, females accounted for <measure type="value"><num>20</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the finishers in the same time period at <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultramarathons in North America. <!-- [35] --></p>
		<p>Physiological and morphological characteristics may account for the sex differences seen in triathlon performance. <!-- case not supported: interval in interval--><!-- Until the 1970"s, data was scarce with regard to the physiological determinants of female in endurance sports.  -->Even though there is a lesser amount of data for females compared to males, studies have shown that maximal oxygen uptake ( V  O 2max ), lactate threshold and running economy interact similarly in females as determinants of endurance performance as they do in males. <!-- [36] --> Current explanations for sex differences in V  O 2max among elite athletes, when expressed relative to body mass, provide <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> major findings. <!-- [37,38] --> First, elite females have more <!-- encoding problem--><!-- (13% vs. 5%) --> body fat than males. <!-- [39] --> Indeed, much of the difference in V  O 2max between males and females disappears when it is expressed relative to lean body mass. <!-- [37,38] --> Second, the hemoglobin concentration of elite athletes is <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num>-<num atMost="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> lower in females than in males. <!-- [40] --> Concerning lactate threshold, there is no reason to believe that values should be lower in females than in males because mitochondrial adaptations in the skeletal muscles of highly-trained male and female athletes appear to be similar. <!-- [41] --> Finally, the average oxygen cost to run a given speed, (i.e. running economy) by groups of elite male and female athletes is similar and appears to play the same role in determining success in endurance performance. <!-- [42] --> Therefore, the major physiological reason that explains the slower record performances by females compared to males is probably the lower V  O 2max values observed in females.</p>
		<p>Physiological differences between male and female triathletes have been infrequently investigated. <!-- [14,39,43] --> The differences in the physiological responses in cycling and the energy cost of running after cycling have been compared in males and females for both elite junior and senior triathletes. <!-- [14] --> These authors showed that senior females had a significantly higher cycling peak power output than their junior counterparts. Additionally, senior males had a higher ventilatory threshold than junior males whereas the ventilatory threshold was similar in junior and senior females.</p>
		<p>A recent study conducted on junior triathletes has suggested that morphological characteristics of triathletes have evolved since late <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1990" to-iso="1999">1990"s</date></measure>. <!-- [44] --> In <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure>, both male and female junior elite triathletes appeared more ectomorphic than their <measure type="value"><date when="1997">1997</date></measure> counterparts.</p>
		<p>Nowadays, junior triathletes are proportionally lighter, with significantly smaller flexed arm and thigh girths, and femur breadths. The junior males in <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure> also had significantly longer segmental lengths and lower endomorphic values than their <measure type="value"><date when="1997">1997</date></measure> counterparts.</p>
		<p>More research is required however, to validate these findings for senior triathletes.</p>
		<p>Male triathletes possess a larger muscle mass, greater muscular strength and lower relative body fat compared to female triathletes. <!-- [45] --> Low body fat is an important predictor variable for total time performance in triathlon. For example, Knechtle et al. <!-- [46] --> showed that low body fat was associated with faster race times in male Ironman triathletes but not in females. Males possess on average <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="7">7</num>-<num atMost="9">9</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> less percent body fat than females, which is likely an advantage for males. Therefore, it appears that sex differences in percentage body fat, oxygen carrying capacity and muscle mass may be major factors for sex differences in overall triathlon performance. Menstrual cycle, and possibly pregnancy, may also impact training and racing in female athletes, factors that do not affect males. <!-- [47] --></p>
		<p>Sex differences in endurance and ultra-endurance (&gt; <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">6</num><measure type="TIME" unit="h">h</measure></measure>) <!-- [48] --> performance have received considerable attention over the past <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>, but the majority of studies have focused on running performances. <!-- [49,50] --> Interestingly, Speechly et al. <!-- [51] --> reported that females, who were matched with males for a <measure type="value"><num>42</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> run, were faster than males in a <measure type="value"><num>90</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> race. Similarly, it has been shown that females and males who were matched for <measure type="value"><num>50</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> trail running performance also performed similarly in trail runs of <measure type="list"><num>80</num>-and <num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> distances. <!-- [52] --> Despite the suggestion in <measure type="value"><date when="1992">1992</date></measure> that females may one day outrun males in competitive ultra-endurance events <!-- [53] --> , elite males appear to run approximately <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>-<num atMost="12">12</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> faster than elite females across all endurance running race distances up to marathon, with the sex difference narrowing as the race distance increases. <!-- [49,50] --> However, at distances greater than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="100">100</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>, such as the <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultramarathon, the difference seems even larger, with females <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num>-<num atMost="30">30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> slower than males. <!-- [49,54,55] --> Insert TABLE 1</p>
		<p>Sex differences in triathlon performance have previously been described for elite triathletes <!-- [2,9,,56,57] --> and for non-elite triathletes of different age groups <!-- [30,34,58] --> for long distances (distances greater or equal to <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure>-Ironman) <!-- [2,,,56,57] --> and for off-road triathlon <!-- [9] --> . Surprisingly, very little data is available for short distance triathlons especially for high-level international races. <measure type="value"><num>One</num></measure> reason may be that the top international short distance triathlons, (i.e. World Championship Series events or Olympics) have all been draft legal for <measure type="value"><num>several</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> and therefore it is difficult to find a reference of high level Olympic distance triathlon without drafting for comparison. The increase in nondrafting international distance triathlons such the Hy-Vee triathlon that offers significant prize money <!-- ocr problem? it should be 151,000--><!-- of $151,<measure type="list"><num>31</num><num>31</num><num>34</num><num>000</num></measure> USD  -->for both male and female winners and represents a highly competitive platform for professional triathletes should help to better determine sex differences in short distance triathlon performance when athletes compete on a level (non-drafting) playing field in the future. Table 2 presents the most recent data for sex differences in triathlon performance for international elite triathletes participating in the most competitive races at each triathlon distance. By <measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure>, values narrowed so much that, for the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> triathletes overall in <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> top level international road-based triathlon races, the difference between males and females was <measure type="value"><num>11.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the Hawaii Ironman triathlon, <measure type="value"><num>14.1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the Olympics and <measure type="value"><num>9.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the Hy-Vee short distance triathlon (see Table 2). Non road-based triathlon produced a greater sex difference (discussed in more detail below). Interestingly, for ultra-triathlons, it has been shown that with increasing length of the event, the best females became relatively slower compared to the best males. <!-- [4] --> Indeed, if the world"s best performances are considered, males were <measure type="value"><num>19</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> faster than the females in both Double and</p>
		<p>Triple Ironman distance, and <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> faster in the Deca-Ironman distance. <!-- [4] --> However, nonphysiological factors may have contributed to these observations, in particular a fewer overall number of female finishers in ultra-triathlons, compared to formats of more standard length. <!-- [4] --> 2.4 Sex differences in triathlon swimming performance</p>
		<p>The average sex difference in swimming performance during triathlon for race distances between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.5">1.5</num> and <num atMost="3.8">3.8</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ranged between approximately <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for elite triathletes (see Table 1). The sex difference in triathlon swimming performance is consistent with values found for different pool swimming events. It has been shown that sex differences in pool swimming performances become progressively smaller with increasing distance from<!-- case not supported: atomic values embedded in an interval--><!--  <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>19</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) to 1500 m (<measure type="value"><num>11</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) -->. <!-- [59] --> This seems also to be the case for triathlon as Table 1 shows that, the longer the distance of the swim component of a triathlon race, the smaller the sex difference, particularly when the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> age group athlete performances are considered. In ultra-endurance outdoor swimming events, female swimmers have tended to reduce the gap with their male counterparts. For example, time differences between male and female swimming records are <measure type="value"><num>6.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the <measure type="value"><num>32</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> "English Channel Swim" and <measure type="value"><num>2.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the <measure type="value"><num>26</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> "Marathon Swim in Lake of</p>
		<p>Zurich" in Switzerland, respectively. <!-- [60,61] --> However, the sex difference in performance between the best male and female ultra-swimmers is more generally close to <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="11">11</num>-<num atMost="12">12</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, which corresponds to values observed for swimming in triathlon. <!-- [60,61,62] --> It has been shown that the elite male and female triathletes completed the <measure type="value"><num>3.8</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swim stage of the Hawaii Ironman triathlon ~ <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> slower than the elite swimmer specialists for the same distance at the Waikiki Roughwater Swim race. <!-- [2] --> This difference could be explained by better propelling efficiency in elite swimmers compared with elite triathletes. <!-- [63] --> Analysis from <measure type="value"><date when="2005">2005</date></measure> showed that the sex difference in triathlon swimming appears lower than in cycling and running at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon and at the off-road triathlon Xterra World Championship. <!-- [2,9,34] --> The difference between swimming and the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> other disciplines could be explained in part by the biological difference in relative body fat (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="7">7</num>-<num atMost="9">9</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> higher in females). <!-- [64,65] --> Performance in activities that involve supporting ones weight, for example running, may be more susceptible to a greater body fat percentage compared to water-based events such as swimming, during which body fat can increase buoyancy and therefore improve performance. <!-- [65] --> Buoyancy is also improved in females through a lower "underwater torque", which can be defined loosely as the tendency for the feet to sink. <!-- [66] --> In addition, in contrast to running where the energy cost appears to be similar between females and males, the energy cost of freestyle swimming has been shown to be significantly higher (i.e. lower economy) in males compared to females. <!-- [66,67] --> At a velocity of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">m/s</measure></measure>, there are differences in drag force and coefficient of drag between males and females. <!-- [68] --> The energy cost of swimming depends essentially on the propelling efficiency of the arm stroke and hydrodynamic resistance, but it has been suggested that differences in energy costs of swimming between sexes are mainly to be attributed to differences in hydrodynamic resistance. <!-- [69] --> In contrast, differences in energy cost of swimming across ages may be attributed also to changes in the propelling efficiency of the arm stroke. <!-- [69] --> Females have smaller body size (resulting in smaller body drag), smaller body density (greater fat percent) and shorter lower limbs, resulting in a more horizontal and streamlined position and therefore a smaller underwater torque. <!-- [64,66] --></p>
		<p>Sex differences in triathlon cycling vary from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="12">12</num> to <num atMost="16">16</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> according to the level of expertise of participating triathletes for road-based triathlons (Table 1). Data gained from analysing male and female participants" performances in the <measure type="value"><num>180</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycling leg of an</p>
		<p>Ironman triathlon are unique datasets as official time-trial road-cycling championships generally take place on distances much shorter than <measure type="value"><num>180</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure><!-- encoding problem --><!-- , with distances also being greater for males (40 <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) than for females (25 <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) -->. Moreover, there is a paucity of data concerning sex differences in road or track cycling performance. <!-- [70,71,72] --> In track cycling, where females are generally weaker than males in terms of power/weight ratios, the performance gap between males and females appears to be constant <!-- encoding problem --><!-- (<measure type="value"><num>11</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>)  -->and independent of the race distance from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="200">200</num> to <num atMost="1000">1000</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure>. <!-- [70] --> In ultra-cycling events, such as the "Race Across America", sex difference in performance was around <measure type="value"><num>15</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> among top competitors. <!-- [71] --> Greater muscle mass and aerobic capacity in males, even expressed relative to the lean body mass <!-- [73] --> , may represent an advantage during long distance cycling, especially on a relative flat course such as Ironman cycling where cycling approximates to a non-weight-bearing sport. Indeed, it has been shown that absolute power output (which is greater for males than for females) is associated with successful cycling endurance performance because the primary force inhibiting forward motion on a flat course is air resistance. <!-- [74] --> Interestingly, for elite triathletes the sex difference in mountain bike cycling during off-road triathlon <!-- encoding problem --><!-- (20%) --> is greater compared to cycling sex differences in conventional roadbased events. <!-- [9] --> Mountain biking differs in many ways from road cycling. Factors other than aerobic power and capacity such as off-road cycling economy, anaerobic power and capacity, and technical ability might influence off-road cycling performance. <!-- [75] --> Bouts of high intensity exercise frequently encountered during the mountain biking leg of off-road triathlon <!-- encoding problem --><!-- (lasting  <measure type="value"><num>1h 30</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> for elite males and 2h for elite females) --> can result from: 1) having to overcome the constraints of gravity associated with steep climbs, 2) variable terrain necessitating wider tires and thus greater rolling resistance, and 3) isometric muscle contractions associated with the needs of more skilled bike handling skills, not so often encountered in road cycling. In particular however, lower power-to-weight ratios for females compared to male triathletes inevitably leave them at a disadvantage during steep climbs. <!-- [76,77] --> Moreover, the increased bike handling skills, required especially during downhill mountain biking may be impaired by relatively lower female arm or leg isometric muscle strength, meaning that greater sex differences in off-road triathlon could be attributed to decreased ability to control the bicycle in females. However, this assumption needs to be confirmed with specific investigations of the effect of sex on technical ability in mountain biking. <!-- [9] --> As percentage differences in time do not equate to percent differences in power output, due to non-linear relationships between speed and power output from air or water resistance <!-- [78] --> , the magnitude of the sex difference has also been examined by calculating the percentage difference between males and females in estimated power outputs for each discipline. <!-- [2,9,34,79] --> In this case, differences in estimated power output between the sexes are greater for triathlon cycling than for the swimming and running disciplines. For example, sex differences in power output in swimming, cycling and running were estimated to be <measure type="list"><num>28</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>39</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>33</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, respectively for Ironman triathlon, and <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>, <num>45</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num>33</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for off-road triathlon. <!-- [9] --> Because power output is proportional to oxygen uptake, the magnitude of sex differences in power output provides a more realistic representation of underlying sex differences in physiological capacity. <!-- [80] --> 2.6 Sex differences in triathlon running performance</p>
		<p>During the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1988">1988</date>-<date to-iso="2007">2007</date></measure> period, the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> elite males have run the Hawaii Ironman marathon on average <measure type="value"><num>13.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> faster than the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> females. <!-- [2] --> In contrast, during the same period, elite female triathletes have improved their marathon running times by <measure type="value"><num>0.8</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>/yr while times have remained stable for the males. While these improvements in female performances compared to males are impressive, they remain as yet unexplained, which is strange when it is considered that females have benefited from similar training and nutritional advances. <!-- [21] --> If females continue to improve their running performance at Ironman, they could reduce the sex difference in the marathon leg and therefore their overall performance times.</p>
		<p>For example, at the <measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure> Hawaii Ironman, the difference in marathon times between the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> elite males and the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> elite females reduced to <measure type="value"><num>7.3</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> <!-- encoding problem --><!-- (males: 3h <measure type="value"><num>05</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>, females: 3h Table 2) -->. Another notable example is that the female winner of the famous Roth</p>
		<p>Ironman (Germany) in <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure> ran only <measure type="value"><num>2.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> slower than the winning male <!-- case not supported --><!-- (<measure type="value"><num>2h 44</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> vs. <measure type="value"><num>2h 40</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) -->. At the same race, both female and male winners bettered the Ironman distance performance world record <!-- case not supported --><!-- (<measure type="value"><num>8h 18</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> vs. <measure type="value"><num>7h 41</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) -->. <!-- [81] --> Thus, it appears that the marathon running leg of Ironman triathlon has become the discipline in which female elite triathletes have most reduced the gap with their male counterparts. Interestingly, Lepers <!-- [2] --> showed that for the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> elite finishers the sex difference in running at the Hawaii Ironman marathon was similar to that recorded during the New-York marathon, suggesting above all, that the swim and cycle legs of the triathlon do not exacerbate the sex difference in running a marathon. Thus, the physiological differences between males and females in running performance that have been identified to occur in a regular marathon still persist in the marathon of an Ironman.</p>
		<p>Contrary to the knowledge of running performance differences between sexes for the marathon distance, few analyses have been conducted between males and females who have run <measure type="value"><num>10</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> during an Olympic distance triathlon. A mean sex difference of <measure type="value"><num>17</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> was found for the Zurich Switzerland Olympic distance triathlon during the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2000">2000</date>-<date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> period. <!-- [30] --> However, as Table 2 shows, when data from <measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure> only is considered, there is a considerable difference even within elite level Olympic distance run performances, between males and females. A difference of <measure type="value"><num>12.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> existed during the draft-legal Olympic short distance race in London, whereas the difference was lower (<measure type="value"><num>8.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) at the Hy-Vee international triathlon in Des Moines (draft-free). It would appear that the format of the triathlon (drafting or not) affects males differently to females, with the possibility that males benefit in terms of their subsequent running performance off the bike, to a greater extent when riding in a peloton. However, running performances in males and females need to be more closely analyzed in relation to the effort produced during the cycle leg of an Olympic distance triathlon.</p>
		<p>Performance density (i.e. the time difference between the winner and 10 th placed competitor) has been quantified by considering overall performance times in triathlon. <!-- [2] --> For example, at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1981">1981</date> and <date to-iso="2008">2008</date></measure>, the average time difference between 1st and 10 th place was smaller for male (<measure type="value"><num>5.8</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) than for female athletes (<measure type="value"><num>7.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). <!-- [2] --> During the past <measure type="value"><num>five</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, the performance density has decreased <!-- encoding problem --><!-- for both male (3.<measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) and female athletes (5.<measure type="value"><num>7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) -->, a trend which would suggest that in the future, high performing female athletes may be as performance dense as the males. In fact, Table 2 indicates that in <measure type="interval"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure> performance density was similar across the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> sexes for top international road-based triathlon events, regardless of format (Hawaii, Olympics and Hy-Vee). A notable exception to this was the Xterra World Championships (off-road triathlon) in which female performance density (<measure type="value"><num>12.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) was considerably lower than the male performance density (<measure type="value"><num>4.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>). As explained earlier (section 2.5), this can likely be explained by the specific physiological and technical abilities needed for the mountain bike leg of Xterra, in particular explosive strength which favours males over females. <!-- [82] --> The small performance density observed for the London Olympics compared to other events, for both males and females, may be explained by the drafting component of the cycling leg that led to a grouped start of a number of athletes (approximately <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> of the field) at the beginning of the run leg. It must also be considered that a number of nations fielded &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">1</num></measure> athlete, and identified a designated leader who was "protected" during the swim/cycle legs. This would also have led to a higher overall athlete density in terms of overall performance times in both males and females.</p>
		<p>Physiological, (e.g. lower muscle strength and oxygen carrying capacity), morphological, (e.g. greater percentage of body fat, lower muscle mass), and functional capacities are well known to change with advancing age in both males and females. <!-- [83] --> In addition, is has been shown that, after <measure type="value"><num>55</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of age, the decline in endurance performance is more pronounced in females than in males. [ years. <!-- [30] --> The occurrence of this large sex difference was somewhat earlier with respect to athletes" age than recorded during the Hawaii Ironman triathlon. <!-- [34] --> Possible explanations for this include the greater competitive level of older participants at the Hawaii Ironman triathlon because athletes are required to qualify as it is a World Championship event.</p>
		<p>There is a need for further research to understand if exercise duration exerts an influence upon sex differences across older age groups by analysing performances of athletes in a wider range of triathlon events, from Sprint distance, through Olympic distance and Halfironman, to Ironman distances. <!-- [79] --> The exact reasons for these sex-related differences with advancing age are currently not clear but may result from physiological, sociological and psychological changes. <!-- [38,86,87] --> For example, a greater decline of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> or more physiological determinants of endurance performance for females compared to males, (e.g. V  O 2max , lactate threshold, or exercise economy), or a difference in age-related changes in body composition (increase in percentage body fat and loss of muscular mass), hormonal changes, and fluid balance changes (e.g. decline in the thirst mechanism), could affect triathlon performance. <!-- [38,83,84,88] --> In addition, differences in terms of years of training, training volume and intensity between elderly male and female triathletes performing Ironman triathlon may exist, but further research is needed to clarify this. However <!-- [34] --> This participation difference may diminish over the next couple of decades as has been observed in marathon running <!-- [24,26] --> , such that because the welltrained females move up to the older age groups, the improvement of the oldest females may actually surpass the oldest males.</p>
		<p>Age-related declines in endurance and ultra-endurance performance have been well described in the literature for running <!-- [24,,,,,,,91] --> , cycling <!-- [92,,,95] --> , swimming <!-- [83,85] --> and more recently, for triathlon. <!-- [34,,,3538548389909394799296,97,98] --> <!-- case not supported: intervals embedded in intervals --><!-- Endurance and ultra-endurance performance appears to be maintained until approximately <measure type="value"><num>35-40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of age, followed by modest decreases until <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> of age and a progressive decrease in performance thereafter. --> <!-- [83,84,88] --> The greatest declines in endurance and triathlon performance occur after the age of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="70">70</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (Table 3).</p>
		<p>Physiological factors contribute to age-related declines in endurance performance in older athletes and there is obviously an interaction between training behaviour and performance in older athletes. <!-- [38,83,86,88] --> It has been found that the age of peak performance in Ironman triathlon is around <measure type="value"><num>33</num></measure>-overall performance of marathoners. <!-- [99] --> However, this finding observed for the Ironman Switzerland triathlon needs be confirmed for other Ironman events. For non-elite triathletes, the fastest race times are usually achieved between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="25">25</num> and <num atMost="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for both Ironman and Ultra-triathlons. <!-- [32,57,97] --></p>
		<p>Total triathlon performance decreases progressively in a curvilinear manner with advancing age. However, there is a smaller age-related decline in cycling performance compared to running and swimming performances for both short and long distance triathlons. <!-- [8,96,97] --> These findings suggest that age-related declines in endurance performance are specific to the mode of locomotion, although the cause for such modespecificity is not clear. Where does the focus of this locomotor mode-specificity with age lie? Our group has previously proposed that mechanical power could explain these agerelated differences in cycling and running. <!-- [98] --> According to the formula P = k.V (k: constant), mechanical power output (P) is dependent upon velocity (V) during running, whereas it is dependent upon the third power of velocity during cycling (P = k.V 3 ).</p>
		<p>Following this, we previously suggested that as changes in aerobic capacity with age are tied to reductions in P, those reductions during running and cycling with age would give rise to lower cycling velocities than running velocities. <!-- [98] --> A number of explanations can be given to explain the smaller decline in cycling performance during triathlon compared to the declines in the other <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> disciplines. These include a lesser reduction in lactate threshold or economy during cycling, or a greater muscular fatigue during running with age, although these propositions remain to be validated. Some authors have though, attempted to explain this age-related phenomenon in cycling by proposing that the "training stimulus", the ability or will to train, is reduced in running compared to cycling. <!-- [85] --> In particular, this may be because running is associated with a greater amount of orthopedic injuries, which limits the ability to train in running. <!-- [100] --> The training stimulus would therefore be maintained in cycling due to the less traumatic nature of the endurance activity and therefore with age, triathletes would tend to cycle more than run.</p>
		<p>However, this proposition remains speculative and requires further investigation.</p>
		<p>The duration of a triathlon race exerts an important influence on the age-related changes in triathlon performance. <!-- [98] --> Age-related declines in swimming performance are not influenced by triathlon duration with the magnitudes of decreases in swimming performance similar for Olympic distance versus Ironman triathlon. However, in contrast to swimming the magnitude of the declines in cycling and running performances with advancing age during</p>
		<p>Olympic distance triathlon were less pronounced than during Ironman. <!-- [98] --> For age group competitors of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="70">70</num>-<num atMost="74">74</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure>, total finishing time is approximately <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure> for the Olympic distance triathlon whereas it is around <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hours</measure></measure> for an Ironman (Table 3). Certainly the Ironman triathlon induces greater neuromuscular fatigue in cycling and running compared to the Olympic distance event. <!-- [101] --> Furthermore, muscle damage during a <measure type="value"><num>10</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">k</measure></measure> run of the Olympic distance triathlon is limited compared to that which occurs during an Ironman marathon. Greater muscle fatigability and greater sensibility to muscle damage of older triathletes needs further investigation to determine if these factors underlie the greater declines in cycling and running performance of older triathletes.</p>
		<p>It has recently been shown that the rate of the decline in performance for off-road triathlon is greater than for road-based triathlon. <!-- [8] --> This suggests that the type of discipline (road versus mountain bike cycling and road versus trail running) exerts an important influence on the magnitude of the age-associated changes in triathlon performance. <!-- [8] --> The specific aspects of mountain biking and trail running may explain why age-related declines in off-road triathlon are more pronounced for off-road compared to conventional on road triathlon. In particular, a decrease in power-to-weight ratio that has been shown to occur with age <!-- [102,103] --> leaves older athletes with a distinct advantage during steep climbs often encountered in off-road triathlons. Moreover, despite a preservation of muscle strength in comparison to sedentary persons <!-- [104] --> , older athletes may be disadvantaged in their technical bike handling skills due to lower arm/leg muscle strength. Poorer running performances in older athletes, especially when variations in intensity are required, may be explained be a reduced ability to modify the biomechanical components of running (e.g., support phases, stride frequency, changes in stride length, etc.) <!-- [8] --> Insert TABLE 3</p>
		<p>An increase in participation of both male and female athletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> over the past <measure type="value"><num>few</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure> has been reported for marathon and ultra-marathon running, such as <measure type="value"><num>161</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> ultra-marathons and for <measure type="value"><num>100</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running in Switzerland. <!-- [24,25,35,90] --> A relative increase in participation of masters triathletes has also been observed during the past <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME">decade</measure></measure> for short and long distance triathlon, while the participation of triathletes younger than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="40">40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">yrs</measure></measure> of age has decreased. <!-- [27,28,30,58] --> The relative increase in participation of master triathletes at the Ironman distance triathlons has been accompanied by an improvement in their performance. <!-- [27,105] --> We have previously presented data for the <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date>-<date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure> period showing that swimming, cycling, running and total time performances at the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon improved for male triathletes older than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> age and female triathletes older than <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> age. <!-- [27] --> <!-- encoding problem + cases not supported--><!-- During the <measure type="value"><num>25</num></measure>-year study period, the total time decreased by <measure type="value"><num>21</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (from 14h 18min to <measure type="value"><num>11h 16</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) for the best male finishers in the age group 60 to 64 years and by the same percentage (from 14h --></p>
		<p><!-- case not supported --><!-- <measure type="value"><num>38</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>11h 30</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) for the best finishers in the age group <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num> to <num atMost="44">44</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. --> <!-- [27] --> Similar findings have been observed for a Hawaii Ironman qualifying race such as the Switzerland</p>
		<p>Ironman. <!-- [105] --> In Table 3, we show that, when the most recent data (Ironman Hawaii, <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure> and) is added, improvements of older age groups, especially for the males has continued, and for some age groups, is quite startling. For example, the best male finisher in the <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="70">70</num>-<num atMost="74">74</num></measure> age group has bettered the best time set in <measure type="value"><date when="2010">2010</date></measure> <!-- case not supported --><!-- (<measure type="value"><num>12h 41</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) --> by almost <measure type="value"><num>one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="h">hour</measure></measure> <!-- case not supported --><!-- (<measure type="value"><num>11h 45</num><measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) -->.</p>
		<p><!-- case not supported --><!-- Other, more modest improvements have been recorded in the male 65-69 and &gt;80 age groups, and the female 45-49 age group with respect to the 2010 data. --> <!-- [27] --> What is clear however, is that, if the most recent (<measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure>) data is compared to that of <measure type="value"><date when="1986">1986</date></measure>, age groups show improvements of between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="114">114</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num atMost="194">194</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> for the males over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="45">45</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="106">106</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure> and <num atMost="179">179</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure></p>
		<p>for females over <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="45">45</num></measure>, and that these improvements seem to be continuing, most significantly for the oldest athletes.</p>
		<p>Several reasons may explain the improved performance of master triathletes. These include an improvement of training facilities, coaching, training techniques, nutritional strategies and equipment, <!-- [84,86] --> as well as the possibility that they have had better and prolonged access to the facilities required to train effectively. It is also obvious that the higher participation rates of master athletes increases the possibility of them obtaining better results due to the competitive nature of the sport. Additionally, athletes that have attained a number of good results and positive outcomes, have increased levels of motivation to train and compete in endurance events. <!-- [106] --> Accordingly, the better physical condition of older athletes is likely to increase competitive spirit, participation and performance. <!-- [84,86] --> The advancement of training quality is also a possible reason for these improved performance trends. Earlier studies suggested the performance decline with advancing age was due to decreased training volumes and intensity. <!-- [86] --> Other, more sociological, factors may also play a role in reducing the ability and motivation to train. These include greater work demands, demands of the family, a diminished inherent drive to push oneself or even train. <!-- [83,84,86] --> An important factor is also the greater amount of time needed by the body to recover from hard, physical effort resulting from training as humans age. Indeed, training for an Ironman triathlon is very demanding and in order to place in the top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> of an age group category, extremely high training volumes and intensities are required. <!-- [18,,,] --> However, it has been suggested that masters athletes could optimize their quality of training, so they could reduce their training volume to save time for adequate recovery and remain injury free. <!-- [84] --> These studies suggest that masters triathletes have probably not reached their limits in ultra-endurance performance. Unfortunately, no information is available concerning the sporting background of these successful masters triathletes. Nevertheless, even if recreational masters athletes had relatively short training histories and little experience in triathlon, these successful athletes probably have lifelong histories of physical activity. <!-- [110,,107108109111112,113] --></p>
		<p>Sex differences in triathlon performance differ generally between the locomotion modes with lower differences seen in swimming compared to cycling and running for both elite and non-elite triathletes. In elite triathletes, sex differences in performance (~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>-<num atMost="14">14</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) are in agreement with values generally observed in endurance sports. At present, the performance density in highly competitive international triathlon races appears to have become similar between elite male and female triathletes. Marathon running during an</p>
		<p>Ironman triathlon appears to be the discipline where female elite triathletes have reduced the gap with the males to the greatest extent over the recent years. Sex-related differences increase with advancing age most likely due to physiological, sociological and psychological changes. However, these differences should decrease in the future with the increase in participation of elderly female triathletes.</p>
		<p>Age-related declines in triathlon performance depend on the locomotion mode, the exercise duration (short versus long distance triathlon) and the triathlon format (off-road versus road based triathlon). <!-- table --><!-- Hawaii Ironman Triathlon (3.8-180-42 <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) 14.1 ± 7.9 13.1 ± 2.3 7.3 ± 2.9 <measure type="interval"><num type="base">11.3</num> ± <num type="range">0.5</num></measure> <measure type="value"><num>3.6 4.0</num></measure> --></p>
		<!-- table --><!-- <p>Olympics Triathlon (1.5-40-<measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) with drafting 11.8 ± 2.0 11.3 ± 0.6 14.7 ± 0.8 <measure type="interval"><num type="base">14.1</num> ± <num type="range">7.9</num></measure> <measure type="value"><num>1.5 1.4</num></measure></p>
		<p>Hy-Vee Triathlon (1.5-40-<measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) without drafting 8.6 ± 4.8 10.2 ± 3.5 8.6 ± 4.4 <measure type="interval"><num type="base">9.3</num> ± <num type="range">0.5</num></measure> <measure type="value"><num>4.1 3.3</num></measure></p>
		<p>World Championship Off-Road Triathlon (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.5">1.5</num>-<num atMost="30-10">30-10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure>) 15.2 ± 15.5 22.6 ± 4.4 15.1 ± 6.7 <measure type="interval"><num type="base">17.3</num> ± <num type="range">2.9</num></measure> <measure type="value"><num>4.6 12.2</num></measure></p> -->
		<p>Sex difference in performance in top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> athletes in <measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure> (mean ± SD) Difference between 10th and 1st (%) Table 2 Mean percentage differences in times for swimming, cycling, running and total event between the top <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> females and males and time difference between the winner and 10 th placed athlete in <measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure> at <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> international triathlons: Hawaii Ironman triathlon World championship (Kona, Hawaii, USA Table 3 Total time records (actualized with <measure type="value"><date when="2012">2012</date></measure> data) and corresponding split times for male and female age-groups at the Hawaii Ironman Triathlon between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1986">1986</date> and <date to-iso="2012">2012</date></measure>. The change in percentage compared to the fastest total time (age group <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num>-<num atMost="39">39</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>) is given for each different age group.</p>
		<p>This research project was not funded. All authors declare that there were no conflicts of interests.</p>
	</text>
</tei>