<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<p>Comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) will have a <quantifiedObject id="182e73b4-e7fe-4a79-aebd-ccc479866a34">close encounter</quantifiedObject> with Mars on <measure type="value" ptr="#182e73b4-e7fe-4a79-aebd-ccc479866a34">Oc-tober 19, 2014</measure>. We model the dynamical evolution of dust grains from the time of their ejection from the comet nucleus to the Mars close encounter, and determine the flux at Mars. Constraints on the ejection velocity from Hubble Space Telescope observations indicate that the bulk of the grains will likely miss Mars, although it is possible that a <measure type="value" ptr="#f3c19d0c-e29d-41a1-a1ef-d625bea081d9">few-percent</measure> of <quantifiedObject id="f3c19d0c-e29d-41a1-a1ef-d625bea081d9">grains</quantifiedObject> with higher velocities will reach Mars, peaking approximately <measure type="interval" ptr="#f3c19d0c-e29d-41a1-a1ef-d625bea081d9">90-100 minutes</measure> after the close approach of the nucleus, and consisting mostly of millimeter-radius grains ejected from the comet nucleus at a <quantifiedObject id="grains2">heliocentric distance</quantifiedObject> of approximately <measure type="interval" ptr="#grains2">9 AU</measure> or larger. At higher velocities, younger <quantifiedObject id="grains">grains</quantifiedObject> from <measure ptr="#grains" type="interval">sub-millimeter to several millimeter</measure> can reach Mars too, although an even smaller fraction of grains is expected have these velocities, with negligible effect on the peak timing. Using NEOWISE observations of the comet, we can estimate that <quantifiedObject id="55521379-0c7d-4dc5-baec-bda966727d62">the maximum fluence</quantifiedObject> will be of the order of <measure type="value" ptr="#55521379-0c7d-4dc5-baec-bda966727d62">10 −7 grains/m 2</measure>. We include a detailed analysis of how the expected fluence depends on the grain density, ejection velocity, and size-frequency distribution, to account for current model uncertainties and in preparation of possible refined model values in the near future.</p>
	<p>Comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) will have a <quantifiedObject id="d17835b6-d6cb-4773-99fc-9a17f42b3b6e">close approach</quantifiedObject> (hereafter c/a) with Mars on <measure type="value" ptr="#d17835b6-d6cb-4773-99fc-9a17f42b3b6e">October 19, 2014 at approximately 18:29 UT</measure>, reaching a <quantifiedObject id="7f3102f2-d3ae-4ebc-b66f-8fd25f6f90fb">minimum distance</quantifiedObject> of approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#7f3102f2-d3ae-4ebc-b66f-8fd25f6f90fb">134,000 km</measure> from the center of Mars, according to JPL solution #46 ( Farnocchia et al. 2014). This orbital solution was retrieved from the JPL Horizons system ( Giorgini et al. 1996), on <measure type="value">March 17, 2014</measure>, and include all the observations before the low solar elongation period. The comet is on a hyperbolic retrograde orbit (<measure type="value" ptr="#c4593465-1afc-4bf7-8654-98df17f30d3e">129 •</measure> <quantifiedObject id="c4593465-1afc-4bf7-8654-98df17f30d3e">inclination</quantifiedObject>), and the encounter with Mars will be at a <quantifiedObject id="c3ec6a5c-2c92-4a75-bd21-be8e914e136c">relative velocity</quantifiedObject> of approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#c3ec6a5c-2c92-4a75-bd21-be8e914e136c">56 km/s</measure>. Observed from Mars, the comet reaches a <quantifiedObject id="comet3">minimum solar elongation</quantifiedObject> of approximately <measure ptr="#comet3" type="value">72 •</measure> . After the close approach between the <measure type="value" ptr="#67d37a93-0fbb-4d27-bdb7-21002b32123b">two</measure> <quantifiedObject id="67d37a93-0fbb-4d27-bdb7-21002b32123b">bodies</quantifiedObject>, Mars continues to move closer to the orbit of the comet, crossing the comet orbit plane approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#a92b3ef5-69f4-432e-85db-b7ebd8a16d87">100 minutes</measure> after <quantifiedObject id="a92b3ef5-69f4-432e-85db-b7ebd8a16d87">c/a</quantifiedObject> and then reaching a minimum distance of approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#6ceb4ec6-0e0e-40c1-bc0a-a1f11a8d4902">27,000 km</measure> from <quantifiedObject id="6ceb4ec6-0e0e-40c1-bc0a-a1f11a8d4902">the comet orbit</quantifiedObject> approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#f87a3452-9d15-48f8-aa15-5d6bdd209985">102 minutes</measure> after <quantifiedObject id="f87a3452-9d15-48f8-aa15-5d6bdd209985">c/a</quantifiedObject>. A detailed trajectory analysis by Farnocchia et al. (2014) indicates that the current uncertainty on the c/a distance, projected on the target plane normal to the velocity of the comet nucleus relative to Mars, is an <quantifiedObject id="ellipse3">ellipse</quantifiedObject> approximately <measure ptr="#ellipse3" type="value">1600 × 700 km</measure> (1σ) with the long axis <measure type="value" ptr="#8db2d103-6e27-49c7-92aa-b85230d82bb3">20 •</measure> from the line connecting the comet nucleus and Mars, and the <quantifiedObject id="catimeuncertanty3">c/a time uncertainty</quantifiedObject> is about <measure type="value" ptr="#catimeuncertanty3">1 minute</measure> (1σ). These uncertainties exclude any collision of the comet nucleus with Mars, yet warrant a detailed investigation of the possibility that the dust coma of the comet may be able to reach Mars. C/2013 A1 was discovered at a <quantifiedObject id="e2c7f6b9-2ac9-401b-801c-f414ee64f5bd">heliocentric distance</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#e2c7f6b9-2ac9-401b-801c-f414ee64f5bd">7.2 AU</measure> ( McNaught et al. 2013), suggesting hyper-volatile activity (i.e., driven by CO or CO 2 ) was likely causing long-term build-up of larger grains in the coma. Hubble Space Telescope (HST) observations by Li et al. (2014) allow us to estimate the ejection velocity of the dust grains at the µm radius scale, or more precisely grains with <!--CHECK START--><quantifiedObject id="cd886d4f-494b-43bb-833e-16faa3c2d36b">β ≃</quantifiedObject> <measure type="value" ptr="#cd886d4f-494b-43bb-833e-16faa3c2d36b">1</measure>, where β is the ratio between the radiation pressure force and the gravitational force due to the Sun on the grain ( Burns et al. 1979).<!-- CHECK \ --> Observations were performed on <measure type="list">October 29, 2013, on Jan 21, 2014, and on March 11, 2014</measure>. By using a technique based on the sunward turn back distance in the continuum (e.g., Mueller et al. 2013) we determined a velocity approximately between <measure type="interval" ptr="#8253c5a9-6a61-45fd-bc73-d4f8f7d36632">28 and 46 m/s</measure> at a <quantifiedObject id="490dd318-5029-4136-82ea-29737dd1e203">heliocentric distance</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#490dd318-5029-4136-82ea-29737dd1e203">4.59 AU</measure>, then between <measure type="interval">44 and 74 m/s</measure> at <measure type="value">3.77 AU</measure>, and between <measure type="interval">48 and 80 m/s</measure> at <measure type="value">3.28 AU</measure>, all for β = <measure type="value">1</measure> dust grains, see Figure 1. The ranges are relatively broad because of the inherent difficulty of determining a single value for the turn back distance in a continuous brightness distribution.</p>
	<p>NEOWISE obtained <quantifiedObject id="infraredObservations">infrared observations</quantifiedObject> of C/2013 A1 on <measure type="value" ptr="#infraredObservations">Jan 16, 2014</measure>(Mainzer et al. 2014), when the comet was at <measure type="value" ptr="#5b2b9a3b-6f3c-4b46-a78b-d1dc948ed9cd">3.82 AU</measure> from the Sun. We used these observations to model the dust production. Adopting the techniques in Bauer et al. (2011) yields a <quantifiedObject id="4be35fc0-b84c-4eba-81a6-9b7877da74af">dust production rate</quantifiedObject> of approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#4be35fc0-b84c-4eba-81a6-9b7877da74af">10 kg/s</measure> at the grain velocities for that heliocentric distance, and for grains with <quantifiedObject id="92774f43-7589-466d-bb79-3881e6cd8ce7">radius</quantifiedObject> between <measure type="interval" ptr="#92774f43-7589-466d-bb79-3881e6cd8ce7">1.7 µm and 2.3 µm</measure> ( Mainzer et al. 2014).</p>
	<p>In this paper we use the HST and NEOWISE observations to anchor the grain ejection velocity and production rate. Fig. 1.-Ejection velocity of dust grains with β = 1 as a function of the heliocentric distance of the nucleus at the time of the ejection. The curves are not a fit, but correspond to the empirical scaling law of Eq. (1) with <quantifiedObject id="vrefValues">v ref values</quantifiedObject> between <measure ptr="#vrefValues" type="interval">0.5 m/s and 1.5 m/s</measure> in <quantifiedObject id="b96e0c57-ecaa-4caa-a9f3-76846b81a682">increments</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#b96e0c57-ecaa-4caa-a9f3-76846b81a682">0.1 m/s</measure>. The <measure type="value" ptr="#06aa5da4-d7be-42d6-ac05-6d1eb2499397">three</measure> <quantifiedObject id="06aa5da4-d7be-42d6-ac05-6d1eb2499397">vertical bars</quantifiedObject> are the velocity ranges as constrained from HST observations ( Li et al. 2014).  In the next Section we discuss how we use these constraints to model the velocity of larger dust grains ejected at larger heliocentric distances, which are in the relevant range for delivery of dust grains to Mars. In Section 3, we present the results from numerical simulations where we model the dynamical evolution of dust grains after ejection from the comet nucleus to their close approach with Mars. In Section 4 we discuss the consequences of our modeling choices and how they likely affect the outcomes of the simulations, and compare our results with earlier works which characterize the delivery of dust grains to Mars ( Moorhead et al. 2014;Vaubaillon et al. 2014;Ye &amp; Hui 2014). Conclusion are then drawn in Section 5.</p>
    <p>The trajectories of the comet nucleus and of the dust grains are determined numerically by integrating the equations of motion, using an efficient numerical integrator with variable timestep (Everhart 1974), and that includes gravitational perturbations and solar radiation pressure ( Burns et al. 1979). The state vectors of the Sun and the planets are obtained from the DE405 planetary ephemeris (Standish 1998). The initial conditions of the comet nucleus are chosen at the time of the c/a, as retrieved from the Horizons JPL system ( Giorgini et al. 1996), and are then integrated backward in time to the epoch when the comet was at <measure type="value">10 AU</measure>, i.e., the heliocentric distance that we assume as the beginning of the activity of the comet. The <quantifiedObject id="e5b968fe-3c9f-41b6-9e8f-a06c6c5dbc6b">maximum heliocentric distance</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#e5b968fe-3c9f-41b6-9e8f-a06c6c5dbc6b">10 AU</measure> is chosen based on pre-discovery images of the active comet at approximately <measure type="value">8 AU</measure>, and considering that the region of <quantifiedObject id="57372bf6-489d-49e8-954d-71ee21a58b4f">the sky</quantifiedObject> where the comet was between <measure type="interval" ptr="#57372bf6-489d-49e8-954d-71ee21a58b4f">8 and 10 AU</measure> was not covered by surveys (T. Spahr, MPC, priv. comm.). The comet nucleus is considered massless, and grains are assigned a radius and density in order to compute the effects of radiation pressure, and are integrated individually. As a trade-off between simulation performance and accuracy, gravitational interactions are computed only with the Sun, Jupiter, and Mars, and limit the nominal accuracy of the numerical integrator. This causes a significant speed-up of simulations compared to including all planets, and causes a difference in c/a distance of dust grains of <quantifiedObject id="fc14401a-b269-4755-9d80-c9a77c843d03">the order of</quantifiedObject> a <measure type="value" ptr="#fc14401a-b269-4755-9d80-c9a77c843d03">few hundred kilometers</measure>. This is relatively small compared to the <measure type="value">few thousand kilometers</measure> uncertainty on the comet c/a distance, especially considering the statistical nature of this study.</p>
    <p>Dust grains are ejected isotropically from the nucleus, at a velocity that is determined using an empirical scaling law, based on the results in Whipple (1951). This choice is due to the difficulty of developing a detailed self-consistent physical model of grain ejection driven by hyper-volatiles at large heliocentric distances and then water within approximately <measure type="value">3 AU</measure> from the Sun, as such a model would require some mechanisms for the depletion of hyper-volatiles at shorter heliocentric distance, or would otherwise produce unrealistically large ejection velocities. The ejection velocity is:</p>
    <p>where we choose the reference grain to have <quantifiedObject id="6b2f2d4b-ecba-43a8-b1af-1ffeecd3616c">radius</quantifiedObject> r ref = <measure type="value" ptr="#6b2f2d4b-ecba-43a8-b1af-1ffeecd3616c">1 mm</measure> and <quantifiedObject id="density">density</quantifiedObject> ρ ref = <measure type="value" ptr="#density">1 g cm −3</measure> , which correspond to β ref ≃ <measure type="value" ptr="#0e73709c-bf65-47f0-9cf1-c491cdb9597c">5.76 × 10 −4</measure> , and D ref = <measure type="value" ptr="#0e73709c-bf65-47f0-9cf1-c491cdb9597c">5 AU</measure> for <quantifiedObject id="0e73709c-bf65-47f0-9cf1-c491cdb9597c">the heliocentric distance</quantifiedObject>. The value of D ref is chosen to be approximately halfway between the comet activation and the comet close encounter with Mars. Since these reference values are fixed for all simulations, we have v ref as the only free parameter characterizing the ejection velocity of all grains within each simulation. Because of the lack of an estimate of the nucleus size, we consider the ejection velocities defined outside of the gravitational influence region of the nucleus. In Figure 1 we show how the velocities from our modeling compare to the observed HST velocities. The <measure ptr="#observations" type="value">three</measure> HST <quantifiedObject id="observations">observations</quantifiedObject> ( Li et al. 2014) indicate velocities of micron-size grains roughly compatible with <quantifiedObject id="e4ae0df4-69a2-49f8-8a3b-67cb9c664fb6">v ref</quantifiedObject> between <measure type="interval" ptr="#e4ae0df4-69a2-49f8-8a3b-67cb9c664fb6">0.8 and 1.0 m/s</measure>. Because of the significant dispersion in the velocity range, and the limited number of HST observations, we choose not to fit the exponent of the heliocentric distance D in Eq. (1) and instead scale all velocities as D −1 and use different values of v ref to sample different points of the ejection velocity distribution. Values of v ref above the HST range are reasonable if we include a high-velocity tail of the distribution due for example to jets. As such, high v ref values would be representative only of a <measure type="value">few-percent</measure> of the total grains.</p>
    <p>The density of dust grains ejected from comets depends strongly on what they are made up of and the bulk porosity of such dust grains. In the literature we find estimates as low as approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#ed9e9447-3d4c-4edc-977e-66112c4fd80a">0.1 g/cm 3</measure> (Greenberg &amp; Li 1999), and as high as approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#ed9e9447-3d4c-4edc-977e-66112c4fd80a">2 g/cm 3</measure> for <quantifiedObject id="ed9e9447-3d4c-4edc-977e-66112c4fd80a">interplanetary dust particles</quantifiedObject> ( Love et al. 1994), although that may not necessarily be representative of cometary dust. In our simulations we use a <quantifiedObject id="grain_density">grain density</quantifiedObject> of <measure ptr="#grain_density" type="value">1.0 g/cm 3</measure> and provide scaling laws to different densities for all the main results.</p>
    <p>The size-frequency distribution (SFD) and production rate Q of grains are assigned during post-processing of the simulations. First, we used a uniform distribution (in log scale) in <quantifiedObject id="2034ab0e-6c46-48c8-a3fd-f79dcc33ec47">grain radius</quantifiedObject> between <measure type="interval" ptr="#2034ab0e-6c46-48c8-a3fd-f79dcc33ec47">1 µm to 10 cm</measure> during the simulations, and a constant production rate. Then in post-processing each simulated grain is scaled up to represent a far larger number of real grains, according to the specific SFD and Q distributions selected. The SFD is parameterized using the differential distribution dQ/dr ∝ r −a and Q depends on the heliocentric distance as Q ∝ D −2 . The index a for cometary dust grains depends on many factors including the heliocentric distance, the specific comet, and the specific grain sizes under consideration (e.g., Hanner &amp; Bradley 2004;Fulle 2004, and references therein). However, many authors find that adopting a single power law index is convenient for modeling purposes although there are a number of counter examples against this approach (e.g., comet 1P/Halley, comet 2P/Encke). Therefore, as a compromise, we adopt the values of <measure type="list">3.5 and 4</measure> for a, which are representative of many comets based on dust tail modeling (Fulle 2004, and references therein).</p>
    <p>The flux of grains at Mars is determined from simulations after accounting for SFD and Q, by tracking the grains which come within <measure type="interval" ptr="#fcc1e82a-fcba-44e0-b58c-a6bb99a51167">3,400 km</measure> from <quantifiedObject id="fcc1e82a-fcba-44e0-b58c-a6bb99a51167">the center</quantifiedObject> of Mars. For scaling purposes, the grains are binned logarithmically into <measure type="value" ptr="#9f30d51b-d271-44a3-8b41-2c610ad99860">3</measure> <quantifiedObject id="9f30d51b-d271-44a3-8b41-2c610ad99860">intervals</quantifiedObject> per decade in grain radius, and in <quantifiedObject id="linear_intervals">linear intervals</quantifiedObject> of size <measure type="value" ptr="#linear_intervals">0.2 AU</measure> in heliocentric distance. The properties of the grains are assumed to be uniform within each bin.</p>
    <p>We performed several simulations, each one with a different v ref value. In each simulation, we generated <measure type="value" ptr="$grains4">five million</measure> <quantifiedObject id="grains4">grains</quantifiedObject> and tracked their trajectory as described in Section 2. Typically only a <measure type="interval">few hundred to a thousand</measure> simulated grains cross the Mars volume, which we approximate with a <quantifiedObject id="6be78882-aa14-4322-93eb-51824837e3df">sphere</quantifiedObject> of radius <measure type="value" ptr="#6be78882-aa14-4322-93eb-51824837e3df">3,400 km</measure>. In preliminary simulations we used a <quantifiedObject id="grain_radius">grain radius</quantifiedObject> between <measure ptr="#grain_radius" type="interval">10 −6 and 10 −1 meter</measure>, and then reduced this range to <measure type="interval" ptr="grain_radius">10 −4 to 10 −2 meter</measure>, as this is the relevant range for Mars collisions, see Figure 2. Note how the increased velocity of grains causes a wider range in Fig. 2.-Distribution of grain radius and arrival time (in hours) relative to the nucleus close approach time. The displayed values are for grains with <quantifiedObject id="798410ab-edc8-41f5-95a1-927b4c733ff6">density</quantifiedObject> ρ ref = <measure type="value" ptr="#798410ab-edc8-41f5-95a1-927b4c733ff6">1 g cm −3</measure> . For grains with different density ρ, the grain radius distribution will shift vertically by a factor ρ ref /ρ. grain radius to reach Mars, and also how the arrival time window grows accordingly. At the <quantifiedObject id="83eac461-5c62-48f9-84ea-6bd40bcabb1f">highest velocity</quantifiedObject> tested of v ref = <measure type="value" ptr="#83eac461-5c62-48f9-84ea-6bd40bcabb1f">3.0 m/s</measure> we start to see smaller grains arriving at early times, and this effect becomes dominant at higher velocities. The grains have to be ejected at large heliocentric distances to reach Mars: beyond <measure type="interval">9.1 AU</measure> for v ref = <measure type="value">1.5 m/s</measure>, beyond <measure type="interval">6.7 AU</measure> for v ref = <measure type="value">2.0 m/s</measure>, beyond <measure type="interval">4.6 AU</measure> for v ref = <measure type="value">2.5 m/s</measure>, and beyond <measure type="interval">2.4 AU</measure> for v ref = <measure type="value">3.0 m/s</measure>. Therefore, if the comet was not active at heliocentric distance beyond <measure type="interval" ptr="#a2614998-bf95-4ae5-872c-a3b99e5155c4">8 AU</measure> and the maximum v ref was <measure type="value">1.5 m/s</measure>, no grains could reach Mars.</p>
    <p>The arrival time of grains is well concentrated for lower ejection velocities, with the peak of the flux between <measure type="interval" ptr="#166eabdc-22e6-4795-9913-79a384856f1c">90 and 100 minutes</measure> after <quantifiedObject id="166eabdc-22e6-4795-9913-79a384856f1c">the close approach time</quantifiedObject> of the nucleus, see Figure 3. As we increase the grain ejection velocity, the arrival time interval tends to widen, while the peak tends to move to earlier times. At <quantifiedObject id="vref">v ref</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#vref">3.0 m/s</measure> the peak is well below one hour after c/a, and the flux tends to have a fast raise and then a slow <quantifiedObject id="0f7cf4d8-bf7a-4626-9fa8-d51596f9ef0f">decay</quantifiedObject>, over <measure type="value" ptr="#0f7cf4d8-bf7a-4626-9fa8-d51596f9ef0f">one hour</measure> long.</p>
    <p>In Figure 4 we have the integrated fluence (count and mass) versus the grain ejection velocity parameter v ref and at different SFD index values. The figure provides the fluence values for all ejected grains at the given v ref value. However, as we have discussed above, HST observations indicate lower velocities at which no grains intercept Mars. The way to interpret these plots is then to assume that while the v ref parameter from HST indicates the velocity of the bulk of the grains, it is possible that the velocity distribution of grains contains an high-velocity tail, so that only a <measure type="value" ptr="#few-percent123">few-percent</measure> of the <quantifiedObject id="few-percent123">grains</quantifiedObject> will have these higher velocities. Processes responsible for this could be the presence of jets, or the shape of the nucleus causing non-uniformities in the gas flow and in the acceleration of grains from the surface. In view of this interpretation, the fluence values in Figure 4 should be decreased by several orders of magnitude as we move to higher values of v ref , to reflect the smaller and smaller fraction of grains which could be in the high-velocity tail. As a result, the <quantifiedObject id="b890e681-8489-4a62-865e-c461900732be">fluence</quantifiedObject> decreases by approximately <measure type="value" ptr="#b890e681-8489-4a62-865e-c461900732be">two</measure> orders of magnitude at <quantifiedObject id="358e8a15-c3a2-43e5-a98e-6c807dbf356c">v ref</quantifiedObject> ≃ <measure type="value" ptr="#358e8a15-c3a2-43e5-a98e-6c807dbf356c">1.5 m/s</measure> and by several orders of magnitude at higher v ref values, to obtain a maximum <quantifiedObject id="a5807d26-6feb-46ba-97b2-04c8114c1025">fluence</quantifiedObject> of the order of <measure type="value" ptr="#a5807d26-6feb-46ba-97b2-04c8114c1025">10 −7 grains/m 2</measure> .</p>
    <p><quantifiedObject id="29f29090-db9f-4e16-8ff8-5e566ea8c6a4">The radiant of the dust grains</quantifiedObject> is at R.A. <measure type="value" ptr="#29f29090-db9f-4e16-8ff8-5e566ea8c6a4">41.1 •</measure> and Dec. <measure type="value">−15.5 •</measure> in the constellation Cetus. In Figure 5 we show the hemisphere of Mars that is exposed to dust grains. Depending on the velocity of the grains, <measure type="value" ptr="#8080d728-3a4a-4aaa-b25f-08ae7bc7c6c3">one</measure> <quantifiedObject id="8080d728-3a4a-4aaa-b25f-08ae7bc7c6c3">side of Mars</quantifiedObject> is accessible at lower velocities than the other one. Thus, it is reasonable to expect that the flux of grains in the low-v ref side will be somewhat higher than on the opposite side.</p>
    <p>The results presented here can be compared with previous works already in the literature. In Moorhead et al. (2014) the dust grains fluence is determined using both analytical and numerical approaches, obtaining a <quantifiedObject id="fluence234">count fluence</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#fluence234">0.15 m −2</measure> . In their model, the comet orbit solution was not yet as constrained as ours, the grain densities used (<measure type="value">0.1 g/cm 3</measure> ) are relatively low, and the ejection velocities appear significantly higher than what we used. We find that the modeling details and parameters in Moorhead et al. (2014) are not supported by observations such as we used in our work, and the large difference in fluence is a direct consequence of very different models.</p>
    <p>In Vaubaillon et al. (2014), <measure type="value" ptr="#6afc93cf-877c-47e8-b973-5c760bb3f1ae">two</measure> <quantifiedObject id="6afc93cf-877c-47e8-b973-5c760bb3f1ae">different numerical approaches</quantifiedObject> are used to obtain a <quantifiedObject id="fluence2345">count fluence</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#fluence2345">3.5 m −2</measure> , with grains reaching Mars over a <measure type="value" ptr="#a504de05-b2c9-43a5-8267-9131260a2d3e">five hours</measure> <quantifiedObject id="a504de05-b2c9-43a5-8267-9131260a2d3e">period</quantifiedObject> centered at <measure type="value">20 UT</measure>. The model uses very high ejection velocities, assumes that water-driven production will be principally The displayed values are for <quantifiedObject id="5b5510fe-0c8d-45eb-899e-e1d77f2f25b1">grains</quantifiedObject> with density ρ ref = <measure type="value" ptr="#5b5510fe-0c8d-45eb-899e-e1d77f2f25b1">1 g cm −3</measure> , and for grains with different density ρ the count fluence scales as (ρ ref /ρ) 1−a , while the mass fluence scales as (ρ ref /ρ) 3−a .</p>
    <p>In Ye &amp; Hui (2014) a dynamical model very similar to ours is employed, including a similar velocity scaling and similar constraints from observations, and an orbit solution just a <measure type="value">few weeks</measure> older than ours. They obtain no collisions with Mars at the nominal grain velocities, and fluence similar to ours if the grain velocity is increased, after accounting for different parameters (density and SFD index).</p>
    <p>Although the peak timing tends to shorter delays after c/a at high v ref values (see Figure 3), the strong attenuation from the velocity distribution causes the <quantifiedObject id="vref3">v ref</quantifiedObject> ≃ <measure type="value" ptr="#vref3">1.5 m/s</measure> timing to dominate, with a peak between <measure type="interval">90 and 100 minutes</measure> after c/a. The timings provided in this paper refer to the current estimate of the c/a time as indicated in the Introduction, and will not change even if the nucleus c/a will change due to possible strong non-gravitational forces which may become important in the last few months before c/a ( Farnocchia et al. 2014). As a matter of fact, Farnocchia et al. (2014) show that non-gravitational perturbations may become relevant only when approaching the perihelion, The sub-solar point is just <measure type="value">two degrees</measure> beyond the edge of Mars. The Opportunity rover (MER-B) will be in favorable position for possible observations but in daylight.</p>
    <p>We have presented the results of our dynamical model for the delivery of dust grains ejected from the nucleus of comet C/2013 A1 (Siding Spring) to Mars. Direct extrapolation of the grain ejection velocity from HST observations indicates that the bulk of the grains will likely miss Mars. If we include the possibility of a <measure type="value">few-percent</measure> of the grains to have higher velocities, we find that millimeter radius grains ejected at <measure type="interval">9 AU</measure> or more from the Sun will collide with Mars. At higher velocities, younger grains from <measure type="interval">sub-millimeter to several millimeter</measure> can reach Mars too. The <quantifiedObject id="ff146096-9791-495d-941e-048dca80fd22">maximum fluence</quantifiedObject> will be of the order of <measure type="value" ptr="#ff146096-9791-495d-941e-048dca80fd22">10 −7 grains/m 2</measure> . The timing of the peak flux is expected to be <measure type="interval">90-100 minutes</measure> after c/a, which is between <measure type="interval" ptr="#0926ef04-a52c-4b96-9f43-06450206b0ea">19:59 and 20:09 UT of October 19, 2014</measure>.</p>
</text>