<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <p>Polycrystalline samples of layered pnictogen diselenide NdO0.8F0.2Sb1xBixSe2 (<quantifiedObject id="a1acbbbf-dc54-4ca0-99a3-eea0167dbc1a">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="interval" ptr="#a1acbbbf-dc54-4ca0-99a3-eea0167dbc1a">0 to 0.8</measure>) were successfully synthesized by solid-state reactions. Electrical resistivity in the synthesized samples was systematically decreased with an increase in Bi content x. Crystal structure analysis using synchrotron X-ray diffraction suggests that insulator to metal transition upon Bi doping correlates with anomalous change in c-axis length and/or corrugation in conducting layer. The emergence of superconductivity under high pressure is demonstrated using diamond anvil cell (DAC) with boron-doped diamond electrodes, for <quantifiedObject id="a1acbbbf-dc54-4ca0-99a3-eea0167dbc1b">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure ptr="#a1acbbbf-dc54-4ca0-99a3-eea0167dbc1b" type="value">0.3</measure> and <measure type="interval" ptr="#6257fe59-33b7-4e7d-a2c6-a55a7d05ff14">0.7</measure> as the representative samples. For Sb-rich one (x = <measure type="value">0.3</measure>), we observed a superconducting transition with <quantifiedObject id="5d6b14f4-1295-4301-aa02-fd61cceb9113">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#5d6b14f4-1295-4301-aa02-fd61cceb9113">5.3 K</measure> at <measure type="value">50 GPa</measure>, which is the first-ever report of the superconductivity in layered SbCh2-based (Ch: chalcogen) compounds.</p>
	<p>The Tc onset of <quantifiedObject id="5d6b14f4-1295-4301-aa02-fd61cceb9113">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#5d6b14f4-1295-4301-aa02-fd61cceb9113">0.3</measure> increased with increasing pressure and reached <measure type="value">7.9 K</measure> at <measure type="value">70.8 GPa</measure>, followed by the gradual decrease in <quantifiedObject id="39fba237-8a6d-404f-a7f6-a114f00e1fb2">Tc</quantifiedObject> up to <measure type="interval" ptr="#39fba237-8a6d-404f-a7f6-a114f00e1fb2">90 GPa</measure>. For Bi-rich one (<quantifiedObject id="95945dd7-db68-4c6f-8c8c-8f5606829631">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#95945dd7-db68-4c6f-8c8c-8f5606829631">0.7</measure>), a superconducting transition with <quantifiedObject id="04a22cec-628d-4a88-88b8-3f28622b5843">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#04a22cec-628d-4a88-88b8-3f28622b5843">5.9 K</measure> was observed at <measure type="value">43.5 GPa</measure>, which is the almost comparable to that of <quantifiedObject id="04a22cec-628d-4a88-88b8-3f28622b5844">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#04a22cec-628d-4a88-88b8-3f28622b5844">0.3</measure>. The present work will be helpful to bridge the gap between insulating SbCh2-based and metallic BiCh2-based systems, which show superconductivity at ambient pressure.</p>
	<p>Since the discovery of the BiCh2-based (Ch: S, Se) layered superconductors in <measure type="value">2012</measure>, such as Bi4O4S3 and R(O,F)BiS2 (R: rare-earth element), this family of compounds has received much attention as a new class of layered superconductors [1][2][3][4][5][6][7][8]. The crystal structure is composed of alternate stacks of electrically conducting BiCh2 layers and insulating (blocking) carrier reservoir layers, as schematically depicted in Fig. 1. Several types of BiCh2-based superconductors have been reported, and the <quantifiedObject id="c7a84537-5245-42d6-819a-125a141b4194">highest-record Tc</quantifiedObject> of <measure type="value" ptr="#c7a84537-5245-42d6-819a-125a141b4194">11 K</measure> was obtained for LaO0.5F0.5BiS2 using high-pressure technique [3,9]. In the early stages of research on a paring mechanism of BiCh2-based compounds, it was suggested that the conventional superconductivity with a fully gapped s-wave state is realized, on the basis of the first-principles calculation [10], Raman scattering [11], muon-spin spectroscopy [12], and thermal conductivity [13] experiments. However, recent first-principles calculations [14], angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy [15], and Se isotope effect [16] proposed the possibility of unconventional pairing mechanisms in BiCh2-based superconductors. Therefore, systematic characterization is still crucial to clarify the superconductivity mechanisms of these compounds.</p>
	<p>Generally speaking, the parent phase of BiCh2-based compounds is an n-type semiconductor. These compounds show superconductivity when electron carriers are generated at the conduction bands. Because the conduction bands are mainly composed of hybridization between Bi 6p and Ch p orbitals [17,18], it is quite reasonable to expect that the understanding of the doping effects of Sb for Bi is essentially important to elucidate the superconducting mechanisms and the underlying physics in this family of compounds. Besides superconductivity, Sb doped BiCh2-based 4 compounds, namely SbCh2-based compounds, are also attractive from the viewpoint of the thermoelectrics and topological materials [19][20][21]. However, most of SbCh2-based compounds have been insulators so far, in spite of isovalent Sb doping on the Bi site [22][23][24][25][26]. Although the origin of insulating nature in SbCh2-based compounds has not been fully understood yet, it is probably due to insufficient orbital overlapping between Sb 5p and Ch p orbitals [27]. Indeed, insulator to metal transition was observed for Ce(O,F)SbS2 under high pressure [25].</p>
	<p>We have reported the effects of Bi doping on high-temperature thermoelectric transport properties of SbSe2-based layered compounds NdO0.8F0.2Sb1xBixSe2 (<quantifiedObject id="7bb8f68d-480f-4a5c-940c-a3f20c05eae9">x</quantifiedObject>  <measure type="value" ptr="#7bb8f68d-480f-4a5c-940c-a3f20c05eae9">0.4</measure>) [26]. <measure type="value">Room temperature</measure> <quantifiedObject id="073a42a3-54bb-41bd-8172-76941200ef6a">electrical resistivity</quantifiedObject> was decreased down from <measure type="value" ptr="#073a42a3-54bb-41bd-8172-76941200ef6a">300 mcm</measure> for <quantifiedObject id="x123">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="interval" ptr="#x123">0 to 8 mcm</measure> for <quantifiedObject id="x1234">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#x1234">0.4</measure>. However, the temperature dependence of electrical resistivity was still insulating for <quantifiedObject id="x1">x</quantifiedObject>  <measure type="interval" ptr="#x1">0.4</measure>. In the present study, we show that Bi-rich composition up to ca. <quantifiedObject id="x2">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#x2">0.8</measure> can be obtained by optimizing synthesis temperature. Electrical resistivity in the synthesized samples was systematically decreased with an increase in Bi content x. Weakly localized behavior in low temperature electrical transport was still observed for all of examined samples. Electrical transport of <quantifiedObject id="fe608092-51bf-4b9b-9dcc-6081a06163a2">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="list" ptr="#fe608092-51bf-4b9b-9dcc-6081a06163a2">0.3 and 0.7</measure> was examined under <quantifiedObject id="gpa">high pressure</quantifiedObject> exceeding <measure type="interval" ptr="#gpa">50 GPa</measure> using diamond anvil cell (DAC) with boron-doped diamond electrodes. It was found that both samples show superconductivity at low temperature, which is the first-ever report of superconductivity in SbCh2-based layered compounds. Further, the present study is the first report that tunes in a wide range of Bi/Sb content (<quantifiedObject id="x12">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="interval" ptr="#x12">00.8</measure>). The results enable us to bridge the gap between insulating SbCh2-based and metallic BiCh2-based systems, which shows superconductivity at ambient pressure. Because the Nd powder is reactive in air and a moist atmosphere, this process was carried out in an Ar-filled glovebox with a gas-purifier system. Then, a stoichiometric mixture of these starting materials was pressed into a pellet and heated for 15 h at <measure type="value">700ºC</measure> for <quantifiedObject id="39d24ac8-2494-450d-8f0c-a749f0c7b0e3">x</quantifiedObject>  <measure type="interval" ptr="#39d24ac8-2494-450d-8f0c-a749f0c7b0e3">0.4</measure> and at <measure type="value">650ºC</measure> for <quantifiedObject id="x24">x</quantifiedObject>  <measure type="interval" ptr="#x24">0.5</measure> in an evacuated silica tube. Notably, amounts of impurity phases, Bi2Se3 and Nd2O2Se, was significant when the samples with x  <measure type="value">0.5</measure> were synthesized at <measure type="value">700 o C</measure>.</p>
	<p>The chemical compositions of the obtained samples were examined using an energy dispersive X-ray spectrometer (EDX; Oxford, SwiftED3000). The phase purity and crystal structure of the samples were examined by synchrotron powder X-ray diffraction (SPXRD) performed at the BL02B2 beamline of SPring-8 (proposal numbers 2018A0074 and 2018B1246). <quantifiedObject id="72d7be4f-4b2d-433d-badb-77cca6a41e90">The measurements</quantifiedObject> were performed at <measure type="value" ptr="#72d7be4f-4b2d-433d-badb-77cca6a41e90">297 K</measure>. The diffraction data were collected using a high-resolution 6 one-dimensional semiconductor detector (multiple MYTHEN system) [28]. The wavelength of the <quantifiedObject id="2d4cfa5b-5c41-4a46-82c7-b656fb945b87">radiation beam</quantifiedObject> was determined to be <measure type="list" ptr="#2d4cfa5b-5c41-4a46-82c7-b656fb945b87">0.495274(1) Å (proposal number 2018A0074) and 0.496345 (1) Å</measure> (No. 2018B1246) using a CeO2 standard. The crystal structure parameters were refined by the Rietveld method using RIETAN-FP software [29]. The crystal structure was visualized using VESTA software [30].</p>
	<p>Electrical resistivity at ambient pressure was measured using the four-probe method on a GM refrigerator system. Measurements of electrical resistance under high pressure were performed using an originally designed DAC with boron-doped diamond electrodes [25,31,32] on the bottom anvil of nanopolycrystalline diamond [33], as shown in Fig. 2. The sample was placed on the boron-doped diamond electrodes in the center of the bottom anvil. The surface of the bottom anvil except for the sample space and electrical terminal were covered by the undoped diamond insulating layer. The cubic boron nitride powders with ruby manometer were used as a pressure-transmitting medium. The applied pressure was estimated by the fluorescence from ruby powders [34] and the Raman spectrum from the culet of top diamond anvil [35] by an inVia Raman Microscope (RENISHAW). The resistance was measured by a standard four-probe method on a Physical Property Measurement System (Quantum Design: PPMS). representative data. Almost all the diffraction peaks can be assigned to those of the tetragonal P4/nmm space group, indicating that the obtained sample is mainly composed of NdO0.8F0.2Sb1-xBixSe2-type phase. However, several peaks, attributable to impurity phases, <quantifiedObject id="247da27d-2599-4c72-83b4-8a51eca3dae5">Nd2O2Se</quantifiedObject> (<measure type="value" ptr="#247da27d-2599-4c72-83b4-8a51eca3dae5">4.1 wt%</measure>), <quantifiedObject id="e151ac23-fe08-450e-8116-3b5fa4cc8c4c">NdOF</quantifiedObject> (<measure type="value" ptr="#e151ac23-fe08-450e-8116-3b5fa4cc8c4c">1.9 wt%</measure>), and <quantifiedObject id="627864d9-57f7-4b84-b215-b429924677d6">Bi2Se3</quantifiedObject> (<measure type="value" ptr="#627864d9-57f7-4b84-b215-b429924677d6">0.8 wt%</measure>), were also observed. At the same time, the diffraction peaks for other samples can also be assigned to those of the tetragonal P4/nmm space group, as shown in Fig. S1 [36]. Amounts of secondary phases are significant for <quantifiedObject id="x244">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#x244">0.8</measure>, Nd2O2Se</p>
	<p>(<measure type="value">13.2 wt%</measure>) and <quantifiedObject id="bi2Se3">Bi2Se3</quantifiedObject> (<measure type="value" ptr="#bi2Se3">12.9 wt%</measure>), suggesting solubility limit of Bi for Sb in NdO0.8F0.2Sb1-xBixSe2 is at around this composition. (Channon's five-coordinate ionic radius, rBi 3+ = <measure type="value">96 pm</measure> and rSb 3+ = <measure type="value">80 pm</measure>) [37]. On the other hand, the c exhibits anomalous change at around <quantifiedObject id="x1111">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="list" ptr="#x1111">0.50.6</measure>. Although the origin of this deviation from linear relationship between c and x is not clear yet, it seems to be correlated to electrical carrier transport of the present samples, as described below. Note that c-axis length tends to correlate with amount of electron doping in the BiCh2-based systems [2][3][4][5][6][7][8].</p>
	<p>To investigate the electrical transport under high pressure, we employed x = <measure type="value">0.3</measure> and <measure type="interval">0.7</measure> as the representatives of Sb-rich and Bi-rich composition, respectively. It should be noted that x = <measure type="value">0.8</measure> is ruled out for high pressure measurements because of the existence of nonnegligible amount of <quantifiedObject id="9f17eb57-decd-4435-9815-385a5ba2c72e">Bi2Se3 secondary phase</quantifiedObject> (<measure type="value" ptr="#9f17eb57-decd-4435-9815-385a5ba2c72e">12.9 wt%</measure>), which shows superconductivity under high pressure [38,39]. Figure 6 shows the temperature dependences of electrical resistance for x = <measure type="value" ptr="#e7e36f65-3674-47bc-bc73-353c858d9fd7">0.3</measure> under various pressures (a) from <measure type="value">12.2 GPa</measure> to <measure type="interval">50 GPa</measure>, and (b) from <measure type="value" ptr="#834d0284-2882-4e97-89c1-bd4bd417abce">50</measure> <quantifiedObject id="834d0284-2882-4e97-89c1-bd4bd417abce">GPa</quantifiedObject> to <measure type="interval">90 GPa</measure>. The resistance exhibits an insulating behavior with <quantifiedObject id="61aca200-f5af-4dc1-9f9e-9961aceb6915">a negative slope of</quantifiedObject> dR/dT up to <measure type="value" ptr="#61aca200-f5af-4dc1-9f9e-9961aceb6915">42.5 GPa</measure>, although it decreases with increasing pressure. A sudden drop of resistance was observed at <measure type="value">5.1 K</measure> at <measure type="value">50 GPa</measure>, corresponding to a superconducting transition. At <measure type="value" ptr="#fcc2feae-f26c-49d4-b9d1-ee4bacdefb29">57.2 GPa</measure>, the resistance at 10 K decreases about four orders in magnitude as compared to that at 12.2 GPa, indicating the insulator to <quantifiedObject id="fcc2feae-f26c-49d4-b9d1-ee4bacdefb29">metal transition</quantifiedObject> at this pressure. The resistance continued to decrease up to <measure type="interval">90 GPa</measure>, and then, the diamond anvil was broken. It should be noted that <measure type="value" ptr="#f37caf6b-7017-4814-af06-d1505fa40e80">zero</measure> <quantifiedObject id="f37caf6b-7017-4814-af06-d1505fa40e80">resistivity</quantifiedObject> was not observed at low temperature, most likely due to inhomogeneity of applied pressure for polycrystalline sample, which is generally occurred with DAC systems [40]. To confirm that the observed drop of resistance was originated from the superconductivity, we measured the resistance under magnetic fields. Werthamer-Helfand-Hohenberg (WHH) approximation for type II superconductors in a dirty limit [41]. <quantifiedObject id="28eb84e8-29e9-4976-abfb-0b4900d57bf0">The Hc2(0) at</quantifiedObject> <measure type="value" ptr="#28eb84e8-29e9-4976-abfb-0b4900d57bf0">70.8 GPa</measure> was estimated to be <measure type="value">6.6 T</measure>, which is comparable to that of BiCh2-based superconductors. Notably, the lower Hc2(0) at <measure type="value" ptr="#83d95b2e-efc3-4b74-b2bf-2bbba30a693d">90</measure> <quantifiedObject id="83d95b2e-efc3-4b74-b2bf-2bbba30a693d">GPa</quantifiedObject>, <measure type="value" ptr="#4d1e0d04-57f5-4d08-b831-a2f4a6af7026">4.0 T</measure>, than that at <measure type="value">70.8 GPa</measure> is consistent with lower Tc at this pressure. composition, which seems to contradict to our simple expectation that superconductivity is more easily induced under high pressure in Bi rich sample, because of its metallic-like nature at ambient pressure. We deduce this is due to lattice instability in the present compounds. All of the crystal structure of the samples presented in this study is assigned to tetragonal P4/nmm space group using SPXRD measured at room temperature. However, theoretical studies show that the existence of imaginary phonons in the related compounds [10,[42][43][44][45]. These studies also reported that the total energy of the tetragonal P4/nmm is not the lowest [43,44]. Indeed, symmetry lowering to monoclinic P21/m [46][47][48] and nanoscale atomic distortion [49][50][51][52][53][54] have been experimentally observed for BiCh2-based compounds. For another layered compound, R2O2Pn with a Pn 2-net, insulating nature that originates from lattice distortion has recently been investigated [55][56][57][58][59][60]. Although both R2O2Bi</p>
	<p>We synthesized Bi-substituted SbCh2-based compounds NdO<measure type="value">0.8</measure>F0.2Sb1-xBixSe2 (x = <measure type="value">00.8</measure>) and demonstrated in-situ transport measurements under high pressure condition to examine the pressure-induced superconductivity. In Sb-rich composition, <quantifiedObject id="x111">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#x111">0.3</measure>, a superconducting transition with <quantifiedObject id="1ea2baaa-636e-4a63-ad9a-71273aade394">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#1ea2baaa-636e-4a63-ad9a-71273aade394">5.3 K</measure> was observed at <measure type="value">50 GPa</measure> , and reached <measure type="value">7.9 K</measure> at <measure type="value">70.8 GPa</measure>. The Hc2(0) was estimated to be <measure type="value">6.6 T</measure> at <measure type="value">70.8 GPa</measure> using WHH model. For Bi-rich one (<quantifiedObject id="5c1a8950-209a-42c4-ae43-4a26576978c7">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#5c1a8950-209a-42c4-ae43-4a26576978c7">0.7</measure>), a superconducting transition with <quantifiedObject id="5c1a8950-209a-42c4-ae43-4a26576978c8">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#5c1a8950-209a-42c4-ae43-4a26576978c8">5.9 K</measure> was observed at <measure type="value">43.5 GPa</measure>, which is the almost comparable to that of <quantifiedObject id="x112323232">x</quantifiedObject> = <measure type="value" ptr="#x112323232">0.3</measure>. The present work will be helpful to bridge the gap between insulating SbCh2-based and metallic BiCh2-based systems, which show superconductivity at ambient pressure.</p>
</text>