<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<p>suggests possible ferromagnetic fluctuations in the Mott phase which might mediate the corresponding unconventional pairing mechanism in the superconductivity phase observed in our system. These results establish the twisted double bilayer graphene as easily tunable platform for exploring new paradigm of quantum many-body states. [10][11][12][13][14][15][16][17] Twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) with a small twist angle θ possesses significantly reconstructed band structure. 1,2,3 In vicinity of a magic angle (MA), i.e. <quantifiedObject id="theta">θ</quantifiedObject>≈<measure type="value" ptr="#theta">1.1°</measure>, strong interlayer hybridization leads to a flat band formation with low energy and narrow bandwidth, greatly enhances the electronic interaction effect 1,4,5,6 than those of graphene or bilayer graphene without twisting. 7 So far, correlated insulating states and superconductivity have been observed for a variety of partially filled bands, 4,5,6 suggesting the TBG systems acquire novel features resembling strange metal in highTc superconductivity, 5,10 novel states of the Mott insulator, 4,11-15 unconventional and topological superconductor, 5,16,17 (fragile) topological band structure, 18,19 quantum anomalous Hall effect 11,20 and many others, consequently spur the interests of theoretical and experimental communities alike. However, to observe these interesting correlation induced phenomena, one has to control θ accurately enough in TBG, which puts strict constraint in device fabrications. Therefore, easier access to the flat band by alternative approaches is of high importance. Recently, Mott insulator and superconductivity have been observed in TBG with <quantifiedObject id="56ecea15-b1cc-4d8d-9992-2e5ea9421618">θ</quantifiedObject>&gt;<measure type="interval" ptr="#56ecea15-b1cc-4d8d-9992-2e5ea9421618">1.1°</measure> by exerting an external high pressure. 6 Another approach is to apply vertical displacement electrical fields, achieved in ABC-stacked trilayer graphene on hexagonal boron nitride (hBN). 21,22 However, tuning by displacement field fails in TBG, possibly due to strong interlayer hybridization. 3,6 Twisted double bilayer graphene (TDBG), on the other hand, is more likely to possess a flat band and display correlated phenomena. 23 It is known that monolayer graphene possesses linearly dispersive energy bands, showing no dependence on the displacement electrical fields. In contrast, AB stacked bilayer graphene shows parabolic band dispersion and gap opening at charge neutral point (CNP) could be induced under displacement electrical fields. 7,8,9 The gap reaches its minimum not rightly at, but close to K point, displaying a "Mexican-hat" dispersion of band structure. 7,9 Such a dispersion hosts a narrower band width and could enable flat band formation in TDBG by displacement fields.</p>
	<p>In this work, we report the success in easy tunability in TDBG by vertical electrical fields. At specific range of electric fields, we observe correlated Mott-like insulating state corresponding to the half-filled band on the electron branch, and more importantly, signatures of superconductivity with <quantifiedObject id="tcOnset1">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> at <measure type="value" ptr="#tcOnset1">~12 K</measure> and <measure type="value">50%</measure></p>
	<p>resistance <quantifiedObject id="tc1">Tc</quantifiedObject> at <measure type="value" ptr="#tc1">~7 K</measure> in the vicinity of the Mott insulator. Our devices have the unique advantages that the characteristic temperature scales of Mott insulator and superconductivity are above the liquid helium temperature, therefore greatly reduced the requirement in device fabrications and sample characterizations. Moreover, under parallel magnetic fields, we found Mott gap for the <measure type="value" ptr="#33c51635-7eaf-4fb7-80c5-58f9546218e2">half</measure>-<quantifiedObject id="33c51635-7eaf-4fb7-80c5-58f9546218e2">filled band</quantifiedObject> become stronger, suggesting a spin-polarized ordering and the correspondingly unconventional pairing mechanism of superconductivity.</p>
	<p>TDBG samples were fabricated following a typical "tear and stack" technique 24 with <quantifiedObject id="39739c58-1a24-4bb0-bd5b-f5fdb8b3aa55">θ accuracy</quantifiedObject> at <measure type="value" ptr="#39739c58-1a24-4bb0-bd5b-f5fdb8b3aa55">~0.1°</measure>. One-dimensional edge contact 25 was applied with a <quantifiedObject id="39739c58-1a24-4bb0-bd5b-f5fdb8b3aa56">good characteristic</quantifiedObject> less than <measure type="interval" ptr="#39739c58-1a24-4bb0-bd5b-f5fdb8b3aa56">1 kΩ·um</measure>. Figure 1a shows the schematic structure of our devices. Under proper displacement electrical fields, the reformed band structure of AB stacked bilayer graphene, hosts more flatness in the top of valence band and bottom of conduction band, and thus facilitate the formation of flat band in TDBG (Fig. 1b). All the devices are first picked out through their "U" shaped G-Vg curves at room temperature，which show greatly decreased carrier mobility because of the presence of flat band. .</p>
	<p>We firstly tested <measure type="value" ptr="#cadfe026-ed6d-4587-ae6c-32271a00a52b">two</measure> <quantifiedObject id="cadfe026-ed6d-4587-ae6c-32271a00a52b">dual-gate devices</quantifiedObject> with <quantifiedObject id="cadfe026-ed6d-4587-ae6c-32271a00a52c">θ</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="value" ptr="#cadfe026-ed6d-4587-ae6c-32271a00a52c">1.28°</measure> (device-1) and <quantifiedObject id="cadfe026-ed6d-4587-ae6c-32271a00a52d">θ</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="value" ptr="#cadfe026-ed6d-4587-ae6c-32271a00a52d">1.31°</measure> (device-2) to reveal the transport behavior of the <measure type="value" ptr="#76e8ca8b-725c-43a8-a7b2-3208807a7b6d">half</measure>-<quantifiedObject id="76e8ca8b-725c-43a8-a7b2-3208807a7b6d">filled insulating states</quantifiedObject> in TDBG.</p>
	<p>Both devices show single-particle superlattice gap at n=±ns at electron and hole branch (Fig. 1c, 1d) (we note higher-order superlattice gaps at <quantifiedObject id="n1">n</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="interval" ptr="#n1">±3ns</measure> are observed in device-3 with a smaller <quantifiedObject id="aeb71b61-1823-4db9-9a60-a9036804dcbc">θ</quantifiedObject> around <measure type="value" ptr="#aeb71b61-1823-4db9-9a60-a9036804dcbc">1.0°</measure>). The twist angle can be calculated through equation í µí°´í µí°´≈µí°´≈ √3í µí±í µí± 2 2í µí¼í µí¼ 2 , 4,5 where A is the area of moiré unit cell, extracted from magnetic flux where Landau levels cross or superlattice carrier density ns=4/A, and <quantifiedObject id="aeb71b61-1823-4db9-9a60-a9036804dcbd">a</quantifiedObject>=<measure ptr="#aeb71b61-1823-4db9-9a60-a9036804dcbd" type="value">0.246nm</measure></p>
	<p>is the lattice constant of graphene. The dual-gate structure makes it easier to tune carrier concentration as well as the displacement fields across TDBG. The displacement field is set by í µí°·í µí°· = 1 2 (í µí°·í µí°· í µí±¡í µí±¡ + í µí°·í µí°· í µí±í µí± ) , where í µí°·í µí°· í µí±¡í µí±¡ = +í µí¼í µí¼ í µí±í µí±í µí±¡í µí±¡ (í µí±í µí± í µí±¡í µí±¡ − í µí±í µí± í µí±¡í µí±¡ 0 ) í µí±í µí± í µí±¡í µí±¡ ⁄ and í µí°·í µí°· í µí±í µí± = −í µí¼í µí¼ í µí±í µí±í µí±í µí± (í µí±í µí± í µí±í µí± − í µí±í µí± í µí±í µí± 0 ) í µí±í µí± í µí±í µí± ⁄ . Here, í µí¼í µí¼ í µí±í µí±í µí±¡í µí±¡ and í µí¼í µí¼ í µí±í µí±í µí±í µí± are relative dielectric constant for top dielectric layer with thickness dt, and bottom with db, respectively. í µí±í µí± í µí±¡í µí±¡ 0 and í µí±í µí± í µí±í µí± 0 represent the offset gate voltage to reach the charge neutrality.</p>
	<p>We can see an obvious insulating state at n=ns/2 at electron branch under an intermediate D (Fig. 1c). Fitting through Arrhenius formula í µí± í µí± ~í µí±í µí± ∆ 2í µí±í µí±í µí±í µí± , the correlated gap in device-2 is estimated to be around 1meV, modified by displacement fields (Fig. 1d, inset) (We also note that the gap at <measure type="value" ptr="#abb717d2-b32e-459b-afdd-a200456e7045">half</measure>-<quantifiedObject id="abb717d2-b32e-459b-afdd-a200456e7045">filling</quantifiedObject> varies with twist angle and device quality). resulted from displacement fields D.</p>
	<p>The superconductivity in TDBG in device-1 with <quantifiedObject id="abab6a84-ed69-425b-9aed-1944c3c6ac85">θ</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="value" ptr="#abab6a84-ed69-425b-9aed-1944c3c6ac85">1.28°</measure> is discovered near the <measure type="value" ptr="#28df6a97-55e4-45ba-a2fb-97cf6c0cafcf">half</measure>-<quantifiedObject id="28df6a97-55e4-45ba-a2fb-97cf6c0cafcf">filled insulator</quantifiedObject>. Figure 3a shows a representative R-T curve. At a <quantifiedObject id="low_temperature12">low temperature</quantifiedObject> &lt;<measure ptr="#low_temperature12" type="interval">4K</measure> the system develops <measure type="value" ptr="#7175c775-f727-408b-8fda-73633518937a">zero</measure> <quantifiedObject id="7175c775-f727-408b-8fda-73633518937a">resistance</quantifiedObject>. The estimated Tc for <measure type="value" ptr="#bfdadd3f-6c7d-4366-a8d7-92e82646f1c9">50%</measure> <quantifiedObject id="bfdadd3f-6c7d-4366-a8d7-92e82646f1c9">normal state resistance</quantifiedObject> is about <measure type="value">7K</measure>, and <quantifiedObject id="tc_onset2">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> is about at <measure ptr="#tc_onset2" type="value">12K</measure>. Such high Tc in TDBG is above the liquid helium temperature and also much higher than the temperature scale of Tc in MA-TBG 5,6 and ABC stacked trilayer graphene, 22 this discovery certainly bestows one with confidence and points out direction to achieve even higher Tc in future experiments. Figure 3b shows only <measure type="value" ptr="#superconductivity_pocket1">one</measure> <quantifiedObject id="superconductivity_pocket1">superconductivity pocket</quantifiedObject>, located at electron side of halffilled insulator. The pocket shrinks with the increased temperature. Note that fluctuations around <measure type="value" ptr="#ba1e54cd-e86e-492a-8e33-48cdd7d1ed5d">zero</measure> <quantifiedObject id="ba1e54cd-e86e-492a-8e33-48cdd7d1ed5d">resistance</quantifiedObject> possibly arises from inhomogeneous distribution of twist angle in our devices, which is also hosted in previous work. 6 The inhomogeneity leads to the co-existence of insulator and superconductivity and finally forms stray capacitance which causes fluctuation of AC current phase during our measurements. Similar to the electrically tunable Mott insulator, superconductivity in TDBG can also be mediated by displacement fields, as depicted in Figure 3c. As we sweep the top gate voltage while keeping a constant <quantifiedObject id="d0f2e0ce-5a8f-4812-ac29-f976b82af188">back gate voltage</quantifiedObject> varied from <measure type="value" ptr="#d0f2e0ce-5a8f-4812-ac29-f976b82af188">-16V to -31V</measure>, the <measure type="value" ptr="#d0f2e0ce-5a8f-4812-ac29-f976b82af189">zero</measure> <quantifiedObject id="d0f2e0ce-5a8f-4812-ac29-f976b82af189">resistance pocket</quantifiedObject> shrinks and finally disappears. Thus a <measure type="value" ptr="#d0f2e0ce-5a8f-4812-ac29-f976b82af119">zero</measure> <quantifiedObject id="d0f2e0ce-5a8f-4812-ac29-f976b82af119">resistance</quantifiedObject> behavior modulated by carrier density as well as displacement fields is present in TDBG.</p>
	<p>Finally, we discuss the electronic nature of the <measure type="value" ptr="#5ca23664-be55-4812-8793-75e6dd126da4">half</measure>-<quantifiedObject id="5ca23664-be55-4812-8793-75e6dd126da4">filled Mott insulator</quantifiedObject> and superconductivity in its vicinity. Since perpendicular fields affect not only spin but also orbital dynamics, to isolate the mechanism related with these correlated states, we instead exerted parallel magnetic fields in device-3 (graphite acts as back-gate) with <quantifiedObject id="a32e4654-a703-4c4e-8019-286a05dc918b">θ</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="value" ptr="#a32e4654-a703-4c4e-8019-286a05dc918b">1.06°</measure> and probe the field dependence in resistances. Fig. 4a shows absence of half-filled insulating state at <quantifiedObject id="a32e4654-a703-4c4e-8019-286a05dc918c">B//</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="value" ptr="#a32e4654-a703-4c4e-8019-286a05dc918c">0T</measure> (Fig. 4a). The parallel magnetic fields monotonously enhance resistance at n=ns/2 (Fig. 4c) and lead to an obvious insulating state at moderate D and higher B// (Fig. 4b, 4c). Since B// only affects spin degree of freedom, the enhanced insulating behavior implies the insulating state at ns/2 is likely to be spin-polarized. Arising from Zeeman effect, magnetic fields induces gap Δ=gμBB//, between spin-up and spin-down electrons, where the g factor for electrons in graphene is ~2 and μB is the Bohr magneton. From the Arrhenius formula of resistance, we obtain thermal activated gap as a function of B//, which shows nearly linear increase as shown in Fig.4d. Thus we deduce the <quantifiedObject id="a32e4654-a703-4c4e-8019-286a05dc918dd">effective g factor</quantifiedObject> is about <measure type="value" ptr="#a32e4654-a703-4c4e-8019-286a05dc918dd">2.12</measure>, coincident with the expectation, and more importantly reveal the fact that the Mott gap is more likely to be spin-triplet gap, very different from the spin-singlet gap in the TBG system. 4,6</p>
	<p>Although in many cases Mott insulators are likely to be associated with the antiferromagnetic ordering. However, ferromagnetism can also be present in Mott insulators such as Ba2NaOsO6 31 and Lu2V2O7. 32 Considering that the superconductivity occurs in the vicinity of the <measure type="value" ptr="#d51758aa-db29-4d1f-82ae-37af7adff7da">half</measure>-<quantifiedObject id="d51758aa-db29-4d1f-82ae-37af7adff7da">filled spin-polarized</quantifiedObject> Mott-like state, a bold conjecture of ferromagnetic fluctuations mediated superconductivity in TDBG could be put forward. Such a case has been found in UGe2, where the superconductivity phase coexists with itinerant-electron ferromagnetic phase 33 . Note that spin-triplet (valley-singlet in the case of TDBG) pairing superconductivity is also present in 3 He superfluid. 34,35 Further investigations on TDBG, towards clarifying the ferromagnetism at ns/2 and B-enhanced superconductivity, are now of utter most importance to verify the appealing conjecture presented here.</p>
	<p>In summary, our work demonstrates electrically tunable half-filled Mott-like insulating state for a wide range of twist angle and superconductivity in TDBG, with estimated Tc for <measure type="value" ptr="#4cf826c8-2396-4fa9-b2bb-63f1caedb4fa">50%</measure> <quantifiedObject id="4cf826c8-2396-4fa9-b2bb-63f1caedb4fa">normal state resistance</quantifiedObject> at <measure type="value">7K</measure> and <quantifiedObject id="7e130e4e-f9b2-4f4b-bafd-4963eddc20e7">Tc onset</quantifiedObject> at <measure type="value" ptr="#7e130e4e-f9b2-4f4b-bafd-4963eddc20e7">12K</measure>. Our work suggests that TDBG hence provides an alternative, maybe easier, approach to observe</p>
	<p>Sample preparations. Raw materials of bilayer graphene, hexagonal boron nitride (<measure type="value" ptr="#43366329-4ade-42eb-825d-3d262795eda4">20-35nm</measure> in <quantifiedObject id="43366329-4ade-42eb-825d-3d262795eda4">thickness</quantifiedObject>) and graphite flakes were first exfoliated on SiO2 (<measure type="value" ptr="#a114f084-f4f3-4ca2-9118-025b335e10fe">300nm</measure> <quantifiedObject id="a114f084-f4f3-4ca2-9118-025b335e10fe">thick</quantifiedObject>), then annealed in Ar/H2 mixture at <quantifiedObject id="172470c2-4924-4fb6-93e6-a48b3a783ee9">temperature</quantifiedObject> up to <measure type="interval" ptr="#172470c2-4924-4fb6-93e6-a48b3a783ee9">450℃</measure> for cleanness.</p>
	<p>Usually, moderate H2 plasma etching was also applied to fully get rid of contaminations coming from the exfoliation process. We used Poly (Bisphenol A carbonate) (PC) supported by Polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) on glass slide to pick up boron nitride firstly and then tear and pick up bilayer graphene. The home-made micro-position stage can control the <quantifiedObject id="59bdffc9-538f-4bca-8326-a1ca8745dad7">rotation angle</quantifiedObject> at <measure type="value" ptr="#59bdffc9-538f-4bca-8326-a1ca8745dad7">0.1°</measure> error range. We performed no annealing for TDBG as it tends to relax to nearly twist angle <quantifiedObject id="23b8ae51-abbe-4daa-8990-8f52ca082961">θ</quantifiedObject>=<measure type="value" ptr="#23b8ae51-abbe-4daa-8990-8f52ca082961">0°</measure> once temperature is high. The fabrication of metal top gate and electrodes follows a standard e-beam lithography and e-beam metal evaporation. Devices were designed as Hall bar structure and shaped by traditional reactive ion etching with CHF3 and O2 mixture gas. Here, the metal top gate also acts as a mask for etching to ensure the channel is fully gated. Finally, all the bars were contacted through one-dimensional edge contact with Cr/Au electrodes.</p>
</text>