<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p><measure type="value"><num>Ten</num></measure> windsurfers (<measure type="value"><num>nine</num></measure> males and <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> female) volunteered to participate in the study and provided written informed consent. The subjects were reminded that withdrawal from the study was possible at any time. For the physical characteristics of the subjects see Table 1.</p>
		<p>All subjects were members of the Tunisian and Turkish Windsurfing National teams. They had regularly participated in <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="6">six</num> to <num atMost="8">eight</num></measure> international events per year for at least the previous <measure type="value"><num>2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (World and European Championships, and European Olympic sailing weeks). Their averaged weekly training programs included <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> running, <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> muscle strengthening, and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="4">four</num> to <num atMost="6">six</num></measure> windsurfing sessions. The study was approved by the University ethics committee.</p>
		<p>Light wind (LW) and medium wind (MW) were defined as wind speeds ranging from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num> to <num atMost="9">9</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure><!--case not supported --> <!--(<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2.57">2.57</num>-<num atMost="4.63">4.63</num> <measure type="?" unit="mAEs">mAEs</measure></measure> )1 ), and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> to <num atMost="16">16</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5.14">5.14</num>-<num atMost="8.23">8.23</num> <measure type="?" unit="mAEs">mAEs</measure></measure> )1 ), -->respectively. The races with too much wind variation switching from LW to MW were excluded from the analysis. Wind speed was measured with an anemometer (Plastimo, France) at the beginning of the race and every <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> throughout the race. These values were then averaged to obtain the mean race wind speed. Data from <measure type="value"><num>22</num></measure> races (<measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> in LW and <measure type="value"><num>12</num></measure> in MW) were analysed. The averaged wind speeds for the LW and MW races were <measure type="value"><num>6. 30</num></measure> (Gue´velGue´vel et al. 1999; ISAF) occurred over <measure type="value"><num>42</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> during a national competition period (<measure type="interval"><date from-iso="--06">June</date> and <date to-iso="--07">July</date></measure>). A typical Olympic course consists of a succession of legs, such as upwind (beating movement with the sail at ~<measure type="value"><num>45</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> to the wind direction), reaching (crosswind movement with the sail angle between ~<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="45">45</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure> and <num atMost="90">90</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure>) and running (downwind movement in the direction of the wind with the sail at ~<measure><num>90</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">°</measure></measure> to the wind). These last <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> legs are also called ''downwind''. Each race consisted of <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> laps. Standard Olympic boards were used (Mistral One Design, <measure><num>7.5</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>2</num></measure> sail) and the subjects were allowed to perform their own warm-up (Gue´velGue´vel et al. 1999). No changes in the usual racing procedure were required for the purposes of the experiment. As not all studied subjects participated in all the races, the analysis was of data from <measure type="value"><num>61</num></measure> individual races in LW and <measure type="value"><num>82</num></measure> in MW. At the end of each race the athletes were awarded classification points according to the current international rules (ISAF), i.e. <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> point for first place, <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> points for second, and so on. Each subject wore their HR monitor on land before their warm-up period. For each individual, the exact time of the start of the HR recording was noted. Each race was accurately timed with its strategic events, i.e. fleet start and individual finish. Then for each subject, the racing HR was isolated from the preand post-race HRs. The mean racing durations were <!-- case not supported --><!-- <measure type="value"><num>26</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>45</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>5 min 25</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure>) and <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> 45 s (<measure type="value"><num>9 min 2</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure>) in LW and MW, respectively. As international windsurfing rules allow only <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> for the fleet to complete the race after the winner's finish, the maximum difference of race duration between the athletes studied was <measure type="value"><num>6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>8 min 10</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure> in LW and MW respectively. --></p>
		<p>On-sea HR measurements HR was monitored with a HR monitor (Polar Vantage, Polar Electro, Kempele, Finland). The monitor consists of an electrode belt worn around the chest, a transmitter, and a wrist-mounted receiver. The sampling rate was set at <measure type="value"><num>0.2</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="Hz">Hz</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>Blood sampling and determination of blood lactate concentration Blood samples were collected <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> after the end of <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> LW and <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> MW races (for some subjects). A total of <measure type="value"><num>4</num></measure> LW and <measure type="value"><num>10</num></measure> MW samples were analysed. The <measure type="value"><num>20</num>-<measure type="VOLUME" unit="μl">ll</measure></measure> samples of capillary blood were withdrawn from an earlobe with Microzym micropipettes. They were stored in tubes containing <measure type="value"><num>180</num> <measure type="VOLUME" unit="μl">ll</measure></measure> of a haemolytic solution to ensure good preservation of the samples at <measure type="value"><measure type="TEMPERATURE">room temperature</measure></measure>. Blood lactate concentration was subsequently measured using an enzymatic method (Microzym L, Setric Ge´nieGe´nie Industriel, Toulouse, France).</p>
		<p>During the competitive period, each subject came to the laboratory to perform a maximal graded exercise test. The tests were performed in the afternoon from <measure type="interval"><time from-iso="14:00:00">2 pm</time> to <time to-iso="17:00:00">5 pm</time></measure> at a laboratory temperature of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure> to <num atMost="22">22</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. The subjects were asked to abstain from: (1) exercise the day prior to the test and (2) drinking caffeine beverages on the day of the test.</p>
		<p>A maximal graded exercise test on a treadmill allowed us to measure the subjects' maximum oxygen consumption (VO 2max ). Prior to the test subjects lay quietly on a bed for <measure type="value"><num>15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> for the measurement of their resting HR (HR rest ). Then the test was performed on a 0 graded treadmill (Woodway, Ergo XELG 90, Weil, Germany). It began with a <measure type="value"><num>3</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> warm-up period at <measure type="value"><num>9</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km/h">kmAEh-1</measure></measure> , immediately followed by <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="km/h">kmAEh-1</measure></measure> increment every minute till exhaustion. Oxygen consumption (VO 2 ) was considered maximal (VO 2max ) if the following criteria were achieved: (1) a levelling off of VO 2 despite a treadmill speed increase; (2) a respiratory gas exchange ratio higher than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.1">1.1</num></measure>, and (3) attainment of age theoretical HR max ±<measure type="value"><num>5</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="bpm">bpm</measure></measure>. All the subjects achieved physiological criteria for VO 2max. The peak HR attained at exhaustion during maximal graded exercise was considered to be HR max ( Chamari et al. 1995). Exhaustion occurred within <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>-<num atMost="15">15</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> of exercise for all subjects. The measurement of the cardiorespiratory variables was performed with a breath-by-breath cardiorespiratory device (ZAN 680, Oberthulba, Germany). This system allowed the continuous measurement of HR, pulmonary gas exchange, and ventilation during the test. Prior to each test the gas analysers were calibrated with gases of known concentrations. The ventilatory membrane was calibrated with a <measure type="value"><num>1</num>-<measure type="VOLUME" unit="l">l</measure></measure> syringe. HR was determined from a <measure type="value"><num>six</num></measure>-lead ECG with <measure type="value"><num>12</num></measure> derivations. On the test reports, HR and the respiratory data were provided once every <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="s">s</measure></measure> with the values averaged on the <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> last respiratory cycles on a sliding technique basis ( Whipp et al. 1982).</p>
		<p>The <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> ventilatory thresholds, Th1 vent and Th2 vent , i.e. anaerobic threshold and the respiratory compensation threshold, respectively, were established according to Beaver et al. (1986).</p>
		<p>The windsurfing HR values are expressed as a percentage of:</p>
		<p>(1) HR max (%HR max ) and (2) HR reserve , i.e. HR max )HR rest (%HR reserve ). For each subject, the race that resulted in the highest HR (%HR reserve ) was called RacingPeak%HR reserve .</p>
		<p>For the maximal graded exercise, the following values were selected: v Peak (treadmill peak velocity attained at exhaustion in the VO 2max trial), the first and second ventilatory thresholds expressed as a percentage of VO 2max (Th1 vent % VO 2max and Th2 vent % VO 2max , respectively). As Paavolaı¨nen Paavolaı¨nen et al. (1999) have shown that peak treadmill velocity is more correlated to endurance performance than VO 2max , VO 2max,demand was calculated as proposed by the American College of Sports Medicine (1986): VO 2max,demand (mlAEkg )1AE min )1 )=12AEv (mAEs )1 )+3.5 (with <measure type="value"><num>0</num></measure> graded treadmill), where v is peak treadmill velocity.</p>
		<p>Values are expressed as mean (standard deviation). A Pearson correlation coefficient and linear regression analysis were performed between the mean HRs measured during the races and: (1) performance (number of points obtained), the athlete's body mass, and race duration, and (2) the physiological variables measured at the laboratory. A linear regression analysis was realized between the racing HR and performance. With respect to the relationship between racing HR and the physiological variables, a forward stepwise multiple regression analysis was realized in order to establish which of the measured variables better explained the racing HR. The independent variables used in this analysis were the parameters of the VO 2max test, i.e.VO 2max , v Peak , Th1 vent % VO 2max , and Th2 vent % VO 2max. Statistical significance was fixed at the p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure> level.</p>
		<p>For the results of the maximal graded treadmill exercise see Table 2.</p>
		<p><!-- case not supported: mixed lists with different units --><!-- The mean HR for all the subjects in the LW and MW races represented <measure type="value"><num>80.51</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>6.82</num></measure>) and <measure type="value"><num>76.20</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>8.47</num></measure>)%HRmax, respectively. -->The linear regression analysis showed that there was a significant correlation between performance and racing HR in both LW and MW.</p>
		<p>In LW, the relationship between racing classification and the HR values expressed as %HR reserve were related by the formula: Racing Classification Points (LW)=)<measure type="value"><num>0.12 (%HR reserve )+13.03</num></measure>; r=)<measure type="value"><num>0.71</num></measure>, r 2 =<measure type="value"><num>0.50</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure> (Fig. 1). Racing HR expressed as %HR max was also significantly correlated to the racing classification points (r=)<measure type="value"><num>0.70</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>).</p>
		<p>In MW, the relationship between racing classification and the HR values expressed as %HR reserve were related by the formula: Racing Classification Points (MW)=)<measure type="value"><num>0.11 (%HR reserve )+10.99</num></measure>; r=)<measure type="value"><num>0.66</num></measure>, r 2 =<measure type="value"><num>0.43</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure> (Fig. 2). Racing HR expressed as % HR max was also significantly correlated to the racing classification points (r=)<measure type="value"><num>0.66</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>).</p>
		<p>These correlations were not influenced by the race duration as there was no correlation between %HR reserve and race duration, r=<measure type="value"><num>0.03</num></measure>, p=<measure type="value"><num>0.70</num></measure> (n=<measure type="value"><num>143</num></measure>).</p>
		<p>For wind speeds over <measure type="value"><num>12.5</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>6.43</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">mAEs )1</measure></measure> ), the correlation was significant between body mass and racing points classification (r=)<measure type="value"><num>0.451</num></measure>, r 2 =<measure type="value"><num>0.203</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.001">0.001</num></measure>, n=<measure type="value"><num>54</num></measure>). There was no correlation between body mass and performance in LW or MW between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num> and <num atMost="12.5">12.5</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure><!-- case not supported: mixed lists with different units --><!-- : r=<measure type="value"><num>0.085</num></measure>, p=<measure type="value"><num>0.515</num></measure> (n=<measure type="value"><num>61</num></measure>) and r=<measure type="value"><num>0.006</num></measure>, p=<measure type="value"><num>0.975</num></measure> (n=<measure type="value"><num>28</num></measure>), respectively. Post-racing lactate concentrations were higher in LW compared to MW: <measure type="value"><num>7.14</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>0.21</num></measure>) and <measure type="list"><num>5.18</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>2.02</num></measure>) mmolAEl )1 , respectively (t=<measure type="value"><num>3.01</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="value"><num>0.01</num></measure>) -->.</p>
		<p>The Pearson correlation matrix showed that there were some significant relationships between sailing HR measurements and laboratory variables. When the highest individual racing HR (%HR reserve ) was plotted against the main aerobic power variables, the stepwise regression analysis showed that <measure type="value"><num>51</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of the racing HR was explained by the second ventilatory threshold:</p>
		<p>r=<measure type="value"><num>-0.71</num></measure>, r 2 =<measure type="value"><num>0.51</num></measure>, p&lt;<measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure>.</p>
		<p>The present study showed that there was a positive correlation between the Olympic windsurfing performance and racing HR in both LW and MW conditions. Furthermore the relationship between windsurfing racing HR and laboratory variables showed that the higher individual HR (expressed as a percentage of HR reserve ) was negatively correlated to the second ventilatory threshold expressed as a percentage of VO 2max .</p>
		<p>Despite the possible effect of some non-physiological variables on HR and the fact that HR measurement is an indirect estimation of the cardiorespiratory responses, it is widely admitted that this variable is a good indicator of continuous exercise intensity (ACSM 1978;Le´gerLe´ger 1994). It has been shown that the HR expressed as a percentage of HR max is more representative of exercise intensity than the absolute HR value ( Gilman and Wells 1993;Londeree et al. 1995). Furthermore, when expressed as a percentage of HR reserve , i.e. HR max-HR rest , the HR was closely related to VO 2 in continuous exercise (Gilman 1996). It has recently been shown that even if the exercise pattern is intermittent, in long aerobic exercise such as tennis, HR time course is similar to that of VO 2 ( Dansou et al. 2001). The present results show that the subjects sailed with HRs representing <measure type="list"><num>80.5</num> and <num>76.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>HR max in LW and MW, respectively. This is slightly lower than values reported by Gue´vel Gue´vel et al. (1999), namely <measure type="list"><num>87.4</num> and <num>82.9</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>HRmax, respectively. This may not be due to race duration, as HR was not correlated to race duration in either study. De Vito et al. (1997) have reported even higher values representing about <measure type="value"><num>92</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> HR max , but these values were measured over short periods of time in a race simulation. The slightly lower %HR max values observed in the present study may not be explained by the presence of a female windsurfer in the group, as De Vito et al. (1997) and Vogiatzis et al. (2002) have shown similar %HR max in male and female athletes when pumping. A possible cause of the lower relative HRs could be due to the pumping pattern of the studied subjects. Gue´vel Gue´vel et al. (2000) have shown that <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> periods of <measure type="value"><num>6</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="min">minutes</measure></measure> simulated pumping with <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> frequencies (<measure type="list"><num>1.5</num> vs. <num>1</num> <measure type="FREQUENCY" unit="Hz">Hz</measure></measure>) with the same energy expenditure, resulted in a cardiac response representing <measure type="list"><num>77.1</num> and <num>80.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>HRmax respectively. The time to exhaustion (in a separate test) was <measure type="value"><num>threefold</num></measure> longer for the short and frequent pumping with respect to the high amplitude one. It is then possible that the present study subjects used more the short pumping than the subjects of Gue´vel Gue´vel et al. (1999). It has been reported that if high magnitude pumping is more strenuous, it is more effective at increasing board speed (Gue´velGue´vel et al. 2000). Lastly, an experimental difference could have caused the observed discrepancies in racing intensity, as Gue´vel Gue´vel et al. (1999) only analysed the first race of each competition day. The present study analysed all the races sailed for a given day, which corresponded to <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="2">two</num> to <num atMost="3">three</num></measure> races a day with <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="15">15</num>-<num atMost="20">20</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> of recovery in between. Fig. 1 Linear regression between racing heart rate (%HR reserve ) and racing classification points in light wind (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num>-<num atMost="9">9</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure>, n=<measure type="value"><num>61</num></measure>) Fig. 2 Linear regression between racing heart rate (%HR reserve ) and racing classification points in medium wind (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">10</num>-<num atMost="16">16</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure>, n=<measure type="value"><num>82</num></measure>)</p>
		<p>The cumulative effect of fatigue could have lowered sailing intensity for the second and third races of the day with respect to the first.</p>
		<p>Despite its complex metabolism, lactate is thought to be a relevant indicator of anaerobic glycolysis during exercise (Brooks 1991). The post-racing lactate measured in the present study was similar to values reported by Chardigny et al. (1990), Gue´velGue´vel et al. (1999 and De Vito et al. (1997) and confirms that Olympic windsurfing racing involves anaerobic metabolism. De Vito et al. (1997) have suggested that anaerobic conditions are related mostly to pumping. The present study's values may have been slightly underestimated, as the samples were taken from an earlobe whereas Gue´vel Gue´vel et al. (1999) and De Vito et al. (1997) took blood from the fingertip. Indeed, Dassonville et al. (1998) have shown that fingertip post-exercise lactate values are significantly higher than earlobe values if the arms are involved in the exercise. Lastly, Gue´vel Gue´vel et al. (1999) have clearly shown that the HR is significantly higher in the first half of the race than the second, probably for strategic purposes. Indeed, it seems that the athletes fight hard in the first half of the race to take a position as close as possible to the lead, and then the second part of the race serves to consolidate the windsurfer's position by a somewhat defensive attitude (Gue´velGue´vel et al. 1999). This could have led to a further underestimate of the involvement of anaerobic metabolism. Indeed, no study has stopped a race at the end of the first half to measure blood lactate.</p>
		<p>The exercise HR increases could be due to: (1) the exercise intensity per se and/or (2) to the type of muscle contractions. Indeed, De Vito et al. (1997) have noted that windsurfing is a mix of dynamic (e.g. arms, thighs) and static (e.g. trunk and forearms) contractions. Furthermore, the effect of the raised upper arms on the HR increase has to be considered (De Vito et al. 1997). As the races lasted for more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure> it is possible that cardiac drift also influenced the averaged HR values (Gilman 1996).</p>
		<p>With respect to the relationship between sailing HRs and laboratory variables, there was a negative correlation between individual maximal sailing HR expressed as a percentage of HR reserve and the second ventilatory threshold expressed as a percentage of VO 2max . Billat and Koralsztein (1996) have reported that the second ventilatory threshold is a good indicator of aerobic power. One explanation for the observed negative correlation could be that subjects with lower thresholds have to make a greater relative effort than the fitter ones to generate similar work, resulting in a higher HR. In that case, it is possible that the fittest athletes were often sailing under or just at the level of their respective anaerobic threshold leading to a relatively moderate HR (De Vito et al. 1997). It is possible that the athletes with good aerobic power need only to make a relatively low effort during races against athletes with poorer fitness levels. The present results confirm that Olympic windsurfing is an endurance activity in which physiological variables have an important bearing on performance (De Vito et al. 1997). Indeed it has been reported that, depending on the part of the race, Olympic windsurfing can be compared to a <measure type="value"><num>2000</num>-<measure type="LENGTH" unit="m">m</measure></measure> rowing event (i.e. <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="90">90</num>-<num atMost="95">95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> HR max for about <measure type="value"><num>6.5</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="min">min</measure></measure>) for the downwind leg and to what has been defined as the ''efficient active recovery stage'' of cycling and swimming (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="75">75</num>-<num atMost="80">80</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> HR max ) for the upwind leg (Gue´velGue´vel et al. 2000).</p>
		<p>To summarize, the present study showed that Olympic windsurfing performance depends upon the level of active involvement of each athlete during a race, indeed light and medium racing performances were correlated to the sailing HR, i.e. exercise intensity. These results reinforce the findings of former studies showing that from the moment ''pumping'' was allowed in international windsurfing events, racing intensity has increased. From <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num> to <num atMost="16">16</num> <measure type="VELOCITY" unit="knot">knots</measure></measure>, a windsurfer's performance is greatly dependent on their ability to maintain continuous pumping, resulting in high heart rates. Windsurfing athletes and coaches should consider these findings when planning their physical training programs.</p>
	</text>
</tei>