<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>name to generic substitution of antiepileptic drugs does not lead to seizure-related hospitalization: a population-based case-crossover study. HAL is a multidisciplinary open access archive for the deposit and dissemination of scientific research documents, whether they are published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt etàetà la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, ´ emanant desétablissementsdesétablissements d'enseignement et de recherche français oú etrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés. 1 Brand name to generic substitution of antiepileptic drugs does not lead to seizure-related hospitalization: A population-based case-crossover study. Key points:  There is still controversy on generic substitution in general, and specifically for antiepileptic drugs.  We examined whether brand-to-generic antiepileptic drug substitution was associated with seizure-related hospitalization.  With a narrow confidence interval, our results allow exclusion of a relevant association between brand-to-generic substitution and seizure-related hospitalization, in well-controlled, seizure-free patients.  These findings may contribute to restoring confidence in generic antiepileptic drug formulations and more generally it might be reassuring for generic utilization, especially in stable patients with chronic disease. Sponsor and grant number: French Health Ministry (PHRC-2011) The authors declared no conflict of interest. Word count: <measure type="value"><num>2967</num></measure> Prior presentations: EACPT Geneva, <measure type="value"><date when="2013-08">August 2013</date></measure> (preliminary results) <!-- 2 --> ABSTRACT (Word count: <measure type="value"><num>232/250</num></measure>) Purpose: There is still controversy on brand name to generic (B-G) antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) substitution. Methods: To assess association between brand-to-generic (B-G) antiepileptic drug (AED) substitution and seizure-related hospitalization, we designed a case crossover using the French National Health Insurance Database. We identified a cohort of adult patients who filled a prescription in <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2009">2009</date>-<date to-iso="2011">2011</date></measure> for AEDs with at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> brand name and <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> generic form. The outcome date was defined as the date of hospitalization, coded G40.x or G41.x, with a G40/G41 hospitalization-free period of at least <measure type="value"><num>one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure>. Patients with a medical history of cancer and women who gave birth in <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2009">2009</date>-<date to-iso="2011">2011</date></measure> were excluded. We required individuals to have regular dispensations of AEDs within the year preceding the outcome date. Free patients were defined as patients who had only brand-name dispensations before the control period. Results: <measure type="value"><num>8,379</num></measure> patients (mean age ± SD, <measure type="interval"><num type="base">52.7</num> ± <num type="range">18.8</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>; sex ratio male/female, <measure type="value"><num>1.27</num></measure>) were analyzed. Discordant pairs were <measure type="list"><num>491</num> with B-G substitution in the control period only and <num>478</num></measure> with B-G substitution in the case period only; OR (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>CI) <measure type="value"><num>0.97</num></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.86">0.86</num>-<num atMost="1.10">1.10</num></measure>). No statistically significant interaction was detected among the <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> pre-specified subgroup analyses (gender, age strata, free or non-free and strict AED monotherapy or not). Controlling for non-seizure-related hospitalizations made no material difference. Sensitivity analyses yielded similar results. Conclusions: B-G AED substitution was not associated with an elevated risk of seizure-related hospitalization. <!-- 3 --></p>
		<p>Generic drugs have been developed to control healthcare costs.</p>
		<p>There are conflicting viewpoints regarding generic substitution, particularly towards antiepileptic drugs (AEDs). Potential difference in therapeutic response between bioequivalent products remains a concern, especially for older AEDs with a narrow therapeutic index (NTI) but also for newer, non-NTI AEDs <!-- [1][2][3] --> . Clinicians worry about possible therapy failure, especially in controlled patients, as even a single breakthrough seizure may have severe consequences such as loss of driving license, of employment or injuries <!-- 4 --> .</p>
		<p>Some US states and European countries recommend limiting the substitution of generic AEDs, the American Academy of Neurology opposing antiepileptic generic substitution without physician approval <!-- 1,[5][6][7] --> . It is also not recommended to switch AEDs in seizure-free patients <!-- 4 --> .</p>
		<p>Some studies argued for the association between generic substitution and a risk of breakthrough seizures: opinion studies among clinicians and patients <!-- 1,[8][9][10][11] --> , observational cohort <!-- [12][13][14][15] --> or case-control studies <!-- [16][17][18] --> . These studies present several methodological limits and most of them were sponsored by brand medication manufacturers. In contrast, studies argued for a lack of association between generic substitution and a risk of seizure: meta-analysis of clinical trials, but included few patients and were underpowered to detect true clinical differences <!-- 19 --> , observational cohort , <!-- 21 --> , case-control <!-- 22,2023 --> and case-crossover studies <!-- 24,25 --> . The study of Gagne et al <!-- 23 --> hypothesized that refilling a prescription for the same manufacturer's AED might itself be associated with risk of seizure-related events, due to confounders. The odds ratio (OR) was <measure type="value"><num>2.75</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CI <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.88">0.88</num>-<num atMost="8.64">8.64</num></measure>) for refills that involved switching, yielding a refill-adjusted OR for switching of <measure type="value"><num>1.19</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CI <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.35">0.35</num>-<num atMost="3.99">3.99</num></measure>).</p>
		<p>All these studies did not provide a definite answer about the impact of brand-togeneric substitution on controlled epilepsy patients, especially for valproic acid, carbamazepine and lamotrigine, which are not extensively studied in the case-control studies. The aim of the GENEPI study ('GENeric substitution of antiEPIleptic drugs') was to further assess the association between seizure-related hospitalization and generic substitution and provide the necessary evidence to inform clinician and patient decisions.</p>
		<p>We used data from the French national health insurance system (Système National [DE-2012-111]).</p>
		<p>We used a case-crossover design <!-- [26][27][28] --> . We arbitrarily chose a <measure type="value"><num>3</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> induction period and a <measure type="value"><num>3</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="month">month</measure></measure> exposure window (i.e. "case period") for primary analyses. The control period was then defined as the <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> immediately preceding the case period in primary analyses.</p>
		<p>We used data from all adult patients affiliated to the French national health insurance scheme, aged <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="18">18</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> or more on <measure type="value"><date when="2009-01">January 2009</date></measure>, who had at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> reimbursement between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2009">2009</date> and <date to-iso="2011">2011</date></measure> for at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> of the following AEDs: carbamazepine, lamotrigine, levetiracetam, topiramate, or valproic acid, referred to as selected AEDs. These drugs had a brand name and at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> "A-rated" generic form available on the French market by this time (<measure type="list"><date when="2009">2009</date>)(<date when="2010">2010</date>)(<date when="2011">2011</date></measure>) and were widely prescribed for epilepsy, allowing identification of epilepsy patients. They were extracted from the SNIIR-AM databases using anatomical therapeutic chemical (ATC) classification codes (N03AF01, N03AX09, N03AX14, N03AX11 or N03AG01).</p>
		<p>Targeted AEDs, i.e. AEDs with at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> generic form available on the French market, were defined as the above selected AEDs plus oxcarbazepine (N03AF02) which is mostly used in combination.</p>
		<p>Patients with a medical history of cancer (all ICD-10 codes for cancer with LTD) and women who gave birth (hospitalization with ICD-10 codes O80-O84) within the study period were excluded because of the high risk of repeated seizures as well as patients receiving fatty acid derivatives through formulations registered as moodstabilizing drugs such as valpromide (DEPAMIDE) or divalproex sodium (DEPAKOTE) who may be not epilepsy patients.</p>
		<p>Cases were identified, using the PMSI database, as individuals with a seizure-related hospitalization between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2010-01">January 2010</date> and <date to-iso="2011-12">December 2011</date></measure>. We used ICD-10 codes G40.x (epilepsy) or G41.x (status epilepticus) as codes of interest in primary or secondary hospital discharge diagnosis position. The index event date was defined as the date of occurrence in the PMSI database of one of the abovementioned codes of interest with an hospitalization-free (for ICD-10 G40.x or G41.x) period of at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure> preceding the index event date (controlled epilepsy patients). We further required individuals to have regular dispensations of the same product for each targeted AED within the year preceding the index event date; this was defined as the dispensation of products having the same International Non-proprietary Name (INN) at the same strength per unit with the same number of units per box and the same dosage form. Regular dispensation (a proxy for medication adherence) was defined as at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="10">ten</num></measure> dispensation claims within a year, keeping in mind that those dispensations are on a monthly basis in France. Thus, we excluded events that occurred in <measure type="value"><date when="2009">2009</date></measure> to ensure that exposure and hospitalization data were available for the <measure type="value"><num>365</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> prior to the index date for each case.</p>
		<p>A generic substitution (switch from brand to generic) was defined as a dispensation of a generic drug that was preceded by a dispensation of a product having the same INN at the same strength per unit with the same number of units per pack and the same dosage form but corresponding to the brand-name counterpart. Of note, in Substitution was first considered as any substitution of at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> targeted AED.</p>
		<p>Due to the late availability on the French market of levetiracetam generic form (August, 2011), we excluded patients who switched before the index date from the levetiracetam brand to the generic. Substitution was then classified into <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> groups: narrow therapeutic index (carbamazepine and valproic acid) or not (lamotrigine, oxcarbazepine, topiramate). AED-free patients were defined as patients who had only targeted AED brand name dispensations before the control period; which means no prior exposure to AED generics before the control period. Conversely, patients who had at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> dispensation of the generic drug before control period were defined as AED non-free patients.</p>
		<p>Strict monotherapy was defined as dispensations of only <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> targeted AED and without any concurrent use of other AEDs during the year preceding the index event date. These other (non-targeted) AEDs were as follows: barbiturates, benzodiazepines (clonazepam, clobazam, diazepam), phenytoin, GABA analogs (gabapentin, pregabalin). No generic formulation of these drugs was available in the French market (e.g. phenytoin) or they were not specifically dedicated to epilepsy treatment (e.g. gabapentin). They were identified by their CIP number.</p>
		<p>We defined psychiatric disease based on selected ICD-10 codes justifying LTD inscription for psychiatric disorder (LTD 23). We also collected the occurrence of hospitalizations not related to seizure during both control and case periods.</p>
		<p>Data were analyzed using standard methods for matched case-crossover data. Odds ratios (ORs) and <measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> confidence intervals (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CIs) for seizure-related hospitalizations were estimated using conditional logistic regression models.</p>
		<p>We introduced an interaction term between switch occurrence and user profile (AEDfree patient or not), strict monotherapy or not, age strata, or gender. Age strata were defined according to first and third quartiles. Statistical models were first built without any adjustment and then with adjustment for non-seizure-related hospitalizations during case and control periods. All analyses were conducted using the SAS statistical package (version 9.3; SAS Institute, Cary, N.C., USA).</p>
		<p>We reduced case and control periods to <measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> and we tested <measure type="value"><num>1</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>5</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> induction periods. Analyses were also performed for B-G substitution of any targeted AEDs or narrow therapeutic index AEDs (carbamazepine and valproic acid).</p>
		<p>A total of <measure type="value"><num>812,314</num></measure> adults with at least one reimbursement between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2009">2009</date> and <date to-iso="2011">2011</date></measure> for one of the selected AEDs, were identified in the SNIIRAM, of whom <measure type="value"><num>132,927</num></measure> were excluded because they had a diagnosis of cancer or had been pregnant or had received fatty acid derivatives through formulations registered as mood-stabilizing drugs (Figure 1)</p>
		<p><measure type="value"><num>8,379</num></measure> patients [median age (quartiles) <measure type="value"><num>52</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num>-<num atMost="69">69</num></measure>); sex ratio male/female, <measure type="value"><num>1.27</num></measure>] were included in the primary analysis (Tables 1 and 2). Table 1 There were <measure type="value"><num>969</num></measure> discordant pairs: <measure type="list"><num>491</num> with B-G substitution in the control period but not in the case period, and <num>478</num></measure> with B-G substitution in the case period but not in the control period: odds ratio <measure type="value"><num>0.97</num></measure> (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> CI: <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.86">0.86</num>-<num atMost="1.10">1.10</num></measure>). Results were consistent across the different AEDs (Table 3). A post-hoc power analysis showed that <measure type="value"><num>969</num></measure> discordant pairs provided <measure type="value"><num>93</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> power at the <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> level of significance to detect an odds ratio of <measure type="value"><num>1.25</num></measure>.</p>
		<p>No statistically significant interaction was detected among the <measure type="value"><num>four</num></measure> pre-specified subgroup analyses (Table 4). The p value was equal to <measure type="value"><num>0.11</num></measure> for the interaction term between substitution and free/non-free status: OR (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>CI) <measure type="value"><num>1.20</num></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.90">0.90</num>-<num atMost="1.61">1.61</num></measure>) for free patients and <measure type="value"><num>0.93</num></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="0.81">0.81</num>-<num atMost="1.07">1.07</num></measure>) for non-free patients. Non-free patients had a mean ± SD number of B-G AED substitution within the <measure type="value"><num>6</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> prior to the control period of <measure type="interval"><num type="base">0.95</num> ± <num type="range">1.36</num></measure>, which remains a rare event. In addition, substitution was evenly distributed in the <measure type="value"><num>6</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="month">month</measure></measure>, case-control period.</p>
		<p>Less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="25">25</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of patients had a non-seizure related hospitalization in the <measure type="value"><num>6</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="month">month</measure></measure>, case-control period: <measure type="value"><num>22.4</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in free patients and <measure type="value"><num>24.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> in non-free patients. When we considered a non-seizure-related hospitalization as an exposure, the OR (<measure type="value"><num>95</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>CI) was <measure type="list"><num>1.30</num></measure> (<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1.18">1.18</num>-<num atMost="1.44">1.44</num></measure>), p &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.0001">0.0001</num></measure>. Controlling for this covariate made no material difference to the effect estimates for B-G AED substitution (Table 4).</p>
		<p>Sensitivity analyses yielded results similar to primary analysis (Table 4 and Table 5).</p>
		<p>Based on the largest set of data to date, our findings support the absence of association between brand-to-generic antiepileptic drug substitution and the risk of seizure-related hospitalization for AEDs with or without a narrow therapeutic index in the target population for clinicians (i.e. seizure-free patients, controlled by a stable treatment). This result supports that the bioequivalence between generics and their branded counterparts means clinical equivalence and is consistent with the bioequivalence requirements established by the Food and Drug Administration (identical to those of the European Medicines Agency) which are intended to ensure that differences in bioavailability between generics and their brand-name counterparts are not greater than between-lot variations from a single manufacturer <!-- 23,29 --> .</p>
		<p>By seeking an association in patients receiving stable therapy who had been seizurefree for at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="year">year</measure></measure>, this provides the best possible conditions to assess the impact of substitution on the clinical state of patients. Patients for whom loss of seizure control has the most serious medical and social consequences (e.g. injury, loss of driving license, loss of employment…) are stable patients. In our study, the eligibility of seizure-free patients is warranted by the absence of any G40/G41 ICD-10 codes within the year preceding the index date and by continuous brand or generic use, resulting in only adherent patients being captured. Indeed, non adherence has been shown to be associated with increased seizure risk and a significantly higher incidence of hospitalization <!-- 20 -->. Furthermore, the number of AEDs dispensed is a strong predictor of seizure-related events <!-- 24 --> and multiple AEDs are generally reserved for patients with more severe forms of epilepsy, thus making multiple AEDs a potential proxy for disease severity <!-- 22 --> . Yet at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="40">40</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of patients in our study sample were on strict AED monotherapy, mainly valproic acid. In a previous study <!-- 30 --> , it was reported that AED monotherapy was the rule in stable epilepsy patients. The fact that the association remains non-significant in stable patients following strict monotherapy gives the result even more value.</p>
		<p>An individual's risk for epilepsy exacerbations may increase with co-morbidities <!-- 22 --> , which is confirmed when we considered a non-seizure-related hospitalization as an exposure. However, our results are unchanged when controlling for this covariate.</p>
		<p>In the study of Zachry et al <!-- 16 --> , the percentage of patients experiencing a switch in the case group was highest in the <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> prior to the index event (emergent epilepsy-related care) whereas this percentage in the control group was highest only in the first month prior to the index event, with no discernible pattern thereafter. In our study, the switches were evenly distributed throughout the case and control periods and sensitivity analyses, by varying the duration of the case and control periods and the induction period, confirming the robustness of the results.</p>
		<p>It is of note that the analysis based on the <measure type="value"><num>28</num>-<measure type="TIME" unit="day">day</measure></measure> case and control period gave consistent results but a less precise estimation.</p>
		<p>As regards confounding the advantage of the case-crossover method is that the influence of factors that vary among the participants, such as fixed between-person confounders, is removed. Previous studies <!-- [16][17][18] --> which found an association between A-rated formulations of AEDs and an increased risk of inpatient/emergency epilepsy care were limited by confounding on account of the severity of epilepsy. Using a short study period, confounding by time-varying factors is thought to be limited or unlikely. As regards selection bias, the completeness of the SNIIR-AM files narrowed concerns about external generalizability.</p>
		<p>We also have to consider ICD code accuracy and misclassification bias. However, these should be limited, given that most instances of seizures are readily evident for healthcare providers. Other users of AEDs for conditions such as bipolar disorder, neuropathic pain or migraine may also have been included in our study population (i.e. <measure type="value"><num>24</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of our patients have a previous psychiatric diagnosis). Nevertheless, AEDs indicated for diseases other than epilepsy were not selected, such as gabapentin.</p>
		<p>Moreover, studies have shown that the use of a combination of diagnosis codes and pharmacy claims of AEDs can correctly classify <measure type="value"><num>90</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> of epilepsy cases <!-- 31 --> and the most accurate algorithm to identify epilepsy cases in administrative health data is IDC-10 codes G40/G41 32 .</p>
		<p>The relevance of the choice of our outcome should be discussed: it is a highly specific outcome, which does not allow generalization of our results, because not all patients with breakthrough seizures are hospitalized, some of them could be managed in an outpatient setting <!-- 16,17,24 --> . These results are only applicable to serious exacerbations of epilepsy, as claims databases capture only the most serious events <!-- 17,21 --> . However we assume, as other researchers, that stable patients experiencing unexpected breakthrough seizures are likely to seek care in emergency and inpatient settings more often than in ambulatory settings <!-- [16][17][18] --> .</p>
		<p>Switches are usually characterized as one of <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> types: brand to generic, generic to brand or generic to generic <!-- 16,17,24 --> . As many healthcare providers focus on problems related to brand-to-generic switching, our survey has studied this type of switch, but the results could not be extended to switches among different generic formulations.</p>
		<p>Results were consistent across all targeted AEDs, either NTI AEDs or non-NTI AEDs, which is reassuring for the use of valproic acid or carbamazepine generic formulations. Nevertheless, no conclusion for phenytoin, another NTI AED, could be drawn because no generic formulation of phenytoin is marketed in France.</p>
		<p>Previous studies suggested that switching AED medication may result in adverse events although the differences could be attributable to confounders which were not well accounted for. Our results allow exclusion of an association between a brand-togeneric substitution and seizure-related hospitalization, in well-controlled, seizurefree patients. These findings may restore confidence in AED generic formulations, keeping in mind that substitution should not be performed without physician and patient agreement. AED-free patients were defined as patients who had only targeted AED brand name dispensations before the control period; which means no prior exposure to AED generics before the control period. Conversely, patients who had at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> dispensation of the generic drug before control period were defined as AED non-free patients. Presence of previous psychiatric diagnosis is based on inscription in long-term disease (LTD) with an ICD-10 code corresponding to a psychiatric disorder Targeted anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs), i.e. AEDs with at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> available generic form on the French market, were: carbamazepine, lamotrigine, levetiracetam, oxcarbazepine, topiramate and valproic acid. Strict monotherapy was defined as dispensations of only <measure type="value"><num>one</num></measure> targeted AED without any concurrent use of other AEDs during the year preceding the index event date. These other (not targeted) AEDs were the following: barbiturates, benzodiazepines (clonazepam, clobazam, diazepam), hydantoins, GABA analogs (gabapentin, pregabalin). They were identified by their CIP number. They belong to the following ATC classes: N03AA, N03AB, N03AD, N03AE, N05BA09, N05BA01, N03AF03, N03AF04, N03AG04, N03AG05, N03AG06, N03AX12, N03AX15, N03AX16, N03AX17 and N03AX18. AED-free patients were defined as patients who had only targeted AED brand name dispensations before the control period; which means no prior exposure to AED generics before the control period. Conversely, patients who had at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> dispensation of the generic drug before control period were defined as AED non-free patients. P values are for homogeneity testing; AED-free patients were defined as patients who had only targeted AED brand name dispensations before the control period; which means no prior exposure to AED generics before the control period. Conversely, patients who had at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> dispensation of the generic drug before control period were defined as AED non-free patients. P values are for homogeneity testing; AED-free patients were defined as patients who had only targeted AED brand name dispensations before the control period; which means no prior exposure to AED generics before the control period. Conversely, patients who had at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">one</num></measure> dispensation of the generic drug before control period were defined as AED non-free patients.</p>
		<p>The authors are grateful to the CNAM-TS (National Health Insurance Organization) for providing SNIIRAM data and assistance.</p>
		<p>E.P, E.N, E.O. wrote the manuscript. E.O. designed the research. E.P, E.N, A.H., and E.O. performed the research. E.P, E.N, A.H., A.B., and E.O. analyzed the data.</p>
	</text>
</tei>