<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>The high-volume fly ash concrete (HVFAC) system has emerged as a future powerful concrete system that would be far more durable and resource-efficient than those made of conventional Portland cement concrete. As the Portland cement industry is responsible for approximately <measure type="value"><num>7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> of the world's carbon dioxide emission, Malhotra et al. <!-- [1] --> proposed that the fly ash content must be above <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> by mass of total cementitious for making a concrete for sustainable development They also proposed that for concrete mixture with specified <measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> compressive strength of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="30">30</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure></measure> or higher, slumps &gt;<measure type="interval"><num atLeast="150">150</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>, and water-to-cementitious materials ratio of the order of <measure type="value"><num>0.30</num></measure>, the use of highrange superplasticizers is mandatory. For concrete mixture with slumps less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="150">150</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure> and <measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> compressive strength of less than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="30">30</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure></measure>, high fly ash concrete mixture with a water-to-cementitious material ratio of the order of <measure type="value"><num>0.4</num></measure> may be used without superplasticizers. The Confederation of Indian Industry; centre of excellence for sustainable development <!-- [2] --> proposed that for obtaining a superior performance of HVFAC, the water-to-cementitious ratio should be bellow <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.4">0.4</num></measure> and preferably ≤ <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.35">0.35</num></measure> .The use of superplasticizer is most of the time essential.</p>
		<p>Vargas and José A.</p>
		<p>[3] defined a HVFAC as a concrete in which at least <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> by weight or mass of the cementitious material content is the fly ash. The applications (such as foundations) where strengths of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="21">21</num> to <num atMost="28">28</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure></measure> are acceptable and high early strength is not required may be produced without special admixtures. Compared to the conventional Portland concrete, the HVFAC has some qualities: lower cost, very high environmental benefits (reduced CO 2 ), easier flowability and workability, negligible bleeding, quicker finishing, higher ultimate strength up to <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure>, higher crack resistance, very higher resistance to penetration of chloride ions after <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure> and very higher electrical resistivity after <measure type="value"><num>3</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="month">months</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>About the volume the emissions of greenhouse gases which can be reduced, Ehrenberg and Geisler <!-- [4] --> wrote that the replacement of <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="ton">ton</measure></measure> of Portland cement by the fly ash reduces the overall CO 2 emissions by approximately <measure type="value"><num>1</num> <measure type="MASS" unit="ton">ton</measure></measure>. Langley et al. <!-- [5] --> specified that another benefit of using fly ash in concrete is that fly ash makes beautiful architectural concrete because its light in color and its extreme workability ensures smoother finishes. In addition, fly ash in plaster virtually eliminates defects like crazing, map cracking, drying shrinkage cracks, grinning, expansion and popping.</p>
		<p>With the aim to contribute to the study of the compressive and flexural loading resistance for a considerable volume fly ash concrete, a total of <measure type="value"><num>144</num></measure> samples were made in the concrete laboratory (<measure type="list"><num>72</num> for compressive test and <num>72</num></measure> for flexural test).</p>
		<p>The materials used were composed by the cementitious, aggregates, superplasticizer and pure water. The chemical properties of the cementitious used are shown in the Table 2-1.</p>
		<p>The specific surface of the cement used is <measure type="value"><num>310</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="m^2/kg">m 2 /kg</measure></measure> while the fly ash fineness (<measure type="value"><num>80</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="µm">µm</measure></measure> residue on sieve) is <measure type="value"><num>24</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. The mechanical properties of aggregates used are shown below in Table 22. Some chemical properties for the superplasticizer used: Na2SO4:<measure type="value"><num>10.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>; Solid Content: <measure type="value"><num>50</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>; Chlorine ion: <measure type="value"><num>0.01</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>; <measure type="interval"><measure type="ACIDITY" unit="pH">PH</measure>: <num atLeast="6.5">6.5</num>-<num atMost="8.5">8.5</num></measure>; Fluidity: E<measure type="value"><num>250</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>; Density: <measure type="value"><num>1.08</num><measure type="DENSITY" unit="g/cm3">g/cm 3</measure></measure></p>
		<p>The methods used for making the fly ash concrete were based on materials proportioning system according to the percent of the cementitious contents. The Table 3-1 and the Table 32 show respectively our proposition for materials proportioning and the volume of materials. For compressive samples the moulds size is <measure type="value"><num>150</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm^3">mm cubic</measure></measure> while for flexural samples the size is <measure type="list"><num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure> x <num>100</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure> x <num>400</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>The concrete-mixer used could mix at once concrete whose volume is the total volume of <measure type="list"><num>6</num> samples for compressive test and <num>6</num></measure> samples for flexural test. The slump test was done for each fresh concrete and the measure was ranged between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="120">120</num> and <num atMost="180">180</num><measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>. For making the concrete more compact and homogeneous, a vibrating table was used.</p>
		<p>Compressive strength is the capacity of a material to withstand axially directed pushing forces. When the limit of compressive strength is reached, materials are crushed. The cubic concrete specimen is placed on the platform of compression testing machine without any packing between the cube and the steel platens of the testing machine. The load is then applied on a smooth surface on the cube steadily and uniform starting from <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure> at a rate of <measure type="value"><num>35</num> <measure type="UNKNOWN" unit="N/mm^2/min">N/mm 2 /min</measure></measure> till the cube fails.</p>
		<p>The flexural test is one measure of the tensile strength of concrete. It is a measure of an unreinforced concrete to resist failure in bending. The specimen is placed symmetrically on the load-applying and support blocks. In the present test, the distance between the support-block axis and the extremity of the specimen is <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="mm">mm</measure></measure>. The load is then rapidly applied until approximately <measure type="value"><num>50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> of the breaking load has been reached.</p>
		<p>For <measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> fly ash concrete, with water-to-cementitious ratio equal to <measure type="value"><num>0.39</num></measure> and gravel-to-sand ratio equal to <measure type="value"><num>2.12</num></measure>, by using superplasticizer product, the experimental results showed that the high-performance compressive strengths of the fly ash concrete were <measure type="list"><num>30.9</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure>; <num>29.7</num><measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure> and <num>26.2</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure></measure> respectively for , <measure type="list"><num>30</num><num>40</num><!--space character missing--> and <num>50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> of fly ash in cementitious materials.</p>
		<p>For flexural test results, the high-performance of <measure type="value"><num>28</num> <measure type="TIME" unit="day">days</measure></measure> fly ash concrete were <measure type="list"><num>5.1</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure>, <num>4</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure> and <num>3.9</num> <measure type="PRESSURE" unit="MPa">MPa</measure></measure> respectively for <measure type="list"><num>30</num>; <num>40</num> and <num>50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> of fly ash in cementitious materials. The water-to-cementitious ratio and the gravel-to-sand ratio were <measure type="list"><num>0.46</num> and <num>2.12</num></measure> for <measure type="value"><num>30</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> while they were <measure type="list"><num>0.39</num> and  for <num>2.12</num></measure><measure type="list"><num>40</num> and <num>50</num> <measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">percent</measure></measure> of fly ash in cementitious materials.</p>
		<p>The superplasticizer used played a big part in concrete strengthening comparatively to the concrete samples made without the product.</p>
		<p>By analyzing the charts (</p>
		<p>In addition to the environmental protection benefits by reducing the volume of the greenhouse gases emissions, the use of fly ash in the construction domain contributes also to the reduction of the cementitious cost because the fly ash is cheaper compared to the cement. For developing countries, the economic factor is very important especially for designing concrete structures where; in many cases; structure loading forces are not higher. The present study may inspire the actors in the construction domain by choosing appropriate percentage of the fly ash to use in cementitious materials according to the pre-established limits of structure loading.</p>
		<p><!-- [2] --> Confederation of Indian Industry</p>
		<p>The author would like to sincerely thank all those who contributed to the laboratory facilities for making and testing the fly ash samples.</p>
	</text>
</tei>