<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1" />
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Background: Recent findings showed that elite Ironman triathletes competing in 'Ironman Hawaii' improved both split and overall race times. The present study investigated whether elite athletes also improved in transition time (i.e. time needed between disciplines for changing clothes and equipment).</p>
		<p>Triathlon is a sport consisting of sequential swimming, cycling and running <!-- [1] -->. Triathlon races are mainly held on the short or Olympic distance (i.e. <measure type="value"><num>1.5</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swimming, <measure type="value"><num>40</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycling, and <measure type="value"><num>10</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running) <!-- [2] --> and the long distance, the Ironman distance (i.e. <measure type="value"><num>3.8</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swimming, <measure type="value"><num>180</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycling, and <measure type="value"><num>42.2</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running) <!-- [3] -->. Apart from these distances, also the sprint distance <!-- [4] --> and the <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> Ironman distance 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' <!-- [5] --> are of high popularity.</p>
		<p>As one of the toughest and oldest long-distance triathlons in the world, the 'Ironman Hawaii' now serves as the World Championship for Ironman distance triathletes' <!-- [6] -->. It has been recently shown that the annual top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> finishers have improved split and overall race times between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1983">1983</date> and <date to-iso="2012">2012</date></measure>, whilst also becoming older <!-- [7] -->. During the same period, the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest women and men improved their swimming (only men), cycling, running, and overall race times <!-- [8] -->. In addition, the sex difference in overall race time decreased significantly from <measure type="value"><num>15.2</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> to <measure type="value"><num>11.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>. For the split disciplines, the sex difference remained unchanged for swimming (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">12.5</num> ± <num type="range">3.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) and cycling (<measure type="interval"><num type="base">12.5</num> ± <num type="range">2.7</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>) but decreased for running from <measure type="interval"><num type="base">13.5</num> ± <num type="range">8.1</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> to <measure type="interval"><num type="base">7.3</num> ± <num type="range">2.9</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> <!-- [3,8] -->.</p>
		<p>During a triathlon, the triathletes have to change clothes and equipment between the swimming and the cycling part and then again between the cycling and the running part. These transition times between the <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> disciplines are part of the overall race time. As such, a triathlete's ability to negotiate each transition quickly and effectively has been highlighted as an important factor for overall success in the event <!-- [9] -->. However, to our knowledge, no study has previously focused on the changes in the transition times over the <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> in Ironman triathletes. Overall race time could also be substantially improved by a reduction in transition times. Therefore, the purpose of the present study was to investigate the change in transition time in 'Ironman Hawaii' across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Since both female and male triathletes have improved overall race times and split times during the last <measure type="value"><num>three</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure>, we hypothesized that both women and men also improved transition times across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. To investigate a potential difference in transition times between different race distances, we also compared transition times in 'Ironman Hawaii' to transition times in the World Championships 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' covering the <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> distance (<measure type="value"><num>1.9</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swimming, <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycling and <measure type="value"><num>21.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running) of the Ironman distance triathlon.</p>
		<p>All procedures used in the study met were approved by the Institutional Review Board of Kanton St. Gallen, Switzerland with a waiver of the requirement for informed consent of the participants given the fact that the study involved the analysis of publicly available data.</p>
		<p>The data set for this study was obtained from the race website of the 'Ironman World Championship' <!-- [6] -->. All competitors who finished within the top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> in the 'Ironman World Championship' Hawaii between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1998">1998</date> and <date to-iso="2013">2013</date></measure> were analyzed regarding their change in performance, the sex difference in performance and the transition times. Before <measure type="interval"><date to-iso="1998">1998</date></measure>, transition times were not separately recorded in the race results. Therefore, data before <measure type="interval"><date to-iso="1998">1998</date></measure> could not be included into data analysis. To determine the sex difference in performance, overall race times and split times of the annual top and of the annual top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> women and men were taken from the race results of the organizer. Unfortunately, data from [6] do not allow to differentiate the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> transition times (i.e. swimming to cycling and cycling to running) during the whole period <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1998">1998</date><date to-iso="2013">2013</date></measure>. Therefore, absolute transition times were determined in absolute values by calculating the difference between overall race time and split times using the equation overall race times-(swimming times + cycling Table 1 Multi-level regression analyses for change in transition times (i.e. in absolute times and relative in % of overall race times) for the annual fastest and annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> after correction for multiple finishes in 'Ironman Hawaii' times + running times). Relative transition time was expressed as a percentage of overall race times using the equation 100/overall race times × transition times. The sex difference was calculated using the equation (times in women-times in men)/times in men × 100, where the sex difference was calculated for every pair of equally placed athletes (e.g. between female and male winner, between men and women 2 nd place, etc.) before calculating mean value and standard deviation of all pairs. In order to facilitate reading all sex differences were transformed to absolute values before analysing.</p>
		<p>In order to investigate a potential difference in transition times between different triathlon distances, we compared the transition times in 'Ironman Hawaii' to the transition times in the World Championships 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' covering the <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> distance of the Ironman triathlon (i.e. <measure type="value"><num>1.9</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> swimming, <measure type="value"><num>90</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> cycling and <measure type="value"><num>21.1</num> <measure type="LENGTH" unit="km">km</measure></measure> running) <!-- [10] -->.</p>
		<p>Each set of data was tested for normal distribution and for homogeneity of variances prior to statistical analyses. Normal distribution was tested using a D' Agostino and Pearson omnibus normality test and homogeneity of variances was tested using a Levene's test. Single and multilevel regression analyses were used to investigate changes in performance. A hierarchical regression model was used to avoid the impact of a cluster-effect on results in case one athlete finished more than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="1">once</num></measure> in the annual top or annual top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure>. Since the change in sex difference in endurance performance is assumed to be non-linear <!-- [11] -->, we additionally calculated the non-linear regression model that fits the data best. The result of the linear regression analysis was compared to the best-fit result of the non-linear analysis using Akaike's Information Criteria (AIC) and F-test in order to show which model would be the most appropriate to explain the trend of the data. Split times in swimming, cycling, and running as well as overall race times and transition times in top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> women and men and differences in transition times between 'Ironman Hawaii' and 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' in top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> men and women were compared using multiple t-tests with Holm-Sidak correction for multiple comparisons. Statistical analyses were performed using IBM SPSS Statistics (Version 22, IBM SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA) and GraphPad Prism (Version 6.01, GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA, USA).</p>
		<p>Significance was accepted at P &lt; <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.05">0.05</num></measure> (two-sided for ttests). Data in the text and figures are given as mean ± standard deviation (SD).</p>
		<p>Changes in transition times in 'Ironman Hawaii'</p>
		<p>The transition times (Figure 1) remained unchanged across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for the annual fastest women but increased linearly for the annual fastest men in both absolute and relative terms (Table 1). For the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest, the transition times increased linearly for both the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest women and men in both absolute and relative terms. The sex difference in the transition times remained unchanged across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for the annual fastest triathletes, but decreased linearly for the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest triathletes from <measure type="interval"><num type="base">48.0</num> ± <num type="range">47.6</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><date when="1998">1998</date></measure>) to <measure type="interval"><num type="base">18.9</num> ± <num type="range">28.3</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (<measure type="value"><date when="2013">2013</date></measure>). Changes in transition times in 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>'</p>
		<p>In 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' (Figure 2), the transition times remained unchanged for the annual fastest in both absolute and relative terms (Table 2). For the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest, transition times decreased linearly for both women and men in both absolute and relative terms. The sex difference in transition times remained unchanged across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> for both the annual fastest and the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest triathletes.</p>
		<p>Hawaii' and 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>'</p>
		<p>When the changes in transition times across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> between 'Ironman Hawaii' and 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' for the The sex difference in transition times remained unchanged at <measure type="interval"><num type="base">18.4</num> ± <num type="range">11.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> during the whole period.</p>
		<p>Changes in split times, overall race times and sex difference in 'Ironman Hawaii'</p>
		<p>For the annual fastest competitors (Figure 4), swimming split times remained unchanged, cycling split times decreased linearly in men, running split times decreased linearly in women and overall race times decreased linearly in both women and men (Table 3). For the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest ( Figure 5), swimming split times decreased linearly in women, cycling split times, running split times and overall race times decreased linearly in both women and men (Table 3). The sex difference in performance ( Figure 6) decreased linearly in swimming for the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest, in swimming for the annual fastest and the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest and for overall race in the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest (Table 4). For cycling, the sex difference remained unchanged for both the annual fastest and the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest.</p>
		<p>This study investigated the changes in transition times in 'Ironman Hawaii' across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> between <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1998">1998</date> and <date to-iso="2013">2013</date></measure>. It was hypothesized that both elite women and men would improve transition times across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> since they also improved split and overall race times across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. To investigate a potential difference in transition times between different race distances, transition times in 'Ironman Hawaii' were compared to transition times in the World Championships 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' covering the <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> distance of the Ironman triathlon. The main findings were that (i) in 'Ironman Hawaii' , transition times increased in both women and men whereas the sex difference in transition times decreased, (ii) in 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>', transition times decreased in both women and men whereas the sex difference remained unchanged, and (iii), transition times were slower in 'Ironman Hawaii' compared to 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>'.</p>
		<p>In 'Ironman Hawaii' , swimming split times decreased linearly in women, cycling split times, running split times and overall race times decreased linearly in both women and men for the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest. The transition times increased linearly for both the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest women and men in both absolute and relative terms. Generally, elite Ironman triathletes competing in 'Ironman Hawaii' improved performance in both split and overall race times <!-- [3] -->. A recent study investigating the change in performance across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> in elite finishers in 'Ironman Hawaii' from <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="1983">1983</date> to <date to-iso="2012">2012</date></measure> using only linear regression analyses showed similar findings where the annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest women and men improved their swimming (only men), cycling, running, and overall race times <!-- [7] -->.</p>
		<p>The new finding in the present study was that transition times increased across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, although it was hypothesized that transition times would decrease since both women and men improved split and overall race times. A potential explanation for this unexpected finding might be that the transition area has changed across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. The distances between the exit out of the water to the cycling area and the distance between the finish of the cycling to the start of the running might have increased and the athletes might have needed to run longer to change the discipline. A potential change in the transition area could be due to the increasing number of participants in 'Ironman Hawaii' in the last <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. Another explanation could be that the athletes focused Table 3 Multi-level regression analyses for changes in split and overall race times for the annual fastest and annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest women and men across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> after correction for multiple finishes more on the performance in swimming, cycling and running <!-- [12] --> and were not aware that overall race time could also be substantially improved by a reduction in transition times. And a further explanation could be the different time periods investigated in the different studies.</p>
		<p>Differences in transition times between 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' and 'Ironman Hawaii'</p>
		<p>The comparison of the transition times between 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' and 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' showed that transition times decreased in both absolute and relative terms in the shorter race distance 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' whereas in the longer race distance 'Ironman Hawaii' the transition times increased also in both absolute and relative terms. When the transition times were compared between 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' and 'Ironman Hawaii' , athletes changed faster in the shorter race 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' than in the longer race 'Ironman Hawaii'. A potential explanation for this finding could be that the shorter race is faster in both the split and the transition times than the longer race. A further explanation could be that the transition area is smaller in 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' compared to 'Ironman Hawaii' due to the different numbers of participants.</p>
		<p>During the <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, athlete may also have improved their technique to change faster in the transition area <!-- [13][14][15] -->.</p>
		<p>Maybe the athletes are more exhausted in the full Ironman than in the <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> Ironman after a split discipline when they enter the transition area and are therefore slower in the transition in the full Ironman distance compared to the <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> Ironman distance. Other explanations could be different transition areas in the different races and the different location of the races. Apart from changes in the transition area across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>, the World Championship 'Ironman Hawaii' was held during the investigated period at the same place whereas the World Championship 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' was held in <measure type="interval"><date from-iso="2006">2006</date><date to-iso="2010">2010</date></measure>in Clearwater, Florida, USA, and in <measure type="value"><date when="2011">2011</date></measure> in Henderson, Nevada, USA. The <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> different race courts might also have different transition areas.</p>
		<p>A limitation in this study is that the transition area may have changed during this period and therefore the absolute time an athlete spent between <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure> disciplines may have be different from year to year. However, the transition times were expressed here as absolute values and as relative values as a percentage of overall race time. When the transition times changed due to changes of the transition area, overall race time changed accordingly. A further limitation is that transition times between swimming and cycling and between cycling and running were not separated but unfortunately transition times between the disciplines were provided only in recent <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure>. The age of the athletes was not included. It has recently been shown that sex differences in overall race times differed between age groups in sprint, Olympic distance, and <measure type="value"><num>half</num></measure> Ironman triathlon <!-- [16] -->. Since the sex difference in long-distance triathlon increased with increasing race distance <!-- [17] -->, future studies should investigate the sex difference in transition times for different triathlon distances. In addition, the present study focused on elite triathletes only, it would interesting to analyse (i) the sex difference in transition times for age groups triathletes and (ii) the agerelated change in transition times. It is also worth considering in future research what would constitute a practically meaningful change in 'Ironman' and 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' transition times in the context of transition times alone and in relation to overall performance. For example, when the typical within-athlete variability is not available, the average time difference between each of the top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> finishing positions would give an idea of a worthwhile enhancement in performance times, and, more importantly, in transition times.</p>
		<p>In summary, transition times increased for both women and men in 'Ironman Hawaii' whereas the sex difference in transition times decreased. In 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>' , transition times decreased for both women and men whereas the sex difference in transition times remained unchanged. Generally, transition times were slower in 'Ironman Hawaii' compared to 'Ironman <measure type="value"><num>70.3</num></measure>'. Top <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> finishers in 'Ironman Hawaii' might further improve their overall race times by reducing their transition times. Table 4 Multi-level regression analyses for changes in sex difference in split and overall race times for the annual fastest and annual <measure type="value"><num>ten</num></measure> fastest women and men across <measure type="value"><measure type="TIME" unit="year">years</measure></measure> after correction for multiple finishes</p>
		<p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
		<p>Authors' contributions CR performed the statistical analyses and drafted the manuscript, BK collected the data and helped in drafting the manuscript, TR and RL helped in drafting the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
	</text>
</tei>