<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="GROBID" version="0.4.5-dummy" when="2017-08-22T14:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Macromolecules form different kinds of aggregates in aqueous solution. This holds especially for amphiphiles with a hydrophilic and a hydrophobic part. Depending on the molecular structure of the amphiphiles, their concentration and the temperature, these aggregates may be micelles, vesicles, cubic phases, gels or lamellar stacks. Scattering methods like X-ray or neutron small-angle scattering <!-- /I/ -->, dynamic and static light scattering <!-- /2/ --> are widely used to determine the structure of such aggregates. Rheological experiments show the formation of gels indicated by a strong increase of viscosity. Rheological experiments interact strongly with the sample and scattering experiments are rather time consuming and difficult to interpret, especially in the case of higher concentration.</p>
		<p><measure type="value"><num>Two</num></measure> newand complementary methods will be described in the following. The speed of sound waves depends slightly on the number of dissolved particles at fixed mass. Precision experiments using the pulse method can be used to follow micellization in a wide concentration range. Densitometry using the mechanical oscillator method is well established since about <measure type="interval"><num atMost="2">2</num> <measure type="TIME">decades</measure></measure><!--since max 1998 to now--> <!-- /3,4/ -->. A new modified version of this instrument allows the determination of the ratio between the damping force and the elastic force of the oscillator. This method can be used to monitor qualitatively the formation and dissociation of gels as will be shown.</p>
		<p>Triblock Copolymers of the type PEO/PPO/PEO (polyethylene oxide / polypropylene oxide / polyethylene oxide) exist in complex states of aggregation in aqueous solution depending on the relative block sizes. Monomers, micelles and larger aggregates coexist in relative proportions that depend on temperature and concentration. The presently used material (designated Pluronics P-85) has a monomeric molecular weight of <measure type="value"><num>4600</num></measure>(PE02,/PP03,/PE0,,) purified by Serren Hvidt (Roskilde, Denmark) to remove PEO/PPO dimers. This system has allready been studied by dynamic and static light scattering and oscillatory shear measurements <!-- /5/ -->.</p>
		<p>These experiments showed a transition from a mostly monomeric state at low temperatures to a micellar solution at about <measure type="value"><num>2 0</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">&quot; ~</measure></measure><!--OCR problem--> decreasing with concentration. This transition is difficult to measure with increasing concentration by means of scattering techniques due to increasing interparticle interaction. At concentrations higher than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="25">25</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>(W/W) and temperatures of about <measure type="value"><num>35</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">type'C</measure></measure><!--OCR problem--> there is a sharp transition from the micellar phase to a solid-like glass-clear gel. At higher temperatures the gel &quot;dissolves&quot; again. The transitions to and from the gel state are accompanied by extreme changes in viscosity. It will be shown in the following that the formation of micelles can be followed in a wide concentration range by measurements of the speed of sound waves (pulses). The formation of the gel phase can be detected by densitometry with the advantage of negligible energy input into the sample (compared with oscillatory shear experiments).</p>
		<p>The speed of sound wave (SSW) is a function of the adiabatic compressibility and the density of the fluid <!-- /6/ -->. The compressibility of solutions is a function of the tempera-ture and of the solute properties. The speed of sound can be measured with high precision utilizing the pulse mode. The time required for a short pulse (<measure type="values"><num>170</num><measure type="TIME" unit="ns">ns</measure></measure>) to run trough a well defined sample cell (total volume <measure type="value"><num>2</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>) is used to calculate the speed with an accuracy of <measure type="value"><num>+1</num><measure type="VELOCITY" unit="m/s">mjs</measure></measure><!--OCR problem ("j" = "/")-->(DSA 48, Anton Paar K.G. Graz, Austria). The speed of sound at low concentrations is linearly depending on the amount of solute in the solution. In addition there is a further dependence on the number of particles in the solution at fixed concentration. So it is possible to follow the hydrolisis of sucrose into glucose and fructose. This pseudo first<!--not a quantity--> order reaction leads to an exponential decrease of the concentration of sucrose. In a logarithmic plot the data points should fit a straight line. As shown in Fig.1, this inversion can nicely be followed by SSW measurements. This increase of the speed of sound with increasing particle number is the starting point for the micellization studies using SSW experiments, as the number of particles is significantly reduced during micellization. The dependence of the speed on the particle number is very small. We therefore use the specific speed S, of these waves:</p>
		<p>This specific speed S, is the relative change of the speed in the solution SsOwm compared to the speed in water S , , .</p>
		<p>The influence of the temperature on the speed of sound waves in water is eliminated automatically when the specific speed is introduced.</p>
		<p>We want to follow the formation of micelles with increasing temperature. First <!-- not a quantity-->
		of all the specific speed will be reduced by the temperature dependence of the solution. In addition we expect an additional reduction during micellization, as the number of particles in the solution is reduced by this process. Changes can be best visualized by taking the derivative of the interesting variable and, taking into account the decrease, one can use the negative first derivative of the specific speed S ' :</p>
		<p>The dependence of S' on the temperature T for a sucrose solution (<measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>W/W) and a P-85 solution (<measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>W/W) is shown in F i g. 2 .</p>
		<p>F+g. 2: Change of the specific speed of sound waves S' as a functlon of the temperature T for <measure type="list"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure>sucrose (xxx) and <num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>P-85 (+++).</p>
		<p>The solution with sucrose shows a monotonically decreasing behaviour, i. e., there is only a slight change of the specific speed with temperature. The curve for the P-85 solution is quite different. It matches the sucrose curve only at low and high temperatures. Deviations from the temperature behavior of sucrose starting at about <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">aC</measure></measure><!--OCR problem °C not aC (Electric charge)-->, show a clear maximum (highest micelle formation rate) at <measure type="value"><num>29</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure></measure> and vanish at about <measure type="value"><num>45</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure></measure>. This indicates that the formation of micelles essentially starts at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure> and is finished at <num atMost="45">45</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>with a maximum in the formation rate at <measure type="value"><num>29</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. We can also see from this figure that the magnitude of the effects depend on the chosen sample. We get a much higher signal for a <measure type="value"><num>5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>P-85 solution than for a <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>sucrose solution.</p>
		<p>The influence of a varying concentration of P-85 is given in the F i g s . 3 and 4. The signal has been divided by the concentration in order to scale the curves. <!-- case not supported --><!-- From F i g. 3 we can see that the maximum formation rate of micelles is shifted from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="26">26</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure> at <measure type="value"><num>10</num><measure type="FRACTION">%</measure></measure> to <num atMost="15">15</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure> at <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure></measure>.  -->We also see the nonlinearity of the effect for concentrations higher than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> P-85. With decreasing concentration we have a constantly decreasing signal with an increase of the relative error. The effect of micellization can be measured nicely at concentrations as small as <measure type="value"><num>0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> (see Fig. 4). We have performed experiments at even lower concentrations. There is still a significant peak at the micellization temperature, but more sophisticated data manipulations (smoothing) and repeated experiments would be necessary at concentrations lower than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="0.5">0.5</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>.</p>
		<p>It can be concluded from the above results, that SSW experiments can be used to follow micellization. The resulting change in the specific speed of the sound waves indicates and covers the temperature regime where the micellization takes place. The maximum of this formation curve can be used as a parameter for a mean micellization temperature. The fact that it is really a micellization that takes place cannot be found from such experiments. For this purpose it is still necessary to perform some, much more time consuming, scattering experiments.</p>
		<p>Precision densitometry uses the mechanical oscillator method <!-- / 3 , 4 / -->. This method is based on the measurement of the eigenfrequency of a Ushaped glass tube filled with the sample. In the standard setup (DMA 58, A. PAAR K.G., Graz, Aus-tria) the external force is of the same amplitude as the damping force but phase shifted by <measure type="value"><num>180</num><measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">degrees</measure></measure> to maintain steady oscillation. Such a mechanically driven oscillation can be represented by the external force F , and the following <measure type="value"><num>three</num></measure> internal forces: the elastic spring force which is proportional to the dislocation x of the mass cx (c is the spring constant), the damping force (energy absorbing) which is proportional to the velocity x' of the mass bx' (b is the damping constant) and the mass force which is proportio-nal to the acceleration mx&quot; of the mass m of the system <!-- /7/ -->. The external force F , must compensate the damping force, i.e., it must be equal to-bx'. Such a system with synchronized external force will perform a steady harmonic oscillation with a dislocation This situation is visualized in Fig. 5. We call this operation mode, where the external force is balancing the damping force, in phase mode. Here we are not further interested in the well known details of densitometry, but we have to discuss the modifications that allow the qualitative determination of the damping force (viscosity) with such a densitometer. Actually it can be shown that it is possible to measure the ratio between the damping force and the spring force utilizing a second experiment with a phase shifted mode. In this mode the external force Fen is shifted by <measure type="value"><num>45</num> <measure type="ANGLE" unit="°">degrees</measure></measure>. The amplitude is increased so that-.&quot;C;1 the component in direction of the damping force remains constant (see In this mode we observe a different frequency a , or period T,. Combining the <measure type="value"><num>two</num></measure>corresponding differential equations we get</p>
		<p>We see that the ratio DR between the damping force and the spring force is simply related to the oscillating periods. This function runs through a maximum at r]' (see Fig. 7) and goes to <measure type="value"><num>zero</num></measure>at high values of r ] , where the fluid is no longer streaming in the tube but acts like a stiff rod. The value v* is about <measure type="value"><num>100</num><measure type="DYNAMIC_VISCOSITY" unit="mPa.s">mPa.s</measure></measure> in the basic mode (or fundamental mode, frequency w,) of the oscillator. The maximum 7' <!--OCR error not 7-->can be shifted to about <measure type="value"><num>600</num><measure type="DYNAMIC_VISCOSITY" unit="mPa">mPa.s</measure></measure> if the first order mode oscillation (frequency ul) of the tube is excited, but this does not change the situation essentially. This means that this technique is not suited to &quot;measure&quot; viscosity qualitatively in a wide range. We have to keep in mind these facts when we discuss the results from gelation data, where the viscosity increases in a sharp transition over many orders of magnitude. The advantage of the densitometer method lies in the facts that only a small amount of sample ( * <measure type="value"><num>1</num><measure type="VOLUME" unit="ml">ml</measure></measure>) is simply filled in a well thermostated and closed glass tube and that only a negligible energy input into the sample takes place (extremely low shear strain). More difficult is the relation between this ratio (mostly depending on the damping force with a quasi constant spring force) and the viscosity r ]. There is a linear dependence for small values of fi .</p>
		<p>The P-85 solution is a fluid with low viscosity at low temperatures and at low concentrations. At concentrations lower than <measure type="interval"><num atMost="20">20</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>W/W there is a weak temperature dependence up to <measure type="interval"><num atMost="60">60</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure></measure> as we can see from Fig. 8 for experiments using basic mode oscillation. <!-- case not supported: interval bounded by interval --><!-- The damping ratio (the values for water have been subtracted) decreases slightly from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="5">5</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure> up to at least <num atMost="60">60</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>.  -->Then follows a constant increase up to the maximum measured temperature from <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="70">70</num> to <num atMost="78">78</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. A gel phase with moderate viscosity exists in this high temperature regime and the transition is not sharp. This behaviour is also found by oscillatory shear experiments.</p>
		<p>At concentrations of <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="25">25</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> and more exists a gel phase with very high viscosity and sharp boundaries in a certain temperature interval1 around <!-- question, interval with base without range possible? --><measure type="value"><num>4 0</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">&quot; ~</measure></measure><!--OCR error-->. The width of this regime increases with concentration. If we take for example a concentration of <measure type="value"><num>25</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>, we see a slight increase of the damping ratio (i.e. viscosity) between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="20">20</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure> and <num atMost="30">30</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure></measure>. At <measure type="value"><num>31</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> the gel is formed. It has such a high viscosity ( 7 &gt;&gt; 7 '<!--OCR error--> ) that the damping ratio is smaller than the one for water (negative values). The stiff gel is dissolved again between <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="50">50</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure> and <num atMost="52">52</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure>. The regime of the stiff gel is much wider for the <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure> solution, where it starts at <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="23">23</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure> and ends above <num atMost="61">61</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">'C</measure></measure>. The anomaleous behavior of the <measure type="value"><num>30</num><measure type="FRACTION" unit="%">%</measure></measure>solution at temperatures higher than <measure type="interval"><num atLeast="65">65</num><measure type="TEMPERATURE" unit="°C">°C</measure></measure> is not yet studied in detail.</p>
		<p>1 .oo If we use the first order mode of oscillation, we have to expect a higher damping ratio due to its linear dependence on the frequency o (o, * 600)<!-- OCR error --> and a wider range of measurable ratios as 7 '<!--not 7--> increases. So it is possible to measure higher damping ratios at the sharp phase boundaries of the stiff gel (see Fig. 9).</p>
		<p>Densitometry has proved to be a new and complementary method to follow qualitatively changes in the viscosity of a fluid with minimum energy input into the sample and small volume. Excellent temperature control is guaranteed. Formation and dissolution of gels in P-85 solutions can nicely be detected. Calibration techniques may allow quantitative experiments in the future. I thank the Labor fur Messtechnik Dr. Hans Stabinger and his coworkers for technical assistance and fruitful discussions.</p>
	</text>
</tei>